[
    {
        "answer": "require",
        "question": "нуждаться (в чём-л.); требовать (чего-л.)",
        "explanation": "[verb] Require means to need. You require food, water, and shelter to live, but do you really require that new pair of high-fashion shoes? Require is used especially in written English. In everyday English, people usually say \"need\".",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Campbell’s broken leg will probably require surgery.",
            "Most houseplants require regular watering."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "imagination",
        "question": "воображение",
        "explanation": "[noun] the part of your mind that creates ideas or pictures of things that are not real or that you have not seen",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "There's nothing out here- it's just your imagination."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "yesterday",
        "question": "вчера",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "it is not true",
        "question": "это неправда",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am in the third year",
        "question": "я учусь на третьем курсе",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "royal",
        "question": "королевский",
        "explanation": "[adjective] relating to a queen or king and their family",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the British royal family"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "How much does it weigh?",
        "question": "Сколько это весит?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Pomegranate",
        "question": "гранат",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "an expert in marketing",
        "question": "специалист по маркетингу",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "interior",
        "question": "внутренняя часть, интерьер",
        "explanation": "the inner part or inside of something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The interior of the church was dark."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i have arrived with my wife and children",
        "question": "я приехал с женой и детьми",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ginger",
        "question": "имбирь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "receipt",
        "question": "квитанция, чек",
        "explanation": "[noun] a piece of paper that you are given which shows that you have paid for something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Keep your receipt in case you want to bring it back.",
            "Make sure you get receipts for everything.",
            "Can you give me a receipt?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "five minutes past eight",
        "question": "8.05- пять минут девятого",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "observation",
        "question": "наблюдение",
        "explanation": "[noun] the process of watching something or someone carefully for a period of time",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The doctor wants to keep him under observation for a week.",
            "From their direct observations, children absorb a model of marriage."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "prohibit",
        "question": "запрещать (action)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to say officially that an action is illegal and make a law or rule about this",
        "source": "software testing: a craftsman's approach",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Smoking is prohibited on most international flights."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Strawberry",
        "question": "клубника",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is a small world!",
        "question": "мир тесен!",
        "explanation": "said to show your surprise that people or events in different places are connected",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It is a small world!",
            "You know my old science teacher! Well, it's a small world, isn't it?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "can you speak russian?",
        "question": "вы говорите по-русски?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "skill",
        "question": "мастерство, навык",
        "explanation": "[noun] an ability to do something well, especially because you have learned and practised it",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Reading and writing are two different skills."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "It is driving rain.",
        "question": "Идёт проливной дождь.",
        "explanation": "driving rain (=heavy rain that is falling fast or being blown along)",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "They struggled to walk against driving rain."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "motor",
        "question": "двигатель",
        "explanation": "[noun] the part of a machine that makes it work or move, by changing power, especially electrical power, into movement",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an electric motor"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Is it too far to go on foot?",
        "question": "Это далеко пешком?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "mother",
        "question": "мама",
        "explanation": "[noun] a female parent of a child or animal",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "His mother and father are both doctors.",
            "Janet is a full-time teacher and a mother of two."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "ice",
        "question": "лед",
        "explanation": "[noun] water that has frozen and become solid",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Gerry slipped on the ice and broke his arm."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "cultural",
        "question": "культурный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] relating to the habits, traditions, and beliefs of a society",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "cultural diversity/identity"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Yesterday, I met one of my friends.",
        "question": "Вчера, я встретил одного из моих друзей.",
        "explanation": "The general rule for usage of the phrase \"one of the\" is: One of the+ PLURAL NOUN+ that/who etc.+ SINGULAR/PLURAL VERB. So, the noun following the phrase \"one of the\" is always a plural noun, whereas use of verbs as singular or plural will entirely depend upon the subject of the statement, i.e. singular verb for singular subject and plural verb for plural subject.",
        "source": "Spaced rehearsal program readme.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "passion fruit",
        "question": "маракуйя",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "an honest answer",
        "question": "честный ответ (with an article)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sail",
        "question": "совершать плавание (to travel in a boat or a ship)",
        "explanation": "to travel on or across an area of water in a boat or ship",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She always wanted to sail around the world."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "where do you work?",
        "question": "где вы работаете?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "they are there to pay homage, to share in these last moments, a final farewell to this legendary artist",
        "question": "они там, чтобы отдать дань уважения, разделить в эти последние минуты, окончательное прощание с этим легендарным художником",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "Operating Systems: Three Easy Pieces",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "august car sales fell short of the industry's expectations",
        "question": "августовские продажи автомобилей не оправдали ожиданий отрасли",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "Operating Systems: Three Easy Pieces",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "yeast",
        "question": "дрожжи",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "May I settle my bill, please? I would like to check out.",
        "question": "[Hotel] Могу ли я оплатить счет, пожалуйста? Я хочу выехать.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "translate",
        "question": "переводить (с одного языка на другой)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to change written or spoken words into another language",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Translate the text from Italian into English."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "schoolboy",
        "question": "школьник",
        "explanation": "a boy attending school",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "moisturizing cream",
        "question": "увлажняющий крем",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "pliers",
        "question": "щипцы́; кле́щи́; плоскогу́бцы",
        "explanation": "[noun, plural] a small tool made of two crossed pieces of metal, used to hold small things or to bend and cut wire",
        "source": "Genetic algorithms with python",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a pair of pliers"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i work at a hospital",
        "question": "я работаю в больнице",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "what do you do?",
        "question": "кем вы работаете?",
        "explanation": "\"What do you do\" is a way to ask someone what their job is or what they do for a living. It is a polite question to ask when you first meet someone, or when you are getting to know someone new, or when you haven't seen someone for a long time.",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "May",
        "question": "май",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am sorry",
        "question": "прошу прощения",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "muddled thinking",
        "question": "размышление, в котором не достает логики",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "Fundamental Concepts in Programming Languages - paper",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "The buses run every half an hour.",
        "question": "каждые полчаса ходят автобусы (article: the)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I will be back in half an hour.",
        "question": "Я вернусь через полчаса",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "child",
        "question": "ребенок",
        "explanation": "[noun] a young person who is not yet an adult",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an eight-year-old child",
            "How many children are there in your class?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "How high can you jump?",
        "question": "Как высоко вы можете прыгать?",
        "explanation": "[jump] to push yourself up into the air, or over or away from something etc, using your legs",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "news",
        "question": "новости",
        "explanation": "[noun] information about something that has happened recently",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I hope to have some good news for you soon.",
            "What’s the latest news on your university application?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my mother-in-law",
        "question": "это моя свекровь/тёща",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "shrine",
        "question": "храм, святыня",
        "explanation": "[noun] a place where people go to pray because it is connected with a holy person or event",
        "source": "Living with the gods: the protectoresses",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "life",
        "question": "[жизнь] the period of time when someone is alive",
        "explanation": "Your life is the time from your birth to your death.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "You have your whole life ahead of you."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "library",
        "question": "библиотека",
        "explanation": "[noun] a room or building containing books that can be looked at or borrowed",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a public library"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "go up the stairs",
        "question": "Поднимитесь вверх по лестнице",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "call me. my telephone number is",
        "question": "позвоните мне. мой телефонный номер",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "window",
        "question": "окно",
        "explanation": "[a space or an area of glass in the wall of a building or vehicle that lets in light] She looked out of the window to see if it was raining.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "smuggler",
        "question": "контрабандист",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone who takes something illegally from one country to another",
        "source": "The Documentary podcast: Escaping europe.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a drug smuggler"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "light- heavy",
        "question": "легкий- тяжелый",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "new",
        "question": "новый",
        "explanation": "[adjective] recently made, built, invented, written, designed etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the city’s new hospital",
            "I need some new shoes."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i have a new address. please, write it down",
        "question": " у меня новый адрес.  пожалуйста, запишите",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "satisfaction",
        "question": "удовлетворение",
        "explanation": "a feeling of happiness or pleasure because you have achieved something or got what you wanted",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She got great satisfaction from helping people to learn."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "If I remember rightly",
        "question": "если я правильно помню",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "decay",
        "question": "гнить, разлагаться (об органических веществах)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to be slowly destroyed by a natural chemical process, or to make something do this",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "decaying leaves",
            "Sugar makes your teeth decay."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "let me introduce you to my husband",
        "question": "разрешите представить вам моего мужа (официальная форма)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "please, meet my friend",
        "question": "разрешите представить вам моего друга (неофициальная форма)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "iron",
        "question": "утюг",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "second",
        "question": "секунда",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "next week",
        "question": "на следующей недели",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Would you like to listen to that again?",
        "question": "Вы хотите послушать это снова?",
        "explanation": "We use “would like” or “‘d like to” to say politely what we want, especially when making offers or requests. Verbs that follow would like are in the to-infinitive form.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "prevailing",
        "question": "господствующий, широко распространенный",
        "explanation": "[adjective]",
        "source": "code complete by steve mcconnell",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "handrail",
        "question": "поручень",
        "explanation": "[noun] A handrail is a long piece of metal or wood which is fixed near stairs or places where people could slip and fall, and which people can hold on to for support.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "artificial",
        "question": "искусственный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] not natural, but made by people",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an artificial flower/lake",
            "an artificial heart"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "abdicate responsibility",
        "question": "слагать полномочия",
        "explanation": "[verb]",
        "source": "Word smart.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the government was accused of abdicating its responsibility."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "regret",
        "question": "сожаление",
        "explanation": "sadness that you feel about something, especially because you wish it had not happened",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I have no regrets about leaving.",
            "She has already expressed deep regret for what happened."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "him",
        "question": "rodney fell off his board and landed on you and (he/him)",
        "explanation": "The hide-and-seek technique. The stand-in has to make sense all by itself.",
        "source": "Woe is I Jr",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sculptor",
        "question": "скульптор",
        "explanation": "an artist who makes sculptures.",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "light- dark",
        "question": "светлый- темный",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "What is the best way to explain ...?",
        "question": "Какой наилучший способ объяснить ...?",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "zeal",
        "question": "рвение",
        "explanation": "[noun] great energy or enthusiasm in pursuit of a cause or an objective",
        "source": "Word smart.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Laura brought a missionary zeal to her work."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "we regret it so much",
        "question": "мы очень сожалеем",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "fatal crash",
        "question": "авария со смертельным исходом",
        "explanation": "in which someone is killed",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "There have been several fatal crashes on this road."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "tongue",
        "question": "язык (анатомия)",
        "explanation": "[noun] the soft thing inside your mouth that you move and use for tasting and speaking",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The taste of the chocolate was still on her tongue."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "message",
        "question": "сообщение",
        "explanation": "[noun] a spoken or written piece of information that you send to another person or leave for them",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He left a message saying he would probably be a little late.",
            "Did you get my message?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "various",
        "question": "различный, разный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] if there are various things, there are several different types of that thing",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The jacket is available in various colours.",
            "There are various ways to answer your question."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i study at a community college.",
        "question": "я учусь в муниципальном колледже.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I have stayed here for a week.",
        "question": "Я пробыл здесь неделю.",
        "explanation": "\"for\"- used to say how long an action or situation continues for.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "down jacket",
        "question": "пуховик",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "equipment",
        "question": "оборудование, оснащение",
        "explanation": "[noun] the things that are used for a particular activity or purpose",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "kitchen/office equipment",
            "electrical equipment (= equipment that uses electricity)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "almond",
        "question": "миндальный орех",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "If I am not mistaken",
        "question": "если я не ошибаюсь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "criticism",
        "question": "критика",
        "explanation": "[noun] remarks saying that something or someone is bad",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Plans to close the hospital attracted strong public criticism."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "rural",
        "question": "сельский, деревенский",
        "explanation": "happening in or relating to the countryside, not the city",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "rural bus routes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "photographer",
        "question": "фотограф",
        "explanation": "a person who takes photographs, especially as a job",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "so as to",
        "question": "так чтобы, для того чтобы",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "bane",
        "question": "бич (что или кто вызывает несчастья, бедствия, приносит неприятности, огорчения и.т.п.)",
        "explanation": "[noun] something that causes trouble or makes people unhappy. The noun bane refers to anything that is a cause of harm, ruin, or death. But we often use it for things that aren't that bad, just feel like it. You might say mosquitoes are the bane of your existence.",
        "source": "word smart",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Drugs are the bane of the inner cities.",
            "The Morning After Hangovers are the bane of drinkers."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "arrest",
        "question": "арестовывать",
        "explanation": "[verb] If the police arrest someone, they take them away to ask them about a crime that they might have committed.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He was arrested for possession of illegal drugs."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "not bad",
        "question": "неплохо",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "lamb",
        "question": "молодая баранина (ягненок, мясо)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "just punishment",
        "question": "справедливое наказание",
        "explanation": "[adjective] appropriate and right",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Death would be a just punishment."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "garbage",
        "question": "мусор",
        "explanation": "[noun] things that you throw away because you do not want them",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Can you take out the garbage when you go?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "tantalize",
        "question": "дразнить ложными надеждами",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "Living With The Gods (bbc radio 4)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "servant",
        "question": "слуга, служанка",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone who works and lives in someone else's house doing their cooking and cleaning, especially in the past",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "poultry",
        "question": "мясо птицы",
        "explanation": "[noun] the meat of chickens and other birds eaten as food",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "mention",
        "question": "упоминать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to talk or write about something or someone, usually quickly and without saying very much or giving details",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Was my name mentioned at all?",
            "She didn't mention her daughter."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "underpass",
        "question": "подземный переход",
        "explanation": "a road or path that goes under another road or a railway",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "comply with requirements",
        "question": "соблюдать требования",
        "explanation": "[verb] have or do what a rule or law says is necessary",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Failure to comply with these requirements is a criminal offence."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "ambulance",
        "question": "машина скорой помощи",
        "explanation": "[noun] a vehicle that takes people to hospital when they are sick or hurt",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The ambulance crew removed him from the wreckage."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "what a pity!",
        "question": "как жаль!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "That is news to me.",
        "question": "Это новость для меня.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "exhaust",
        "question": "истощать, исчерпывать",
        "explanation": "[verb] [supply] to finish all of the supply of something",
        "source": "From Frequency to Meaning: Vector Space Models of Semantics.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "How long will it be before the world's fuel supplies are exhausted?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "folk song",
        "question": "народная песня",
        "explanation": "The students played guitars and sang folk songs.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "chocolate",
        "question": "шоколад",
        "explanation": "[noun] a sweet brown food that you can eat as a sweet or use in cooking to give foods such as cakes a special sweet taste",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a chocolate bar",
            "a chocolate cake"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "abdicate",
        "question": "отрекаться от престола, власти",
        "explanation": "[verb] (of a monarch) renounce one's throne",
        "source": "Word smart.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "in 1918 Kaiser Wilhelm abdicated as German emperor",
            "Ferdinand abdicated the throne in favour of the emperor's brother."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "half an hour",
        "question": "полчаса",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "mail",
        "question": "почта",
        "explanation": "[noun] the letters and packages that are delivered to you",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "You shouldn't read other people's mail."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "punch",
        "question": "бить кулаком",
        "explanation": "[verb] to hit someone or something hard with your fist (=closed hand)",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He punched Jack in the face.",
            "He punched me and knocked my teeth out."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am twenty-four",
        "question": "мне двадцать четыре года",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "pepper",
        "question": "перец",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "may i offer you an ice cream?",
        "question": "можно предложить вам мороженое?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "crash victim",
        "question": "пострадавший в аварии (жертва аварии)",
        "explanation": "someone injured or killed in a crash",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Families of the crash victims want to know what happened."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "can you keep me company?",
        "question": "вы можете составить мне компанию?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "chop",
        "question": "нарезать, шинковать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to cut something into small pieces",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Chop an onion finely."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "ivory",
        "question": "слоновая кость",
        "explanation": "a hard yellowish-white substance like bone that forms the ↑tusks (= long teeth) of ↑elephants and some other animals. tusk - бивень",
        "source": "Living With The Gods (bbc radio 4)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "alive",
        "question": "живой",
        "explanation": "[adjective] living, not dead",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Are your grandparents still alive?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "can you speak french?",
        "question": "вы говорите по-французски?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "invite",
        "question": "приглашать",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Invite someone to come to a party next Friday."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "voters fall into three main categories.",
        "question": "избиратели делятся на три основные категории.",
        "explanation": null,
        "source": "",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "bliss",
        "question": "a state of complete (extreme) happiness or joy; блажество",
        "explanation": "The first six months of marriage were sheer bliss",
        "source": "",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Is this far away?",
        "question": "Это далеко?",
        "explanation": "Far away indicates something or someone that is far from something else, and implies two points, a here, and a 'there' being referred to. Far however is more general and can be used in more cases, e.g \"He went far in his studies\".",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "the vast majority",
        "question": "подавляющее большинство",
        "explanation": "used when you want to emphasize that something is true about almost all of a group of people or things",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "That's why the vast majority of users are attracted to Microsoft Windows by its very simplicity."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "permanent employee",
        "question": "постоянный сотрудник (штатный сотрудник)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "pork",
        "question": "свинина (мясо)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "transparent",
        "question": "прозрачный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] if something is transparent, you can see through it",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a transparent plastic container"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "spell",
        "question": "писать орфографически правильно",
        "explanation": "[verb] If you can spell, you know how to write the words of a language correctly.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "My grammar's all right, but I can't spell."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "strip of cloth",
        "question": "полоска ткани",
        "explanation": "[strip] a long narrow piece of cloth, paper etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The leather had been cut into strips."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "juice",
        "question": "сок",
        "explanation": "[noun] the liquid that comes from fruit and vegetables, or a drink that is made from this",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "A Coke and a tomato juice, please."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "tarnish reputation",
        "question": "запятнать (порочить) репутацию",
        "explanation": "[verb] =make it worse",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He said Thomas was drunk, and that if anyone found out, it would tarnish his reputation."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Sorry? What was that again?",
        "question": "Извините? Что вы сказали?",
        "explanation": "sorry? spoken used to ask someone to repeat something that you have not heard properly (syn. pardon)",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "‘Want a drink?’ ‘Sorry?’ ‘I said, would you like a drink?’"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "amuse",
        "question": "смешить",
        "explanation": "[verb] to make someone smile or laugh",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He made funny faces to amuse the children.",
            "The question seemed to amuse him in some way."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "extract a tooth",
        "question": "вырвать зуб",
        "explanation": "take it out",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The dentist announced that she would have to extract two teeth."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Excuse me, could you let me through",
        "question": "Извините, не могли бы вы пропустить меня.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "journalist",
        "question": "журналист",
        "explanation": "a person who writes for newspapers, magazines, or news websites or prepares news to be broadcast",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "How is it going?",
        "question": "Как идут дела?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "top",
        "question": "верх, верхняя часть",
        "explanation": "[noun] the highest part of something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "They were waiting for him at the top of the stairs.",
            "I want a cake with cherries on top."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "special attention",
        "question": "особое внимание",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "language",
        "question": "язык, речь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Excuse me, could you let me out",
        "question": "Извините, не могли бы вы выпустить меня.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "huge impact",
        "question": "огромное воздействие",
        "explanation": "[[impact]] an effect that happens as a result of something important, especially a big and permanent effect",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "week",
        "question": "неделя",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "She knew we could not afford two rooms.",
        "question": "Она знала, что мы не можем позволить себе два номера.",
        "explanation": "[verb] To afford means you have enough money or time for something. If you only have ten dollars on you, you can't afford to buy a twenty-dollar hat. Afford is a verb that has to do with means. You either have a surplus and therefore can afford something, or else you have a deficit and can’t. It can be in the monetary sense: \"$100 for cashmere socks? I can’t afford that!” It can also refer to time: “Since my train wasn't scheduled to leave for another hour, I could afford to wait for my sister ten more minutes.” Or even access: “The castle walls afforded a wonderful view of the moat.”",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "tower",
        "question": "башня",
        "explanation": "[noun] a very tall, narrow building, or part of a building",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a church tower",
            "the Eiffel Tower"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "day",
        "question": "сутки",
        "explanation": "the 24 hours between one midnight and the next",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "recent",
        "question": "недавний",
        "explanation": "[adjective] having happened or started only a short time ago",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Irving’s most recent book",
            "a recent photo"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "happy new year!",
        "question": "с новым годом!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "deep- shallow",
        "question": "глубокий- мелкий",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "pace",
        "question": "шаг; длина шага",
        "explanation": "[noun] a single step when you are running or walking, or the distance you move in one step",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He took a pace towards the door.",
            "Every few paces I stopped to listen."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "lime",
        "question": "лайм",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "she emptied a bucket of water over them",
        "question": "она вылела ведро воды на них",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "Environment around you",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Let's get the coffee to go.",
        "question": "Пошли возьмем кофе с собой.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "owe",
        "question": "быть должным, задолжать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to have to pay money back to someone",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "You still owe me money.",
            "He owes a lot of money to the bank."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "awfully",
        "question": "ужасно",
        "explanation": "[adverb] very",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It’s awfully cold in here. Is the heater on?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sentence",
        "question": "(судебный) приговор",
        "explanation": "[noun] a punishment that a judge gives to someone who has committed a crime",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He was given a long prison sentence."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i regret it so much",
        "question": "я очень сожалею",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "discrepancy",
        "question": "расхождение, несоответствие",
        "explanation": "[noun] a difference between two things that should be the same",
        "source": "software testing: a craftsman's approach",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "There is a slight discrepancy between the two statements.",
            "Police found discrepancies in the two men’s reports."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "rumour",
        "question": "слух, молва",
        "explanation": "information or a story that is passed from one person to another and which may or may not be true",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I heard a rumour that you were leaving."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "please, meet my girlfriend",
        "question": "разрешите представить вам мою подругу (неофициальная форма)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i work at a publishing house",
        "question": "я работаю в издательстве",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "We play",
        "question": "Мы играем. (Present Simple)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "valid",
        "question": "юр. действительный, имеющий силу; (о документе, соглашении, итд.)",
        "explanation": "[adjective] a valid ticket, document, or agreement is legally or officially acceptable",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a valid credit card",
            "Your return ticket is valid for three months."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "seal",
        "question": "тюлень",
        "explanation": "[noun] an animal with smooth fur that eats fish and lives near the sea",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I wrote the novel with relish.",
        "question": "Я с наслаждением писал эту повесть. (the novel)",
        "explanation": "[noun] great enjoyment of something",
        "source": "The Documentary: Reformation 500",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I ate with great relish, enjoying every bite."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "curtain",
        "question": "портьера",
        "explanation": "[noun] a piece of hanging cloth that can be pulled across to cover a window, divide a room etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "red velvet curtains"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i cannot speak english",
        "question": "я не говорю по-английски",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "assist",
        "question": "помогать, содействовать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to help",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The army arrived to assist in the search.",
            "He's assisting the police with their investigation."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "you are always welcome",
        "question": "всегда пожалуйста",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "back",
        "question": "обратно",
        "explanation": "[adverb] where someone or something was before",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "When do you go back to college?",
            "I put it back in the cupboard."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "by March",
        "question": "к марту",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I objected to having to rewrite the article.",
        "question": "Я возражал против необходимости переписывать статью.",
        "explanation": "You object to something",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "aunt",
        "question": "тетя",
        "explanation": "[noun] the sister of your mother or father, or the wife of your uncle",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Jerome has an aunt and uncle in Laguna Hills and some relatives in South Dakota."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Do not take it to heart.",
        "question": "Не принимайте близко к сердцу.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Money is being raised to build a new sports facility.",
        "question": "Деньги собираются для строительства нового спортивного сооружения.",
        "explanation": "[noun] a place or building used for a particular activity or industry, or for providing a particular type of service",
        "source": "The Oxford 3000",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a top-secret research facility",
            "the finest indoor sports facility in the US"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "psychiatrist",
        "question": "психиатр",
        "explanation": "a medical practitioner specializing in the diagnosis and treatment of mental illness",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "craft workshop",
        "question": "ремесленная мастерская",
        "explanation": "place where a craftsman or woman works",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "curtain pole",
        "question": "карниз (Перекладина над окном, на к-рую вешают шторы.)",
        "explanation": "a long stick for hanging a curtain",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a curtain rail/pole/rod",
            "Velvet can be heavy so choose a strong curtain pole."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "crop",
        "question": "сельскохозяйственная культура",
        "explanation": "[noun] a plant such as wheat, rice, or fruit that is grown by farmers and used as food",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The main crops were oats and barley."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Why do not you come over for dinner tomorrow?",
        "question": "Почему бы тебе не прийти к нам на ужин завтра?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "crime",
        "question": "преступность, преступление",
        "explanation": "illegal activities in general",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We moved here because there was very little crime."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "representative of a firm",
        "question": "представитель фирмы",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "his name is",
        "question": "его зовут",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "in three hours",
        "question": "через три часа",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "it is a long time since i saw you last!",
        "question": "как давно мы не виделись!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "the tail section of an aircraft",
        "question": "хвостовая часть самолета",
        "explanation": "[section] (часть, отдел, секция) one of the parts that something such as an object or place is divided into",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a busy section of road",
            "the smoking section (=where you can smoke)",
            "the business section of a newspaper"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "a carton of orange juice",
        "question": "пакет апельсинового сока. (article: a)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I am a foreigner",
        "question": "Я иностранец.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "survey",
        "question": "опрос общественного мнения",
        "explanation": "[noun] an examination of people's opinions or behaviour made by asking people questions",
        "source": "From Frequency to Meaning: Vector Space Models of Semantics.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Holidays in the UK are becoming more popular, according to a recent survey.",
            "We conducted a survey of parents in the village."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "pupil",
        "question": "ученик",
        "explanation": "[noun] a student at school",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The school has 1,100 pupils aged 11 to 18."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "imaginary",
        "question": "мнимый, вымышленный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] not real but imagined in your mind",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The story takes place in an imaginary world."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "crash into",
        "question": "врезаться в",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The plane crashed into a mountain."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "editor",
        "question": "редактор",
        "explanation": "a person who is in charge of and determines the final content of a newspaper, magazine, or multi-author book",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "soup",
        "question": "суп",
        "explanation": "[noun] a hot, liquid food, made from vegetables, meat, or fish",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "chicken/tomato soup"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "automatic",
        "question": "автоматический",
        "explanation": "[adjective] An automatic machine works by itself or with little human control.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "automatic doors"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "ruined castle",
        "question": "Разрушенный замок (почти до основания)",
        "explanation": "[[ruined] a ruined building has been almost completely destroyed]",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Tomorrow it will be rainy.",
        "question": "Завтра будет дождливо.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "just for the record",
        "question": "просто к сведению; так, для справки",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "after all",
        "question": "в итоге; все-таки",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "rescue team",
        "question": "спасательная команда",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "need",
        "question": "надобность",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "twin",
        "question": "близнец",
        "explanation": "[noun] one of two children born at the same time to the same mother",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The twins are now eight months old."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "derelict",
        "question": "[прилагательное] брошенный, бесхозный (особенно о суши и строениях)",
        "explanation": "[adjective] A place or building that is derelict is empty and in a bad state of repair because it has not been used or lived in for a long time.",
        "source": "100 Words Every Fourth Grader Should Know",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The derelict garage was finally torn down.",
            "a derelict Georgian mansion"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "bilberry",
        "question": "черника",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "obey",
        "question": "слушаться",
        "explanation": "[verb] to do what someone in authority tells you to do, or what a law or rule says you must do",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The little boy made no effort to obey.",
            "‘Sit!’ he said, and the dog obeyed him instantly."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "it seems to me that you are not right",
        "question": "мне кажется, что вы не правы",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "tonne",
        "question": "метрическая тонна (единица массы в метрической системе мер;= 1000 кг)",
        "explanation": "[noun] a unit for measuring weight, equal to 1,000 kilograms",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sympathy",
        "question": "сочувствие",
        "explanation": "feelings of pity and sorrow for someone else's misfortune",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "they had great sympathy for the flood victims."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "white bread",
        "question": "белый хлеб",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I have lost my way.",
        "question": "Я заблудился.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "signboard",
        "question": "Вывеска",
        "explanation": "a board displaying the name or logo of a business or product: a shop with its name painted on a signboard over the door",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "eventually",
        "question": "в конце концов",
        "explanation": "[adverb] after a long time, or after a lot of things have happened",
        "source": "Booking review",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He eventually escaped and made his way back to England.",
            "Eventually, she got a job and moved to London."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "today",
        "question": "сегодня",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ingredient",
        "question": "ингредиент",
        "explanation": "[noun] one of the foods that you use to make a particular food or dish",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Combine all the ingredients in a large bowl.",
            "The food is home-cooked using fresh ingredients."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "chip",
        "question": "ломтик жареного картофеля",
        "explanation": "[noun] a long, thin piece of potato that is cooked in oil",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "fish and chips"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "you are right",
        "question": "вы правы",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ad hoc",
        "question": "по мере необходимости",
        "explanation": "created or done for a particular purpose as necessary: We meet on an ad hoc basis.",
        "source": "Fundamental Concepts in Programming Languages - paper",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "weigh",
        "question": "взвешивать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to measure how heavy someone or something is",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Can you weigh that piece of cheese for me?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "may i offer you a glass of wine?",
        "question": "можно предложить вам рюмку вина?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "could not you",
        "question": "не могли бы вы",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Have you ironed my shirt?",
        "question": "Вы гладили мою рубашку?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I am leaving tomorrow morning.",
        "question": "Я уезжаю завтра утром.",
        "explanation": "We use the present continuous to describe an event in the future which has already been arranged by the time of speaking.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "husband",
        "question": "муж",
        "explanation": "[noun] the man you are married to",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "A husband is a married man.",
            "Have you met my husband Roy?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "ultimate customer",
        "question": "конечный потребитель",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "indigenous",
        "question": "туземный, аборигенный, коренной",
        "explanation": "[adjective] indigenous people or things have always been in the place where they are, rather than being brought there from somewhere else",
        "source": "A history of the world in 100 objects.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Blueberries are indigenous to America.",
            "the many indigenous cultures which existed in Siberia"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Sales have been tremendous so far this year.",
        "question": "Продажи в этом году были огромными.",
        "explanation": "[adjective] very large, great, strong, etc",
        "source": "Highlights of Calculus",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a tremendous amount of money",
            "She was making a tremendous effort to appear calm.",
            "She praised her husband for the tremendous support he had given her."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i have arrived with my wife",
        "question": "я приехал с женой",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "pilot",
        "question": "лётчик",
        "explanation": "a person who operates the flying controls of an aircraft",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Days of the week",
        "question": "Дни недели",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "distaste",
        "question": "[существительное] отвращение",
        "explanation": "[noun] mild dislike. A feeling of not liking something. ",
        "source": "100 Words Every Fourth Grader Should Know",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I looked with distaste at the plate of undercooked eggs."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "the agricultural sector of the economy",
        "question": "сельскохозяйственный сектор экономики",
        "explanation": "[sector] (сектор) a part of an area of activity, especially of business, trade etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The country is making efforts to expand such economic sectors as tourism and information technology."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "valley",
        "question": "долина",
        "explanation": "[noun] an area of lower land between two lines of hills or mountains, usually with a river flowing through it",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The route passes through a remote mountain valley."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "absolutely correct",
        "question": "совершенно верно",
        "explanation": "Correct sounds more formal than right. By definition they have the exact same meaning. Modern English, however, is a mash-up of Anglo-Saxon (Old English) and Norman (French), linguists often refer to it as Anglo-Norman English. This gives us many cases of synonymous words such as “trash\"(OE) and \"garbage\"(F) or \"weep\"(OE) and \"cry\"(F). Because the Normans were usually the only ones educated, English words of French origin are often considered to be more technical, thus \"correct\"(F) carries a more definitive implication. Whereas words from the Old English are considered to be more emotional (and therefore found more often in poetry) thus \"right\"(OE) is more often used to imply opinion.",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "rule",
        "question": "правило",
        "explanation": "an official instruction that says how things must be done or what is allowed, especially in a game, organization, or job",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Under the rules, the company must publish its annual accounts."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "ideal",
        "question": "идеальный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] the best or most suitable that something could possibly be",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "advice on how to reach your ideal weight"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "stadium",
        "question": "стадион",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "rose hip",
        "question": "шиповник",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "criterion",
        "question": "критерия",
        "explanation": "[noun][plural: criteria] a fact or level of quality that you use when making a choice or decision",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We have strict criteria for deciding which students will receive a grant."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "envious",
        "question": "завистливый; завидующий",
        "explanation": "[adjective] wanting something that someone else has",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Colleagues were envious of her success."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "crisis",
        "question": "кризис",
        "explanation": "[noun] a situation or time that is extremely dangerous or difficult",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an economic/financial crisis"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "century",
        "question": "столетие",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "island",
        "question": "остров",
        "explanation": "[noun] a piece of land completely surrounded by water",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the Hawaiian Islands"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "dusk",
        "question": "сумерки",
        "explanation": "[noun] Dusk is the time just before night when the daylight has almost gone but when it is not completely dark.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "working the land from dawn to dusk."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "spring",
        "question": "пружина",
        "explanation": "[noun] something, usually a twisted piece of metal, that will return to its previous shape after it has been pressed down",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an old armchair with broken springs"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "debt",
        "question": "долг (денежный)",
        "explanation": "[noun] an amount of money that you owe someone",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She had debts of over £100,000."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "veal",
        "question": "телятина",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "today",
        "question": "сегодняшний день, сегодня",
        "explanation": "[adverb] this day, or on this day",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It's Johann's birthday today.",
            "Today is Friday."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "row of houses",
        "question": "ряд домов",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "weak",
        "question": "слабый",
        "explanation": "[adjective] not physically strong",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He felt too weak to sit up."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "tone",
        "question": "тон, эмоциональная окраска голоса",
        "explanation": "[noun] the way your voice sounds, which shows how you are feeling or what you mean",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "‘You must be Annie, ’ he said in a friendly tone."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "My suitcase was so full I did not have room for anything else.",
        "question": "Мой чемодан был настолько полным, что у меня не было места ни для чего другого.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "bone",
        "question": "[Скелет человека] кость",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "topic",
        "question": "тема",
        "explanation": "[noun] a subject that you talk or write about",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The environment is a popular topic these days."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "net",
        "question": "сеть, сетка (металлическая, проволочная и т. п.)",
        "explanation": "[noun] something used for catching fish, insects, or animals which is made of threads or wires woven across each other with regular spaces between them",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a fishing net"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "reputation",
        "question": "репутация",
        "explanation": "[noun] Your reputation is the general belief or opinion that other people have about you. If you are considered trustworthy and kind, you have a good reputation. Reputation comes from the Latin word reputationem, which means \"consideration.\" It's how people consider, or label, you — good or bad. The noun reputation can also mean \"being known for having a specific skill or characteristic.\" For example, if you have a reputation in snow shoveling, your phone will soon be ringing off the hook with your lazy neighbors calling.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "In her last job she gained a reputation as a hard worker."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "victim",
        "question": "жертва",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone who has been attacked, robbed, or murdered",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "victims of crime"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "please, switch off",
        "question": "пожалуйста, выключите",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sugar bowl",
        "question": "сахарница",
        "explanation": null,
        "source": "A history of the World in 100 objects: Early Victorian tea set",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "west",
        "question": "запад",
        "explanation": "[noun] the direction that you face to see the sun go down",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a village to the west of Brussels"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "February",
        "question": "февраль",
        "explanation": "the coldest February in 40 years",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "move",
        "question": "двигать(ся)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to change place or position, or to make something change place or position",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We moved the chairs to another room.",
            "Someone was moving around upstairs."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Every morning I listen to my Mozart CD while I am having breakfast.",
        "question": "Каждое утро я слушаю мой компакт-диск Моцарта, пока я завтракаю.",
        "explanation": "We use to after listen before an object. We use listen without to if we do not mention the object, or if it is a discourse marker.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Meena, listen! I don’t want you staying out late!",
            "The music was beautiful. We just sat there and listened."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "with the sole purpose of",
        "question": "с единственной целью",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The story was published with the sole purpose of selling newspapers."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "the day before",
        "question": "накануне",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "What movie did you see last night?",
        "question": "Какой фильм вы видели прошлой ночью?",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from. Certainly use which, not what, when there are only two choices, or if both speaker and listener can visualise all the items under consideration.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "triangle",
        "question": "треугольник",
        "explanation": "[noun] a flat shape with three straight sides and three angles",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "to expedite the process",
        "question": "ускорить процесс",
        "explanation": "[verb, formal] to make a process or action happen more quickly SYN speed up",
        "source": "software testing: a craftsman's approach",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "strategies to expedite the decision-making process"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "I did not hear you. Could you please repeat what you said?",
        "question": "Я вас не слышал. Не могли бы вы повторить то, что вы сказали?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "give me, please",
        "question": "дайте мне, пожалуйста (надобность)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "it is impossible",
        "question": "это невозможно",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "assistance",
        "question": "содействие",
        "explanation": "[noun] help",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "financial/medical assistance",
            "Can I be of any assistance? (= Can I help you?)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "So that is where the trouble lies!",
        "question": "Так вот в чем дело!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "good- bad",
        "question": "хороший- плохой",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "credit",
        "question": "похвала, заслуга",
        "explanation": "[verb] approval or praise that you give to someone for something they have done",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Credit for this win goes to everybody in the team."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "to sum up",
        "question": "резюмировать (в конце речи)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "IELTS preparation",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "revival of the economy",
        "question": "оживление (возрождение) экономики",
        "explanation": null,
        "source": "A History of the World in 100 Objects: Early Victorian tea set",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "gooseberry",
        "question": "крыжовник",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "We met on June 20th.",
        "question": "Мы встретились 20 июня.",
        "explanation": "[June] the sixth month of the year, between May and July",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my son-in-law",
        "question": "это мой зять",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "January",
        "question": "январь",
        "explanation": "last January my grandmother died",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "half past eight",
        "question": "8.30- половина девятого",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "intend",
        "question": "намереваться",
        "explanation": "[verb] to have something in your mind as a plan or purpose",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "How long are you intending to stay in Paris?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "attach",
        "question": "прикреплять, присоединять",
        "explanation": "[verb] to join or fix one thing to another",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She attached a photograph to her letter."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Let's hope for the best.",
        "question": "Давай будем надеяться на лучшее.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "the rules of the game",
        "question": "правила игры",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I am up for it.",
        "question": "A different expression to say “I would love to do it”",
        "explanation": "You could also ask somebody: “Are you up for it?” instead of “Do you want to do it?”. It’s a reply to someone who has suggested a particular activity. “I’m up for it!” means “That’s a great idea! Let’s do it!”",
        "source": "Operating systems: three easy pieces.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I am pleased to participate in this class.",
        "question": "Я рад участвовать в этом классе.",
        "explanation": "\"pleased with\" precedes a noun and \"pleased to\" precedes a verb. \"Pleased with\" means I have something that I am pleased to have and \"pleased to\" means I am doing something that I am pleased to do.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I am pleased with my new car.",
            "I am pleased to allow you to drive my new car."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "marsh",
        "question": "болотный",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "chestnut",
        "question": "каштан",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "offer",
        "question": "предлагать",
        "explanation": "[verb] They offered me a job.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "venerate",
        "question": "чтить, почитать",
        "explanation": "[verb, formal] to honour or respect someone or something because they are old, holy, or connected with the past. We don't usually venerate our sweethearts; we often save it for those higher powers, or for remarkable people we're in awe of. Mother Teresa was venerated for her work with the poor, and Gandhi was venerated for his efforts for peace, but most people aren't venerated for normal stuff, like being someone's sweetie.",
        "source": "A history of the world in 100 objects.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Ataturk died in 1938, but he still is widely venerated.",
            "Three other officials of the Old Kingdom came to be venerated as gods because they had been wise, good and successful."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "soon",
        "question": "скоро, вскоре",
        "explanation": "[adverb] after a short period of time",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I've got to leave quite soon.",
            "It's too soon to make a decision."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "car crash",
        "question": "автокатастрофа (автомобильная авария)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He was badly hurt in a car crash."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "dealer",
        "question": "дилер",
        "explanation": "a person who buys and sells goods",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ablution",
        "question": "омовение",
        "explanation": "an act of washing oneself: the women performed their ablutions.",
        "source": "Living with the Gods: Water of Life and Death.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "half-year",
        "question": "полугодие",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "bad",
        "question": "плохой",
        "explanation": "[adjective] unpleasant or likely to cause problems",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The plane was delayed for several hours by bad weather."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "What happens if my luggage gets lost?",
        "question": "Что произойдет если мой багаж потеряется?",
        "explanation": "Luggage is always followed by a singular verb.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "bank employee",
        "question": "банковский служащий",
        "explanation": "employee - a person employed for wages or salary, especially at non-executive level",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "to make a precarious living",
        "question": "жить случайными доходами, кое-как перебиваться",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "Living With The Gods (bbc radio 4)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "beautiful- ugly",
        "question": "красивый- некрасивый",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "give my regards to your wife",
        "question": "передайте привет жене",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "we",
        "question": "мы",
        "explanation": "[pronoun] used as the subject of the verb when the person speaking or writing is referring to themselves and one or more other people",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "My wife and I both play golf and we love it."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Did I get you right?",
        "question": "Я правильно вас понял?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I am pleased with the work I did.",
        "question": "Я доволен работой, которую я сделал. (work)",
        "explanation": "\"pleased with\" precedes a noun and \"pleased to\" precedes a verb. \"Pleased with\" means I have something that I am pleased to have and \"pleased to\" means I am doing something that I am pleased to do.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I am pleased with the gift I received.",
            "I am pleased to give you this gift."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my bride",
        "question": "это моя невеста",
        "explanation": "a woman on her wedding day or just before and after the event",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "twig",
        "question": "веточка",
        "explanation": "[noun] a small very thin branch that grows out of a larger branch on a bush or tree",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "And again in what directions do the branches and smaller twigs grow?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "train",
        "question": "тренировать (обучать)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to teach someone the skills of a particular job or activity, or to be taught these skills",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "All staff will be trained in customer service skills.",
            "These dogs are trained to detect drugs.",
            "She’s training to be a doctor."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "advantage",
        "question": "преимущество",
        "explanation": "[noun] something good about a situation that helps you",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "One of the advantages of living in town is having the shops so near.",
            "Her experience meant that she had a big advantage over her opponent."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sportsman",
        "question": "спортсмен",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "day",
        "question": "день",
        "explanation": "[noun] the time between sunrise and sunset (as distinct from night)",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "round red apples",
        "question": "Круглые красные яблоки",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "specific",
        "question": "определенный, особый",
        "explanation": "[adjective] a specific thing, person, or group is one particular thing, person, or group",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "games suitable for specific age groups"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "afternoon",
        "question": "время после полудня",
        "explanation": "This is the time from midday (noon) to evening. From 12:00 hours to approximately 18:00 hours.",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "iron",
        "question": "утюг",
        "explanation": "[noun] a piece of electrical equipment that you use for making clothes flat and smooth",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "crash",
        "question": "авария, крушение",
        "explanation": "[noun] an accident in which a vehicle violently hits something else",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Forty-one people were killed in a plane crash."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "late in the evening",
        "question": "поздно вечером",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "What language does he speak?",
        "question": "На каком языке он говорит?",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from. Certainly use which, not what, when there are only two choices, or if both speaker and listener can visualise all the items under consideration. Because there are so many languages in the world, and you don’t know what all of them are. However, you could very well say “Which language does he speak?” if, for example, his mother speaks French, his father speaks Italian, and the family lives in Brazil—in this case, there are only three clear possibilities.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "petty crime",
        "question": "мелкие правонарушения",
        "explanation": "crime that is not very serious",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Immigrants were blamed for the increase in petty crime."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Buckthorn",
        "question": "облепиха",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "a quotation at the beginning of a book, chapter, etc. suggesting its theme.",
        "question": "epigraph",
        "explanation": "[noun, countable] эпиграф, надпись (на здании, гробнице, статуе); an inscription on a monument or building",
        "source": "Complexity: A guided tour (Melanie Mitchell)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "designer",
        "question": "дизайнер",
        "explanation": "a person who plans the look or workings of something prior to it being made, by preparing drawings or plans",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "somehow or other",
        "question": "Так или иначе",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Somehow or other (= I do not know how) they managed to get in."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "banana",
        "question": "банан",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "a pinch of salt",
        "question": "щепотка соли (with an article)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ultimate outcome",
        "question": "конечный результат",
        "explanation": "[ultimate] the ultimate result of a long process is what happens at the end of it",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The ultimate outcome of the experiment cannot be predicted."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "dairy",
        "question": "containing or made from milk",
        "explanation": "a shop where milk and milk products are sold. milk and milk products collectively",
        "source": "Environment around you",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I rely on soya as a substitute for dairy.",
            "Local dairy foods."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "rub",
        "question": "тереть",
        "explanation": "to move your hand, or something such as a cloth, backwards and forwards over a surface while pressing firmly",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She yawned and rubbed her eyes."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "awkwardly",
        "question": "неуклюже, неловко",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "‘I’m very sorry about your sister, ’ he said awkwardly.",
            "Vera smiled awkwardly."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "industry",
        "question": "промышленность",
        "explanation": "[noun] he large-scale production of goods or of substances such as coal and steel",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "This type of software is widely used in industry.",
            "workers in manufacturing industry"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "row",
        "question": "ряд",
        "explanation": "a line of things or people next to each other",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a row of houses"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "absorb",
        "question": "впитывать",
        "explanation": "[verb] If a substance absorbs a liquid, it takes it in through its surface and holds it.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The fabric absorbs all the moisture, keeping your skin dry."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "spare",
        "question": "запасной, лишний",
        "explanation": "[adjective] not being used or not needed at the present time",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Have you got any spare boxes?",
            "You could sleep in the spare bedroom."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "garage",
        "question": "гараж",
        "explanation": "[noun] a small building, often built next to a house, that you can put a car in",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I’ll just go and put the car in the garage."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "temperance movement",
        "question": "движение трезвенников",
        "explanation": null,
        "source": "A History of the World in 100 Objects: Early Victorian tea set",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "persimmon",
        "question": "хурма",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "hunting",
        "question": "охота",
        "explanation": "[noun] the sport of chasing and killing animals",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "fox-hunting"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "fabulous view",
        "question": "потрясающий вид",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "choice",
        "question": "выбор",
        "explanation": "[if you have a choice, you can choose between several things] Voters have a choice between three main political parties.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "If I had a choice, I'd give up work.",
            "He had no choice but to accept their offer."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sour cream",
        "question": "сметана",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "article",
        "question": "статья",
        "explanation": "[noun] a piece of writing in a magazine, newspaper, etc.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an article on environmental issues",
            "The paper’s leading article (=the main article) described the government as weak.",
            "newspaper articles"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "pistachio",
        "question": "фисташка",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "May I ask you a question?",
        "question": "Можно задать вам вопрос?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "proclaim",
        "question": "провозглашать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to say publicly or officially that something important is true or exists",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The president proclaimed the republic’s independence."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "idea",
        "question": "идея, мысль",
        "explanation": "[noun] a plan or suggestion for a possible course of action, especially one that you think of suddenly",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "You should talk to Ken- he’s always full of good ideas."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sunrise",
        "question": "восход солнца",
        "explanation": "[noun] the time when the sun first appears in the sky in the morning",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "having a strong influence or effect",
        "question": "EXPLAIN: profound CONTEXT: profound changes in society",
        "explanation": "[adjective] (глубокий, серьезный) If an effect is profound, it is extreme.",
        "source": "From Frequency to Meaning: Vector Space Models of Semantics.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The war had a profound impact on people's lives.",
            "The mother’s behaviour has a profound impact on the developing child."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "My tea has gone cold.",
        "question": "Мой чай стал холодным.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "The bell rang.",
        "question": "Зазвонил звонок.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Can I get there by bus?",
        "question": "Можно ли доехать на автобусе?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "to make the acquaintance",
        "question": "познакомиться",
        "explanation": "meet someone for the first time and come to know them slightly",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Let's go for a walk.",
        "question": "Пойдемте погуляем",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "tell a lie",
        "question": "лгать, врать (to deliberately tell someone something that is not true)",
        "explanation": "When you don't tell the truth, you lie.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I could tell from her face that she was lying.",
            "She lied about her age."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "reproduce",
        "question": "воспроизводить",
        "explanation": "[verb] To reproduce is to make more, either by having babies or creating copies. Parents and copy machines both reproduce. To produce is \"to make something,\" and re means “again,” so reproduce literally means to “produce again.” When animals and plants make more of their own kind, they reproduce. Plants reproduce asexually, and people reproduce through childbirth. You can also reproduce a book by printing more copies or a computer file by copying it. Reproducing always creates more of something.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The diagram is reproduced by permission of the original author.",
            "British scientists have so far been unable to reproduce these results."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "The strong wind blows.",
        "question": "Дует сильный ветер.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "A new bookshop had opened in the high street.",
        "question": "На главной улице открылся новый книжный магазин.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am staying at my relatives",
        "question": "я остановился у родственников",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "may i come in?",
        "question": "можно войти?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "amount",
        "question": "количество",
        "explanation": "[noun] how much there is of something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The project will take a huge amount of time and money."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "southern",
        "question": "движущийся с юга, на юг, южный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] in or from the south part of an area",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the southern half of the country"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my son",
        "question": "это мой сын",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "receive guests",
        "question": "принимать гостей",
        "explanation": "to formally welcome guests",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She isn’t well enough to receive visitors yet."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "help yourself, please!",
        "question": "угощайтесь, пожалуйста!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "professions",
        "question": "профессии",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "It is raining.",
        "question": "Идёт дождь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I have stayed here for three days.",
        "question": "Я пробыл здесь три дня.",
        "explanation": "\"for\"- used to say how long an action or situation continues for.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "remorse",
        "question": "угрызения совести; раскаяние",
        "explanation": "the feeling of being extremely sorry for sth wrong or bad that you have done",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I think she is doing a tremendous job.",
        "question": "Я думаю, что она делает потрясающую работу.",
        "explanation": "[adjective] extremely good. (Commas are used to identify separate clauses by \"splitting\" them. You can't use a comma before an essential subordinate clause. The reason you can't say \"I hope, my explanations help\" is because it's like you're saying two separate things. Like \"I eat, my dog is asleep.\" That's two separate ideas split up with a comma, and it's what your sentence sounds like with it.)",
        "source": "Highlights of Calculus",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She’s got a tremendous voice, hasn’t she?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "take a sip of orange juice",
        "question": "сделать глоток апельсинового сока",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "abstruse",
        "question": "невразумительный, трудный для понимания",
        "explanation": "[adjective] unnecessarily complicated and difficult to understand",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Maths is a mix of abstruse theory and detailed calculations."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i have arrived with my child",
        "question": "я приехал с моим ребёнком",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "envelope",
        "question": "конверт",
        "explanation": "[noun] a flat paper container for a letter",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "envelopes and stamps"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "entail",
        "question": "влечь за собой, быть связанным с чем-либо",
        "explanation": "[verb] to involve something as a necessary part or result",
        "source": "software testing: a craftsman's approach",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "A new computer system entails a lot of re-training.",
            "Some foreign travel is entailed in the job.",
            "The journey will entail changing trains twice."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "vegetable",
        "question": "овощ",
        "explanation": "[noun] a plant that is eaten raw or cooked, such as a cabbage, a carrot, or peas",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "fresh fruit and vegetables"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "illustrate",
        "question": "иллюстрировать, пояснять",
        "explanation": "[verb] to make the meaning of something clearer by giving examples",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She illustrated her discussion with diagrams."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "offend",
        "question": "обижать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to make someone upset or angry",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I was deeply offended by her comments."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "give my regards to your brother",
        "question": "передайте привет брату",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Bake the cake for 40 minutes.",
        "question": "Готовьте пирог в течении 40 минут.",
        "explanation": "\"for\"- used to say how long an action or situation continues for.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "watermelon",
        "question": "арбуз",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "old- new",
        "question": "старый- новый",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "in the morning",
        "question": "утром",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "The others have gone out on the town.",
        "question": "[Вечером] Другие пошли гулять по городу.",
        "explanation": "(out) on the town- (informal) going to restaurants, bars, theatres, etc. for entertainment in the evening.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "nectarine",
        "question": "нектарин",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "drudgery",
        "question": "тяжёлая, монотонная работа",
        "explanation": "[noun] hard boring work",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "what",
        "question": "что?; каков? (в прямых вопросах к подлежащему или дополнениям с предлогом или без предлога; обычно- к неодушевлённому) кто? (о людях; по профессии, по характеру) сколько?",
        "explanation": "[pronoun] used to ask for information about something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "What time is it?",
            "What happened?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "tomato",
        "question": "помидор",
        "explanation": "[noun] a soft, round, red fruit eaten in salad or as a vegetable",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "so, all in all",
        "question": "итак, в итоге (в целом) (в конце речи)",
        "explanation": "You use all in all to introduce a summary or general statement.",
        "source": "IELTS preparation",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "at night",
        "question": "ночью",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my uncle",
        "question": "это мой дядя",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Not to mention",
        "question": "не говоря уже о",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "tie a shoelace",
        "question": "Завязывать шнурок",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "wide- narrow",
        "question": "широкий- узкий",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "dill",
        "question": "укроп",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "make a request",
        "question": "сделать запрос",
        "explanation": "[verb]",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I’d like to make a request."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "magazine",
        "question": "журнал",
        "explanation": "[noun] a thin book published every week or month, that has shiny, colourful pages with articles and pictures",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a fashion/news magazine"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "quarter past eight",
        "question": "8.15- четверть девятого",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "go down the stairs",
        "question": "Спуститесь вниз по лестнице",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i work in a firm",
        "question": "я работаю в фирме",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "floor",
        "question": "пол (в комнате)",
        "explanation": "[noun] the flat surface that you stand on inside a building",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a polished wooden floor"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my daughter",
        "question": "это моя дочь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i have lost my way",
        "question": "я заблудился",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "give my regards to your sister",
        "question": "передайте привет сестре",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sole",
        "question": "единоличный (осуществляемый одним лицом)",
        "explanation": "[adjective] not shared with anyone else",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Derek has sole responsibility for sales in Dublin."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "on Tuesdays",
        "question": "по вторникам",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "take hold",
        "question": "start to have an effect",
        "explanation": "the reforms of the late nineteenth century had taken hold.",
        "source": "Living With The Gods (bbc radio 4)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "long- short",
        "question": "длинный- короткий",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "When reporters arrived at the house, they got a hostile reception.",
        "question": "Когда репортеры прибыли в дом, они получили враждебный прием.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "south",
        "question": "юг",
        "explanation": "the direction that is on your right when you face towards the rising sun",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "you are three years younger than me",
        "question": "вы моложе меня на три года",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "All the people on the bus stared at me.",
        "question": "Все люди в автобусе смотрели на меня.",
        "explanation": "If you can walk onto it and stand up inside, you say “get on”. If not, you say “get in”. This rule is especially illustrated by vehicles where we could use either “in/out” or “on/off”, depending on the size of the vehicle. We normally say “get on an airplane” but if you have a small, single-engine airplane, you would normally say “get in”. The same goes for boats, where we get on a large ship, but get in a canoe. This is also true for helicopters, submarines and spaceships.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "rowan",
        "question": "рябина",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "are you free tonight?",
        "question": "вы свободны сегодня вечером?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "conversation",
        "question": "беседа",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "interpret",
        "question": "переводить (устно)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to translate spoken words from one language into another",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "They spoke good Spanish, and promised to interpret for me.",
            "We had to ask the guide to interpret for us."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "stipulate",
        "question": "предписывать (по закону)",
        "explanation": "[verb, formal] to say exactly what must be done",
        "source": "From Frequency to Meaning: Vector Space Models of Semantics.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The rules stipulate that smoking is not allowed."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "what are you going to do tomorrow evening?",
        "question": "что вы делаете завтра вечером?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "there is no need to hurry.",
        "question": "Нет необходимости торопиться.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "taxi rank",
        "question": "стоянка такси",
        "explanation": "a place where taxis wait for customers (AE a taxi stand)",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "quarter to nine, fifteen minutes to nine",
        "question": "8.45- без четверти девять, без пятнадцати девять",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "How was it?",
        "question": "Ну как? (Как все прошло?)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i cannot",
        "question": "я не могу",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "backwards",
        "question": "назад",
        "explanation": "[adverb] towards the direction behind you",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Hannah took a step backward.",
            "She pushed me and I fell backwards into the chair."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "in a month",
        "question": "через месяц",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "have a good trip",
        "question": "счастливого пути",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "rude",
        "question": "грубый (behaving in a way that is not polite and upsets people)",
        "explanation": "speaking or behaving in a way that is not polite and is likely to offend or annoy people",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I didn’t mean to be rude, but I had to leave early."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "toe",
        "question": "палец ноги",
        "explanation": "[noun] one of the five separate parts at the end of your foot",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "your big toe (= largest toe)",
            "your little toe (= smallest toe)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "joint",
        "question": "[Скелет человека] сустав",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "diary",
        "question": "a book in which one keeps a daily record of events and experiences.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "Environment around you",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "tonight",
        "question": "сегодня вечером, сегодняшний вечер",
        "explanation": "[adverb] the night of this day, or during the night of this day",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "What are you doing tonight?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "demise",
        "question": "кончина, крах",
        "explanation": "[noun] the end or failure of an institution, an idea, a company, etc.; (formal or humorous) death",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (Melanie Mitchell)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the demise of apartheid"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "In any case",
        "question": "В любом случае",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "rubbish bin",
        "question": "мусорка (мусорное ведро)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "garlic",
        "question": "чеснок",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "traffic",
        "question": "дорожное движение",
        "explanation": "[noun] the vehicles moving along a road or street",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "There wasn’t much traffic on the roads.",
            "The sound of the traffic kept me awake."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "What flavour of ice cream do you want?",
        "question": "Какой вкус мороженого вы хотите?",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from. Certainly use which, not what, when there are only two choices, or if both speaker and listener can visualise all the items under consideration. Generally speaking, you can replace the usage of \"which” with \"what\" and be OK grammatically. It doesn’t always work the other way around, however. There needs to be a context of choice.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Could you be more specific about what you are looking for?",
        "question": "Не могли бы вы уточнить, что вы ищете?",
        "explanation": "[specific] (конкретный) exact or containing details",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Could you be more specific about the problem?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "salt",
        "question": "соль",
        "explanation": "[noun] a natural white mineral that is added to food to make it taste better or to preserve it",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Could you pass the salt?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "What is going on?",
        "question": "Что происходит?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "crash course",
        "question": "интенсивный курс",
        "explanation": "a course in which you learn a lot about a particular subject in a very short period of time",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a crash course in Spanish"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "wet wipes",
        "question": "влажные салфетки",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sleeve",
        "question": "[деталь одежды] рукав",
        "explanation": "[noun] the part of a piece of clothing that covers all or part of your arm",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a dress with long sleeves",
            "a short-sleeved shirt"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "what faculty do you study at?",
        "question": "на каком факультете вы учитесь?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "enormous interest",
        "question": "огромный интерес",
        "explanation": "[interest] if you have an interest in something or someone, you want to know or learn more about them",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I’d recommend this book to anyone who has an interest in jazz."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Waiting in the airport lounge",
        "question": "Ждать в зале ожидания аеропорта.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "are you free after dinner?",
        "question": "вы свободны после обеда?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "blackberry",
        "question": "ежевика",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "artificial intelligence",
        "question": "искусственный интеллект",
        "explanation": "[intelligence] the ability to learn, understand, and think about things",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "To be good at the game, you need a reasonable level of intelligence."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "advertisement",
        "question": "реклама",
        "explanation": "[noun] a picture, short film, song, etc that tries to persuade people to buy a product or service",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a newspaper/television advertisement"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "an urgent request",
        "question": "срочная просьба (with an article)",
        "explanation": "[verb]",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The family made an urgent request on television for help in finding their daughter."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "take special note",
        "question": "nota bene (n.b.)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "IELTS preparation",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "recipe",
        "question": "кулинарный рецепт",
        "explanation": "[noun] a set of instructions for cooking a particular type of food",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a recipe for tomato soup",
            "a recipe book"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "let me introduce myself, i am",
        "question": "разрешите представиться, я",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "film director",
        "question": "режиссёр",
        "explanation": "a person who controls the making of a film and supervises the actors and technical crew",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "tourist",
        "question": "турист",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone who visits a place for pleasure and does not live there",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "permit",
        "question": "разрешать (formal, by rules or law)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to allow something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Photography is not permitted inside the museum.",
            "He permitted them to leave."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "never",
        "question": "никогда",
        "explanation": "[adverb] not at any time, or not once",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He’s never been to Australia.",
            "It is never too late to give up smoking."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Sweet yellow pears",
        "question": "Сладкие желтые груши",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Where is the toilet?",
        "question": "Где туалет?",
        "explanation": "Where is the ladies room? Where is the gentlemen room?",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I would like a cup of coffee.",
        "question": "Я хотел бы чашечку кофе.",
        "explanation": "We use “would like” or “‘d like to” to say politely what we want, especially when making offers or requests. Verbs that follow would like are in the to-infinitive form.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "What does your wife do?",
        "question": "кем работает ваша жена?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "cross",
        "question": "пересекать, переходить",
        "explanation": "[verb] to go from one side of something to the other side",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It's not a good place to cross the road."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "wear",
        "question": "носить, быть одетым во что-либо",
        "explanation": "[verb] to have a piece of clothing, jewellery, etc on your body",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I wear jeans a lot of the time.",
            "She wears glasses.",
            "I don't usually wear make-up for work."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am forty-nine",
        "question": "мне сорок девять лет",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "What direction should I go in?",
        "question": "В каком направлении мне идти?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "aside",
        "question": "в сторону",
        "explanation": "[adverb] in a direction to one side",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I gave her a plate of food but she pushed it aside."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "animal",
        "question": "животное",
        "explanation": "[noun] something that lives and moves but is not a person, bird, fish, or insect",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a wild animal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "magic",
        "question": "волшебство",
        "explanation": "[noun] the power to make impossible things happen by saying special words or doing special actions",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Do you believe in magic?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "by no means",
        "question": "ни в коем случае",
        "explanation": " not at all; certainly not: the outcome is by no means guaranteed.",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "what are you going to do tomorrow?",
        "question": "что вы делаете завтра?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Which size do you want- small, medium or large?",
        "question": "Какой размер вы хотите- маленький, средний или большой?",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from. Certainly use which, not what, when there are only two choices, or if both speaker and listener can visualise all the items under consideration. Generally speaking, you can replace the usage of \"which” with \"what\" and be OK grammatically. It doesn’t always work the other way around, however. There needs to be a context of choice.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my cousin",
        "question": "это моя двоюродная сестра",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "scratch",
        "question": "чесать(ся)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to rub your skin with your nails because it feels uncomfortable",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "John yawned and scratched his leg."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "ancient",
        "question": "древний, старинный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] from a long time ago",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an ancient building",
            "ancient Greece"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": " i am staying in a hotel",
        "question": "я остановился в гостинице",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I am sorry, I did not catch you.",
        "question": "Простите, я не расслышал.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "imply",
        "question": "подразумевать, намекать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to suggest that something is true, without saying this directly",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Are you implying that I'm fat?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "score",
        "question": "счет, количество очков",
        "explanation": "[noun] the number of points someone gets in a game or test",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "What's the score?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "plum",
        "question": "слива",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "night",
        "question": "ночь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sole survivor",
        "question": "единственный выживший",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Griffiths is the sole survivor of the crash."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "please, show",
        "question": "пожалуйста, покажите",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "traffic congestion",
        "question": "транспортный затор",
        "explanation": "when the roads are full of traffic",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "These vehicles are very often used as a means of transport to escape the problem of traffic congestion."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "induce",
        "question": "склонять",
        "explanation": "[verb, formal] to persuade someone to do something, especially something that does not seem wise",
        "source": "software testing: a craftsman's approach",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Nothing would induce me to vote for him again."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "lid",
        "question": "крышка",
        "explanation": "a cover for the open part of a pot, box, or other container",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He carefully lifted the lid of the box."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "ball",
        "question": "мяч",
        "explanation": "[noun] a round object that you throw, kick, or hit in a game, or something with this shape",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a tennis ball",
            "a ball of string"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "network",
        "question": "сеть (совокупность дорог, каналов)взаимосвязанная цепочка или система нематериальных объектов; схематическое представление событий и действий при изучении эффективности производственного процесса.",
        "explanation": "[noun] a system of lines, tubes, wires, roads etc that cross each other and are connected to each other",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Hungary’s telephone network",
            "a network of cables"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "How can I get to the library?",
        "question": "Как пройти в библиотеку?",
        "explanation": "You can also say \"How do I get to the library?\". The two expressions are essentially equivalent.",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "The bag is divided into separate compartments.",
        "question": "Сумка разделена на отдельные отсеки. (The bag)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "store it in the refrigerator",
        "question": "храните его в холодильнике",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "How could you believe his lie?",
        "question": "Как вы могли поверить в его ложь?",
        "explanation": "[lie] something that you say or write that you know is untrue",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I always know when he’s telling lies."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "aware",
        "question": "сознавать",
        "explanation": "[adjective] to know about something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Are you aware of the risks involved?",
            "The children are aware of the danger of taking drugs."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "under the rules",
        "question": "По правилам",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "town",
        "question": "небольшой город, посёлок городского типа",
        "explanation": "[noun] a place where people live and work, usually larger than a village but smaller than a city",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It's a small town in the north of England."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "crash site",
        "question": "место катастрофы (аварии)",
        "explanation": "place where a crash happens",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The authorities closed off a five-mile area around the crash site."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "all right",
        "question": "Is everything ... (well, OK, satisfactory)?",
        "explanation": "All right may be written as alright, but all right is more common",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "immediate",
        "question": "немедленный, безотлагательный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] happening or done without waiting or very soon after something else",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The government has promised to take immediate action."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "author",
        "question": "автор",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone who writes a book, article, etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a popular author of children's fiction"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "lace up your shoes",
        "question": "Завяжи свои ботинки",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "how is your husband?",
        "question": "как дела у вашего мужа?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "For here or to go?",
        "question": "[restaurant] Здесь или на вынос?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "frame",
        "question": "рама (жёсткая конструкция, охватывающая снаружи и закрепляющая какой-либо объект.)",
        "explanation": "[noun] a structure made of wood, metal, plastic etc that surrounds something such as a picture or window, and holds it in place",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "They removed the picture from its wooden frame."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "direct route",
        "question": "прямой маршрут",
        "explanation": "[route] a way from one place to another",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "What’s the best route to Cambridge?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "name",
        "question": "имя, название",
        "explanation": "[noun] the word or group of words that is used to refer to a person, thing, or place",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "What's your name?",
            "I can't remember the name of the street he lives on."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "water supply",
        "question": "водоснабжение",
        "explanation": "water and the lakes, reservoirs etc where it is stored",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "A dam was built to improve the water supply."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "larva",
        "question": "личинка",
        "explanation": "[noun] (plural larvae /-viː/) an insect at the stage when it has just come out of an egg and looks like a short fat worm",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Growth is rapid, on a diet of tiny larvae, worms and relatives."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "nothing good",
        "question": "ничего хорошего",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "morning",
        "question": "утро",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "perpetuate",
        "question": "make (something) continue indefinitely",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "Living With The Gods (bbc radio 4)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "in other words",
        "question": "другими словами",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "import",
        "question": "импортировать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to bring something into your country from another country for people to buy",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We import about 20 percent of our food."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "precarious ladder",
        "question": "неустойчивая (шаткая) лестница",
        "explanation": "not securely held or in position; dangerously likely to fall or collapse",
        "source": "Fundamental Concepts in Programming Languages - paper",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "anniversary",
        "question": "годовщина",
        "explanation": "[noun] a date on which you remember or celebrate something that happened on that date one or more years ago",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a wedding anniversary"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "down",
        "question": "пух (очень мелкие, нежные пушистые пёрышки у птиц, ближайшие к коже)",
        "explanation": "[noun, uncountable] the soft fine feathers of a bird",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "crowd of people",
        "question": "толпа людей",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "total",
        "question": "общее количество, сумма; итог",
        "explanation": "[noun] including everything",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The total cost of the work was $800."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "military man",
        "question": "военнослужащий",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "deliver",
        "question": "доставлять",
        "explanation": "[verb] to take goods, letters, packages etc to a particular place or person",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The morning mail has just been delivered.",
            "Do you deliver on Saturdays?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "grapefruit",
        "question": "грейпфрут",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "recall",
        "question": "припоминать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to remember something",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I don't recall arranging a time to meet."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "jacket",
        "question": "куртка, пиджак",
        "explanation": "[noun] a short light coat",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "It does not matter.",
        "question": "Это не имеет значения.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "advertise",
        "question": "рекламировать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to tell people about a product or service, for example in newspapers or on television, in order to persuade them to buy it",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Companies are not allowed to advertise cigarettes on television any more."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "audience",
        "question": "публика",
        "explanation": "[noun] the people who sit and watch a performance at a theatre, cinema, etc.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "There were a lot of children in the audience."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "debate",
        "question": "дискуссия",
        "explanation": "[noun] discussion of a particular subject that often continues for a long time and in which people express different opinions",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the gun-control debate in the US",
            "There has been a lot of public debate on the safety of food."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Each piece of luggage can weigh up to 20 kilos",
        "question": "Каждый багаж может весить до 20кг.",
        "explanation": "When talking about one suitcase or bag, you say a piece of luggage or an item of luggage",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "please, telephone",
        "question": "пожалуйста, позвоните",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i have two children",
        "question": "у меня двое детей",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "how is your wife?",
        "question": "как дела у вашей жены?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "early in the morning",
        "question": "рано утром",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "to no avail",
        "question": "безрезультатно",
        "explanation": "if something you do is to no avail or of no avail, you do not succeed in getting what you want",
        "source": "A history of the world in 100 objects.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We searched the whole area but all to no avail. Robbie had disappeared."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "What bus shall I take?",
        "question": "На какой автобус мне нужно сесть?",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from. Certainly use which, not what, when there are only two choices, or if both speaker and listener can visualise all the items under consideration.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "juvenile",
        "question": "несовершеннолетний",
        "explanation": "(formal or law) connected with young people who are not yet adults",
        "source": "Environment around you",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "juvenile crime",
            "juvenile offender"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i speak a little english",
        "question": "я немного говорю по-английски",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "conventional",
        "question": "обычный, общепринятый",
        "explanation": "[adjective] a conventional method, product, practice etc has been used for a long time and is considered the usual type",
        "source": "Word smart.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Internet connections through conventional phone lines are fairly slow.",
            "Bake for 20 minutes in a conventional oven",
            "Rosemary led a quiet, conventional life until she went to college.",
            "a strong believer in conventional morals"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "scheme",
        "question": "план, программа (an official plan or system)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an insurance/savings scheme",
            "a training scheme for teenagers"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "year",
        "question": "год",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sole",
        "question": "представленный только в одном лице; единственный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] the sole person, thing etc is the only one",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the sole American in the room",
            "He was the sole candidate for the post."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i have no children",
        "question": "у меня нет детей",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "what are you going to do today?",
        "question": "что вы делаете сегодня?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "at four o'clock",
        "question": "в четыре часа",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "dry- wet",
        "question": "сухой- мокрый",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "the formulas of politeness",
        "question": "формулы вежливости",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "economist",
        "question": "экономист",
        "explanation": "an expert in economics",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "tomorrow",
        "question": "завтрашний день, завтра",
        "explanation": "[adverb] It's my birthday tomorrow.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Tomorrow is Friday."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "source of income",
        "question": "источник дохода (without an article)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "At present tourism is the principal source of income, employment and foreign exchange."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "I am leaving home.",
        "question": "Я уезжаю из дома.",
        "explanation": "We use the present continuous to describe an event in the future which has already been arranged by the time of speaking.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I have been studying art since I was 13 years old.",
        "question": "Я занимаюсь искусством с 13 лет.",
        "explanation": "\"Has been\" and \"have been\" are both in the present perfect tense. \"Has been\" is used in the third-person singular and \"have been\" is used for first- and second-person singular and all plural uses. The present perfect tense refers to an action that began at some time in the past and is still in progress. For example, if I started studying art when I was 13 years old and I am still studying art, I would say \"I have been studying art since I was 13 years old.\"",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "water",
        "question": "вода",
        "explanation": "[noun] the clear liquid without colour, smell, or taste that falls as rain and that is used for drinking, washing etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Does anyone want a drink of water?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "March",
        "question": "март",
        "explanation": "the March issue of the magazine",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "gasoline",
        "question": "бензин",
        "explanation": "[noun] a liquid obtained from petroleum, used mainly for producing power in the engines of cars, trucks etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Three hundred gallons of gasoline were loaded today."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "what is your profession?",
        "question": "какая у вас профессия?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "give my regards to your family",
        "question": "передайте привет семье",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "What are you up to?",
        "question": "Чем занимаешься?",
        "explanation": "'What are you doing?' is a simple request for information. Without any further context, it means refers to what someone is engaged in at that particular moment. It can sometimes appear a little 'bare' as a question- maybe rude or too direct. 'What are you up to?' is a more informal, conversational question, which can also mean 'Tell me about your life at the moment- what's good? what's bad? what's happening?'. You would often meet a friend or acquaintance whom you haven't seen for a while and say: 'So, what are you up to these days?' It's a fairly open question, and an invitation for them to give you their news. You can also use it in the present perfect: 'So, what have you been up to recently?'",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "twenty-five minutes past eight",
        "question": "8.25- двадцать пять минут девятого",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "How much is the fare?",
        "question": "Сколько стоит проезд?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "when were you born?",
        "question": "какого вы года рождения?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "cucumber",
        "question": "огурец",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Sorry, I was not listening.",
        "question": "Извините, я прослушал.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "weight",
        "question": "вес",
        "explanation": "[noun] how heavy someone or something is",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The average weight of a baby at birth is just over seven pounds."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "impact",
        "question": "воздействие",
        "explanation": "[noun] an effect that happens as a result of something important, especially a big and permanent effect",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Changes in technology have had a massive impact on the way we work.",
            "Winning this competition could have a big impact on my life."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "political rally",
        "question": "политический митинг",
        "explanation": "[rally] a large public meeting, especially one that is held outdoors to support a political idea, protest etc",
        "source": "A history of the world in 100 objects.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "About 1,000 people attended the rally in Hyde Park."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "see you tonight",
        "question": "до вечера",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "jealous",
        "question": "ревнивый; ревнующий",
        "explanation": "[adjective] feeling angry and unhappy because someone you like or love is showing interest in another person, or another person is showing interest in them",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "jealous husband"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "spacious house",
        "question": "просторный дом",
        "explanation": "[adjective] a spacious house, room etc is large and has plenty of space to move around in",
        "source": "Booking review",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a spacious living area"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "running water",
        "question": "водопровод",
        "explanation": "water that comes out of a system of pipes into buildings",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Only half the city’s houses had running water."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "crucial",
        "question": "ключевой, решающий (чрезвычайно важный)",
        "explanation": "[adjective] extremely important or necessary",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Her work has been crucial to the project's success."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "please pass me the salt",
        "question": "пожалуйста передайте мне соль",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "Woe is I Jr",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "with several",
        "question": "с несколькими",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Tom has studied medicine for 3 years.",
        "question": "Том изучает медицину в течение 3 лет. (В этом примере говорится, что Том изучал и до сих пор изучает медицину. Present Perfect)",
        "explanation": "Форма глагола в Present Perfect Tense (настоящем совершенном времени) состоит из вспомогательного глагола has/have и причастия прошедшего времени (Participle II) и обозначает действие, которое, начавшись в прошлом, продолжается в настоящем (или каким-либо образом на него влияет)",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "dome",
        "question": "Купол",
        "explanation": "the dome of St Paul's Cathedral",
        "source": "Living with the Gods: Here Comes the Sun.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "If you talk about the idiosyncrasies of someone or something, you are referring to their rather unusual habits or characteristics.",
        "question": "idiosyncrasy",
        "explanation": "[noun, countable] отличительная особенность (характера, стиля)",
        "source": "Genetic algorithms with python",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "one of the many idiosyncrasies of English spelling",
            "She's easy to work for, and her employees don't mind her idiosyncrasies."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "band",
        "question": "группа, оркестр",
        "explanation": "[noun] a group of musicians, especially a group that plays popular music",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The band was playing old Beatles songs.",
            "Smith joined the band in 1989."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Next time lucky!",
        "question": "Повезет в следующий раз!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "find out",
        "question": "узнай",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Does this bus go to the city center?",
        "question": "Этот автобус идет до центра? (center)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "scarlet",
        "question": "Алый",
        "explanation": "[adjective] of a brilliant red colour",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a mass of scarlet berries"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Would that be okay with you.",
        "question": "You and one of your coworkers want to switch your assignments. You need to check with your boss for permission. You're not sure whether she'll allow it, so you write an email describing the plan and ask this at the end. (Какой фразой нужно спросить разрешения?)",
        "explanation": "На русский можно перевести как: \"ты не возражаешь?\", \"Ты была (был) бы не против?\". Your request to reschedule is a form of **asking permission** which can be phrased using either **would** which would sound neither too formal nor informal.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Would I be able to reschedule and take the test on Wednesday after school instead?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "anxiety",
        "question": "беспокойство, тревога",
        "explanation": "[noun] the feeling of being very worried",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "That explains his anxiety about her health."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "affect",
        "question": "оказывать воздействие",
        "explanation": "[verb] to influence someone or something, or cause them to change",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It's a disease which affects many older people."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "peruse",
        "question": "to read something, especially in a careful way",
        "explanation": "[verb]",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She leant forward to peruse the document more closely."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "poison",
        "question": "яд",
        "explanation": "[noun] a substance that can make you sick or kill you if you eat or drink it",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Someone had put poison in her drink."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "not known to many people",
        "question": "EXPLAIN: obscure CONTEXT: an obscure island in the Pacific",
        "explanation": "[adjective] (малоизвестный) not well known and usually not very important",
        "source": "The Documentary: Reformation 500",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an obscure poet",
            "The details of his life remain obscure."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "bad-tempered",
        "question": "раздражительный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] becoming easily annoyed and talking in an angry unfriendly way to people",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I was wondering why she had been so bad-tempered recently.",
            "Sam has been bad-tempered recently, is something worrying him?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "safe",
        "question": "безопасный",
        "explanation": "not in danger of being harmed, lost, or stolen",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Make sure you keep these documents safe."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Did you sleep well?",
        "question": "Вы хорошо спали?",
        "explanation": "[sleep] to rest your mind and body, usually at night when you are lying in bed with your eyes closed",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I usually sleep on my back."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am married",
        "question": "я женат (замужем)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I am so sorry!",
        "question": "Мне очень жаль!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "lemon",
        "question": "лимон",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "evening",
        "question": "вечер",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "priest",
        "question": "священник",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone who is specially trained to perform religious duties and ceremonies in the Christian church",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Women priests are much more common these days.",
            "The priest who married us was very friendly and helpful.",
            "a Buddhist priest"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "trend",
        "question": "тенденция (общее направление, курс)",
        "explanation": "[noun] a general tendency in the way a situation is changing or developing",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Lately there has been a trend towards hiring younger, cheaper employees.",
            "The current trend is towards more part-time employment."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "please, repeat",
        "question": "пожалуйста, повторите",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i wish you good luck",
        "question": "желау вам удачи",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "spell",
        "question": "произносить или писать слово по буквам",
        "explanation": "[verb] to write down or tell someone the letters that are used to make a word",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Her name's spelt S-I-A-N."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "He is on night duty.",
        "question": "Он на ночном дежурстве.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ultimate fate",
        "question": "конечная судьба",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The ultimate fate of the tribe was even sadder."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "household rubbish",
        "question": "бытовой мусор",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Would you please draw out the route for me?",
        "question": "Не могли бы вы проложить маршрут для меня? (Would)",
        "explanation": "\"Could you please...\" or \"Would you please...\"? Both of these choices are polite ways to ask someone to do something.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "mess",
        "question": "беспорядок",
        "explanation": "[noun] if there is a mess somewhere or a place is a mess, things there are dirty or not neatly arranged",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "What a mess!",
            "When I got home, the house was a complete mess."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "inner courtyard",
        "question": "внутренний двор",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "Booking review",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "businessman",
        "question": "бизнесмен",
        "explanation": "a man who works in commerce, especially at executive level",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "financier",
        "question": "финансист",
        "explanation": "a person concerned in the management of large amounts of money on behalf of governments or other large organizations",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "reviewer",
        "question": "референт",
        "explanation": "a person who writes critical appraisals of books, plays, films, etc. for publication",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "a pair of jeans",
        "question": "пара джинсов (with an article)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ripe tangerine",
        "question": "спелый мандарин",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "road crash",
        "question": "дорожная авария",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am very grateful to you",
        "question": "я вам очень признателен",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "my name is farit",
        "question": "моё имя фарит",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "cruel",
        "question": "жестокий",
        "explanation": "[adjective] extremely unkind, or causing people or animals to suffer",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a cruel joke"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "schedule",
        "question": "расписание",
        "explanation": "[noun] a plan of what someone is going to do and when they are going to do it",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Meg’s new book is still well ahead of schedule."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "licence",
        "question": "лицензия",
        "explanation": "an official document giving you permission to own or do something for a period of time",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He was arrested for driving without a license."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "narrow",
        "question": "узкий, тесный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] Narrow things measure a small distance from one side to the other.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a long narrow road",
            "The stairs were very narrow."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "weapon",
        "question": "оружие",
        "explanation": "[noun] a gun, knife, or other object used to kill or hurt someone",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "nuclear weapons",
            "Police have found the murder weapon."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "broker",
        "question": "брокер",
        "explanation": "a person who buys and sells goods or assets for others",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "think of a way",
        "question": "придумать способ",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I have to think of a way to make some money."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "crisp",
        "question": "хрустящий",
        "explanation": "[adjective] something that is crisp is hard, and makes a pleasant sound when you break it or crush it",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She kicked at the crisp leaves at her feet."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "to wait until a later time to do something",
        "question": "EXPLAIN: delay CONTEXT: He decided to delay his decision until he had seen the full report.",
        "explanation": "[verb]",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Don’t delay – send off for the information now."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "lack of trust",
        "question": "отсутствие доверия",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "towards",
        "question": "(по направлению) к, на; указывает на местонахождение по отношению к другому предмету",
        "explanation": "[preposition] in the direction of someone or something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She stood up and walked towards him."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "overall",
        "question": "в целом",
        "explanation": "[adverb] considering everything or everyone",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "How would you rate the school overall?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "luggage",
        "question": "Багаж",
        "explanation": "[noun, uncountable]",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Excuse me, is this seat free?",
        "question": "Извините, это свободное место?",
        "explanation": "[seat] a place where you can sit, especially one in a vehicle or one from which you watch a performance, sports event etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I was in the back seat and Jo was driving."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "artist",
        "question": "художник",
        "explanation": "a person who creates paintings or drawings as a profession or hobby",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an exhibition of paintings by local artists"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "What is the trouble?",
        "question": "В чем проблема? (Что тебя беспокоит?)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "screen",
        "question": "экран",
        "explanation": "the part of a television or computer where the picture or information appears",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a computer with an 18-inch colour screen",
            "I spend most of my day working in front of a computer screen."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Bus route",
        "question": "Автобусный маршрут",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "hurry",
        "question": "спешить, торопить",
        "explanation": "[verb] to do something or go somewhere more quickly than usual, especially because there is not much time",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "If we hurry, we’ll get there in time."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Would she like to play with us?",
        "question": "Она хотела бы поиграть с нами?",
        "explanation": "We use “would like” or “‘d like to” to say politely what we want, especially when making offers or requests. Verbs that follow would like are in the to-infinitive form.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Believe it or not, but",
        "question": "верите или нет, но",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sustain",
        "question": "поддерживать, не дать прекратиться",
        "explanation": "[verb] to cause or allow something to continue for a period of time",
        "source": "Living with the gods: the protectoresses",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The team may not be able to sustain this level of performance."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "entire day",
        "question": "весь день",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am sorry",
        "question": "which phrase to use when you admit that what you did was wrong and feel remorse for your actions",
        "explanation": "I am sorry is a phrase that is used to express regret or remorse for actions.  I am sorry is also used when you wish to express sympathy for someone who has experienced a loss or hardship. I apologize is a way to formally admit that you did something wrong, whether you feel \"sorry\" about it or not. So while you might formally admit that what you did was wrong, you might not actually feel remorse for your actions.",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "please, switch on",
        "question": "пожалуйста, включите",
        "explanation": "switch something off (or on) {turn an electrical device off (or on)} [she switched on the kettle.]",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am hungry",
        "question": "я голоден",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "personal",
        "question": "личный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] relating to or belonging to a particular person",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I can only speak from my own personal experience.",
            "Please ensure you take all personal belongings with you when you leave the train."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Do not worry, I will wait for you.",
        "question": "Не волнуйся, я буду ждать тебя.",
        "explanation": "[I will wait for you] This sentence is an example of Simple Future Tense, which shows that an event will happen in future. It is generally not used with a time reference. It is simply that you will do this in future in a general way (i.e. without stating or referencing a specific future time).",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "hum a tune",
        "question": "напевать мелодию",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She was humming a little tune to herself."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "supplant",
        "question": "выжить, вытеснить",
        "explanation": "[verb] (formal) If a person or thing is supplanted, another person or thing takes their place.",
        "source": "code complete by steve mcconnell",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "domestic production has been supplanted by imports and jobs have been lost."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "interpretation",
        "question": "толкование",
        "explanation": "[noun] the way in which someone explains or understands an event, information, someone’s actions etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "One possible interpretation is that they want you to resign.",
            "What exactly the author meant by that statement is open to interpretation (=able to be understood or explained in different ways)."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "we are glad to see you",
        "question": "рады вас видеть",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "about five o'clock",
        "question": "около пяти часов",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "What day is it today?",
        "question": "Какой сегодня день?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "affection",
        "question": "привязанность",
        "explanation": "[noun] a feeling of liking or loving someone",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Ann's affection for her grandfather was obvious.",
            "Their father never showed them much affection."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "The sea is stormy",
        "question": "Море штормит",
        "explanation": "Use \"the\" before the names of rivers, oceans, seas and groups of lakes. For e.g., the Nile, the English channel, the Atlantic, the Great Lakes. Do not use \"the\" before the names of lakes and bays. For e.g., Lake Geneva, Lake Erie.",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "crown",
        "question": "корона",
        "explanation": "[noun] a round object made of gold and jewels (= valuable stones) that a king or queen wears on their head",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Are you getting off at the next stop?",
        "question": "Вы выходите на следующей остановке?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Is this nearby?",
        "question": "Это близко?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "bag",
        "question": "пакет",
        "explanation": "[noun] a container made of paper, cloth, or thin plastic, that usually opens at the top",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a paper bag",
            "a garbage bag"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "main",
        "question": "основной",
        "explanation": "[adjective] larger or more important than all other things, ideas etc of the same kind",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The main reason for living in Spain is the weather.",
            "the main problem",
            "The main airport is 15 miles from the capital."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sticking point",
        "question": "камень преткновения (without an article)",
        "explanation": "[noun] something that a group of people cannot agree on and that stops them from making progress",
        "source": "software testing: a craftsman's approach",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "North Korea’s refusal had long been a sticking point."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "duvet",
        "question": "пуховое одеяло",
        "explanation": "[noun] a large cloth bag filled with feathers or similar material that you use to cover yourself in bed",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "She filled the kettle and switched it on.",
        "question": "Она наполнила чайник и включила его.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "not very soon",
        "question": "не очень скоро",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "If you need any help, I could come over tonight.",
        "question": "Если тебе нужна любая помощь, я мог бы придти вечером.",
        "explanation": "[come over] if someone comes over, they visit you at your house",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Do you want to come over on Friday evening?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "so-so",
        "question": "так себе",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "source",
        "question": "источник",
        "explanation": "[noun] where something comes from",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Oranges are a good source of vitamin C."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "offer credit",
        "question": "предложить кредит",
        "explanation": "an arrangement with a shop, bank etc that allows you to buy something and pay for it later",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Most new cars are bought on credit."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "traffic noise",
        "question": "транспортный шум",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "You get a lot of traffic noise living here."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i hope, i will see you soon",
        "question": "надеюсь, я скоро тебя увижу",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "quarter to two",
        "question": "без четверти два",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "There were a lot of tourists on the train.",
        "question": "В поезде было много туристов.",
        "explanation": "If you can walk onto it and stand up inside, you say “get on”. If not, you say “get in”. This rule is especially illustrated by vehicles where we could use either “in/out” or “on/off”, depending on the size of the vehicle. We normally say “get on an airplane” but if you have a small, single-engine airplane, you would normally say “get in”. The same goes for boats, where we get on a large ship, but get in a canoe. This is also true for helicopters, submarines and spaceships.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "on Monday",
        "question": "в понедельник",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "eggplant",
        "question": "баклажан",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "purchase",
        "question": "приобретать что-л. за деньги (покупать) [формальное слово]",
        "explanation": "[verb] [formal] to buy something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Where did you purchase the car?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "white",
        "question": "белый",
        "explanation": "[adjective] of the colour of milk or fresh snow, due to the reflection of all visible rays of light; the opposite of black",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a sheet of white paper",
            "her face was white with fear"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "leaf tea",
        "question": "листовой чай.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sow the seeds",
        "question": "сеять семена",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "pretty well, thank you",
        "question": "ничего, спасибо (в ресторане)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "hot- cold",
        "question": "горячий- холодный",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "are you free on saturday?",
        "question": "вы свободны в субботу?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Are we still on for tonight?",
        "question": "Всё в силе на сегодняшний вечер?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "the area inside the entrance of a hotel, an office building, etc. where guests or visitors go first when they arrive.",
        "question": "Explain: reception. Context: I asked the man at reception.",
        "explanation": "[noun, uncountable] without an article",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "tour",
        "question": "путешествие, турне",
        "explanation": "[noun] a visit to and around a place, area, or country",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a tour of Europe",
            "We went on a guided tour of the cathedral.",
            "The band are on tour (= travelling and performing in different places)."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "meeting is over",
        "question": "встреча закончилась (without an article)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "shower curtain",
        "question": "занавеска для душа",
        "explanation": "for keeping the water in the shower",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "show me, please",
        "question": "покажите мне, пожалуйста (надобность)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "rubbish",
        "question": "мусор (это слово чаще всего используется в британском английском)",
        "explanation": "food, paper etc that is no longer needed and has been thrown away",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a rubbish bin"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "bean",
        "question": "боб",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "version",
        "question": "версия, вариант",
        "explanation": "[noun] one form of something that is slightly different to other forms of the same thing",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I saw the original version of the film."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "homage",
        "question": "дань, уважение, почтение",
        "explanation": "Homage is respect shown towards someone or something you admire, or to a person in authority.",
        "source": "Operating Systems: Three Easy Pieces",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sprinkling",
        "question": "a small thinly distributed amount of something",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "Woe is I Jr",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "hour",
        "question": "час",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I am here to pick up my order.",
        "question": "Я здесь, чтобы забрать свой заказ.",
        "explanation": "[pick something up] to collect something from a place",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I’ll pick my things up later.",
            "She just dropped by to pick up her mail."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "flat tyre",
        "question": "спущенная шина",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "bane of my life",
        "question": "проклятие моей жизни (отрава моей жизни)",
        "explanation": "Bane means poison (wolfbane is a kind of poisonous plant), but the word is usually used figuratively. To say that someone is the bane of your existence is to say that that person poisons your enjoyment of life.",
        "source": "word smart",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Her brother is the bane of her life."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "loud crash",
        "question": "сильный грохот",
        "explanation": "a sudden loud noise made by something falling, breaking etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I heard a loud crash."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "anything",
        "question": "что-нибудь (в вопросительных и условных предложениях); ничто, ничего (в отрицательных предложениях); всё; всё, что угодно (в утвердительных предложениях)",
        "explanation": "[pronoun] used in questions and negatives to mean 'something'; any object, event, or situation;",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I don't have anything to wear.",
            "Was there anything else (= another thing) you wanted to say?",
            "We can do anything you like.",
            "Tom will eat anything."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "perceive",
        "question": "воспринимать, понимать, осознавать",
        "explanation": "[verb] (written) to understand or think of something or someone in a particular way; (formal) to noice, see or recognize something",
        "source": "code complete by steve mcconnell",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "his mouth fell open as he perceived the truth"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "leader",
        "question": "лидер",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone or something that is winning during a race or other situation where people are competing",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Microsoft is a world leader in software design."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "excuse me, may i ask you?",
        "question": "простите, разрешите спросить вас?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "injure",
        "question": "повреждать, ушибать(ся)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to hurt yourself or someone else, for example in an accident or an attack",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Angus injured his leg playing rugby.",
            "Two people have been critically injured in an accident."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "permanent",
        "question": "постоянный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] continuing forever or for a long time",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a permanent job"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "dry irritating cough",
        "question": "сухой раздражающий кашель",
        "explanation": "[irritating] an irritating habit, situation etc keeps annoying you",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "with pleasure!",
        "question": "с удовольствием!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "student",
        "question": "студент",
        "explanation": "a person who is studying at a university or other place of higher education",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "curb",
        "question": "обуздывать, сдерживать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to limit or control something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "to curb crime/inflation"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "homage",
        "question": "special honour or respect shown publicly",
        "explanation": "Daniel's films were a homage to her",
        "source": "Operating Systems: Three Easy Pieces",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i wish you happiness",
        "question": "желаю вам счастья",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "escape route",
        "question": "запасной выход",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "tremendously wealthy",
        "question": "чрезвычайно богатый",
        "explanation": "[adverb] very much",
        "source": "Highlights of Calculus",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "this short list of the great functions is tremendously valuable."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "grain of truth",
        "question": "доля правды (without an article)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "beet",
        "question": "свекла",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "row",
        "question": "грести, работать вёслами (to make a boat move across water using oars)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She rowed across the lake.",
            "Why don’t we go for a row?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "I seem to recall",
        "question": "Я, кажется, припоминаю",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my father-in-law",
        "question": "это мой свёкор/тесть",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i do not object",
        "question": "я не возражаю",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "guest speaker",
        "question": "приглашенный оратор (приглашенный докладчик)",
        "explanation": "[speaker] (оратор, докладчик) someone who makes a speech to a group of people",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "trust",
        "question": "доверие",
        "explanation": "[noun] a strong belief in the honesty, goodness etc of someone or something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "At first there was a lack of trust between them.",
            "an agreement made on the basis of mutual trust (=when people trust each other)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "a hangover from the old days.",
        "question": "пережиток старого времени (with an article)",
        "explanation": "[a hangover from something] something from the past that still exists or happens but is no longer necessary or useful",
        "source": "software testing: a craftsman's approach",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "This feeling was a hangover from her schooldays.",
            "an institution which is a hangover from Victorian times"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Turn the light on so I can see.",
        "question": "Включите свет, чтобы я мог видеть.",
        "explanation": "[see] (видеть) to notice or examine someone or something, using your eyes",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Can I see your ticket, please?",
            "The moment we saw the house, we knew we wanted to buy it."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "July",
        "question": "июль",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "She rubbed her forehead.",
        "question": "Она потерла лоб.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I called them to ask for more details.",
        "question": "Я позвонил им, чтобы узнать подробности.",
        "explanation": "If you ask for something, it means that you want someone to give you something.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "crash the car",
        "question": "разбить машину",
        "explanation": "to have an accident in a car, plane etc by violently hitting something else",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He was drunk when he crashed the car."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "wednesday",
        "question": "среда (день недели)",
        "explanation": "[noun] the day of the week after Tuesday and before Thursday",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "autumn",
        "question": "осень",
        "explanation": "[noun] the season of the year between summer and winter, when leaves fall from the trees",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I'm starting a new job in the autumn.",
            "autumn leaves"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "rare disease",
        "question": "редкое заболевание",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "tyre",
        "question": "шина",
        "explanation": "[noun] a thick rubber ring that fits around the wheel of a car, bicycle etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I made a run to the store.",
        "question": "Я сходил в магазин.",
        "explanation": "[to make a run] usually means to travel to a nearby location",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "We will be waiting for you on Sunday at six o'clock in the evening.",
        "question": "Мы будем ждать вас в воскресенье в шесть часов вечера.",
        "explanation": "[We will be waiting for you] This sentence is an example of Future Continuous Tense, which is used to express a continued or an ongoing action in future. It means you will do that at a specific future time.That specific time may or may not be stated, depending on the context.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "silver",
        "question": "серебро",
        "explanation": "[noun] a valuable, shiny, grey-white metal used to make coins and jewellery (symbol Ag)",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "silver and gold"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "first of all",
        "question": "прежде всего",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "How can I get from the train station to your office?",
        "question": "Как я могу добраться от жд вокзала до вашего офиса?",
        "explanation": "How can I get to your office from the train station?",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Can you turn the sound up?",
        "question": "Вы можете включить звук погромче? (can)",
        "explanation": "make a radio, television, etc louder",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "diminish",
        "question": "when the profits or advantages you are getting from smth stop increasing in relation to the effort you are making",
        "explanation": "Our efforts were producing diminishing returns",
        "source": "",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "carrot",
        "question": "морковь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "what are you going to do tonight?",
        "question": "что вы делаете сегодня вечером?",
        "explanation": "It is also possible to say What are you doing tonight? The former question asks about our intentions; the latter asks what our arrangements.",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "train crash",
        "question": "железнодорожная катастрофа",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "intention",
        "question": "намерение",
        "explanation": "[noun] something that you want and plan to do",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I have no intention of seeing him again."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "it is correct",
        "question": "правильно",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "plane crash",
        "question": "авиакатастрофа",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "fat- thin",
        "question": "толстый- тонкий",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Please, let me through",
        "question": "Пожалуйста, пропустите меня.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "public prosecutor",
        "question": "прокурор",
        "explanation": "a person, especially a public official, who institutes legal proceedings against someone",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "last year",
        "question": "в прошлом году",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "designer",
        "question": "конструктор",
        "explanation": "a person who plans the look or workings of something prior to it being made, by preparing drawings or plans",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "corn",
        "question": "кукуруза",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Why are you so rude to him?",
        "question": "Почему ты так груб с ним?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "kiwi",
        "question": "киви",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "mouth",
        "question": "рот",
        "explanation": "[noun] the part of your face which you put food into, or which you use for speaking",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He lifted his glass to his mouth.",
            "Liam was fast asleep with his mouth wide open."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sunset",
        "question": "заход солнца, закат, вечерняя заря",
        "explanation": "[noun] Sunset is the time in the evening when the sun disappears out of sight from the sky.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "sunset was still a couple of hours away."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "I have to take a bus.",
        "question": "Придется поехать на автобусе.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ground coffee",
        "question": "молотый кофе",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "invitation",
        "question": "приглашение",
        "explanation": "a written or verbal request inviting someone to go somewhere or to do something",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "beige",
        "question": "бежевый",
        "explanation": "[noun] a pale sandy fawn colour",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a beige raincoat"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "initiative",
        "question": "инициатива",
        "explanation": "[noun] the ability to make decisions and take action without waiting for someone to tell you what to do",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I wish my son would show more initiative.",
            "Don’t keep asking me for advice. Use your initiative."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "please",
        "question": "пожалуйста",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Today it is stuffy outdoors.",
        "question": "Сегодня на улице душно.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "The bathroom is next to Jack's room.",
        "question": "Ванная комната находится рядом с комнатой Джека. (with an article)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "chip",
        "question": "щепка",
        "explanation": "[noun] a small piece of wood, stone, metal etc that has been broken off something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a chocolate chip cookie (=one that contains small pieces of chocolate)",
            "Wood chips covered the floor of the workshop."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sore throat",
        "question": "больное горло (воспаленное горло)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I am sorry, did you say something?",
        "question": "Простите, вы что-то сказали?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Where is the nearest underground station?",
        "question": "Где ближайшая станция метро? (underground)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "polite",
        "question": "вежливый",
        "explanation": "[adjective] behaving in a way that is not rude and shows that you do not only think about yourself",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She was too polite to point out my mistake."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "to give a particular quality to something",
        "question": "impart sth to sth",
        "explanation": "[verb, formal] дава́ть, придава́ть",
        "source": "Genetic algorithms with python (Clinton Sheppard)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Use a piece of fresh ginger to impart a Far Eastern flavour to simple ingredients.",
            "The spice imparts an Eastern flavour to the dish."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "We are asking what kind of job he has.",
        "question": "When we ask, \"What does your father do?\", what are we asking?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "travel guide",
        "question": "туристический путеводитель",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "office",
        "question": "офис",
        "explanation": "[noun] a room or building where people work",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an office worker",
            "I never get to the office before nine."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sound",
        "question": "звук",
        "explanation": "[noun] something that you hear or that can be heard",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I could hear the sounds of the city through the open window.",
            "She stood completely still, not making a sound."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sea",
        "question": "море",
        "explanation": "[noun] a large area of salt water",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I'd like to live by the sea.",
            "It was our third day at sea (= travelling on the sea).",
            "It's cheaper to send parcels by sea (= on a ship)."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "school",
        "question": "школа",
        "explanation": "[noun] a place where children go to be educated",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "necessary",
        "question": "необходимый, нужный",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Use must when you say what you think is necessary when you are giving your opinion."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "handy",
        "question": "удобный (для пользования)",
        "explanation": "[adjective] useful",
        "source": "software testing: a craftsman's approach",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It’s quite a handy little tool.",
            "It’s very handy having a light above your desk."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "tap water",
        "question": "водопроводная вода",
        "explanation": "water that comes out of a tap (кран)",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The tap water is not safe to drink."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Do not worry about it!",
        "question": "Не волнуйтесь об этом!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "You have spelled my name wrong.",
        "question": "Вы неправильно написали моё имя.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i work as an editor",
        "question": "я работаю редактором",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I am so happy for you!",
        "question": "Я так рад за вас! (А вот это говорится абсолютно искренне)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "somehow",
        "question": "как-нибудь, тем или иным образом",
        "explanation": "[adverb] in a way which you do not know or do not understand",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Don't worry, we'll fix it somehow.",
            "Don’t worry, we’ll get the money back somehow."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "wall",
        "question": "стена",
        "explanation": "[noun] an upright flat structure made of stone or brick, that divides one area from another or surrounds an area",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the ancient city walls"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "I will wake you up when it is time to leave.",
        "question": "Я разбужу тебя, когда придет время уйти.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "speak",
        "question": "говорить",
        "explanation": "[verb] to say something using your voice",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "at midday",
        "question": "в полдень",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "please, call",
        "question": "пожалуйста, позовите",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sale",
        "question": "продажа",
        "explanation": "[noun] the act of selling something, or the time when something is sold",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The sale of alcohol is now banned."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "not later than Thursday",
        "question": "не позднее четверга",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "together",
        "question": "вместе",
        "explanation": "[adverb] with each other",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We went shopping together.",
            "They live together."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "somewhere",
        "question": "где-то, куда-то, откуда-то",
        "explanation": "[adverb] used to refer to a place when you do not know exactly where it is or when it is not important exactly where it is",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "They had difficulties finding somewhere to live."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "okay",
        "question": "ладно",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "from July till September",
        "question": "с июля по сентябрь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "menu",
        "question": "меню",
        "explanation": "[noun] a list of all the kinds of food that are available for a meal, especially in a restaurant",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Could we have the menu, please?",
            "Is there any fish on the menu?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "toilet",
        "question": "унитаз",
        "explanation": "[noun] a bowl that you sit on or stand near when you get rid of waste substances from your body",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He flushed the toilet (=pulled the handle so that water ran into the toilet to clean it)."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "compelling reasons",
        "question": "неопровержимые доводы",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "software testing: a craftsman's approach",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "cloakroom",
        "question": "гардероб",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Calendar",
        "question": "Календарь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "myriad",
        "question": "бесчисленный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] very many",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (Melanie Mitchell)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "myriad problems"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "teacher",
        "question": "учитель",
        "explanation": "a person who teaches, especially in a school",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "influence",
        "question": "влияние",
        "explanation": "[noun] the power to affect how someone thinks or behaves, or how something develops",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The drug companies have a lot of influence on doctors.",
            "As a scientist, his influence was immense."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "water shortage",
        "question": "нехватка воды",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "There is a severe water shortage in many parts of the country."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "consider a request",
        "question": "рассмотреть просьбу",
        "explanation": "[verb]",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "After carefully considering this request, the council rejected it."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "leather jacket",
        "question": "кожаная куртка",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "till May",
        "question": "до мая",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Jo should arrive home any minute now.",
        "question": "Джо должен приехать домой с минуты на минуту. [Jo]",
        "explanation": "Don't use a preposition after arrive in front of \"home\", \"here\", \"back\", \"there\", \"somewhere\", or \"anywhere\".",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "in January",
        "question": "в январе",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "curious",
        "question": "любопытный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] wanting to know or learn about something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I was curious about his life in India."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "level",
        "question": "уровень",
        "explanation": "A level is a position in a scale.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Dolphins show a high level of intelligence."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "An old technique to induce vomiting.",
        "question": "Старый трюк, чтобы вызвать рвоту.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book, afterthought.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "salary",
        "question": "оклад, заработная плата",
        "explanation": "[noun] money that you receive as payment from the organization you work for, usually paid to you every month",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The average salary for a teacher is $39,000 a year."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "wish",
        "question": "пожелание",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Things happen.",
        "question": "Всякое бывает.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "background",
        "question": "происхождение, биографические данные; связи, окружение (всё, что связано с жизнью человека)",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone’s family, education, previous work etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Students with a background in chemistry will probably find the course easier.",
            "It’s important to understand other people, people from different backgrounds.",
            "She came from a middle-class background."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Your shoelaces are undone.",
        "question": "У тебя шнурки развязались.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "national pride",
        "question": "национальная гордость",
        "explanation": "[adjective] pride in your country",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "A flag is a symbol of national pride."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "a fervent supporter of human rights",
        "question": "ярыи сторонник прав человека",
        "explanation": "[adjective] believing or feeling something very strongly or sincerely",
        "source": "Word smart.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "can you speak italian?",
        "question": "вы говорите по-итальянски?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "corporal punishment",
        "question": "телесные наказания",
        "explanation": "[adjective] =when someone punishes a child by hitting them",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Corporal punishment is banned in state schools."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "secret compartment",
        "question": "секретное отделение (потайное отделение)",
        "explanation": "[secret] (тайный) known about by only a few people and kept hidden from others",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "They kept their relationship secret from their parents."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "lose your way",
        "question": "заблудиться",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He lost his way in the fog."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "It is very kind of you!",
        "question": "Это очень мило с вашей стороны!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "image",
        "question": "имидж",
        "explanation": "[noun] the idea that people have about what something is like, especially when this is created through newspaper stories, advertising etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The aim is to improve the public image of the police."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "patti took up the story where sue had left off",
        "question": "патти продолжила рассказ с места где остановилась сью. (Patti, Sue)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "Germany: Memories of a Nation- Divided Heaven",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "curl",
        "question": "локон, завиток",
        "explanation": "something with a small, curved shape, especially a piece of hair",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a child with blonde curls"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "What do you know!",
        "question": "Кто бы мог подумать!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "midday",
        "question": "полдень",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "search",
        "question": "искать, обыскивать",
        "explanation": "to try to find someone or something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I've searched my bedroom but I can't find my watch."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "lazy",
        "question": "ленивый",
        "explanation": "[adjective] Someone who is lazy does not like working or using any effort.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He's too lazy to make his bed in the morning."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "decade",
        "question": "десятилетие",
        "explanation": "[noun] a period of ten years",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I've been at the top in television for a decade, you see, Blanche."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "I will have a look",
        "question": "Я посмотрю",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "can you speak german?",
        "question": "вы говорите по-немецки?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am farit",
        "question": "меня зовут фарит",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "luminary",
        "question": "книжн. светило (науки, литературы); звезда (экрана, сцены и т. п.); знаменитость",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone who is very famous or highly respected for their skill at doing something or their knowledge of a particular subject",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ostensibly",
        "question": "якобы",
        "explanation": "[adverb] if something is ostensibly true, people say that it is true but it is not really true",
        "source": "Word smart.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She stayed behind at the office, ostensibly to work.",
            "A stranger came to the door, ostensibly to ask for directions."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "I am leaving for home.",
        "question": "Я уезжаю домой.",
        "explanation": "We use the present continuous to describe an event in the future which has already been arranged by the time of speaking",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "source of pride",
        "question": "предмет гордости",
        "explanation": "[phrase] a reason to feel proud",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The Chinese Olympic Games were a source of pride to the whole country."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "trace",
        "question": "обнаруживать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to find someone or something that was lost",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Police have so far failed to trace the missing woman.",
            "She had given up all hope of tracing her missing daughter."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "ordeal",
        "question": "суровое испытание",
        "explanation": "a very unpleasant and prolonged experience: the ordeal of having to give evidence.",
        "source": "Living with the Gods: Water of Life and Death.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "object",
        "question": "предмет",
        "explanation": "[noun] a thing that you can see or touch but that is usually not alive",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an everyday object such as a spoon",
            "a small metal object"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "traffic flow",
        "question": "транспортный поток",
        "explanation": "the steady movement of traffic",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The road widening should help to improve traffic flow."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "An excerpt is a short piece of writing or music which is taken from a larger piece.",
        "question": "excerpt",
        "explanation": "[noun, countable] отрывок, выдержка",
        "source": "Complexity: A guided tour (Melanie Mitchell)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The following excerpt is from one of my students' essays.",
            "The author is grateful to the following publishers for permission to reprint excerpts from the following works that appear as epigraphs in the book."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "psychotherapist",
        "question": "психотерапевт",
        "explanation": "a person who treats mental disorders by psychological rather than medical means",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "lawyer",
        "question": "адвокат",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "assure",
        "question": "заверять",
        "explanation": "[verb] to tell someone that something is definitely true, especially so that they do not worry",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She assured them that she would be all right."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "via",
        "question": "посредством (чего-л.), с помощью (чего-л.), через",
        "explanation": "travelling through a place on the way to another place; using a particular person, machine etc to send something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We flew to Athens via Paris.",
            "You can access our homepage via the Internet."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "currency exchange",
        "question": "Обмен валюты",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "culture",
        "question": "культура",
        "explanation": "[noun] the habits, traditions, and beliefs of a country, society, or group of people",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It's a good opportunity for children to learn about other cultures."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "craft fair",
        "question": "ремесленная ярмаркa",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "merry christmas!",
        "question": "счастливого рождества!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "permission",
        "question": "разрешение",
        "explanation": "[noun] If you give someone permission to do something, you allow them to do it.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She gave him permission without asking any questions."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "entrance",
        "question": "вход",
        "explanation": "[noun] a door or other opening that you use to enter a building or place",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "They must have used the back entrance to the building."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "naked",
        "question": "голый",
        "explanation": "[adjective] not wearing clothes or not covered by anything",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He was stark naked (= completely naked).",
            "a picture of a naked man"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Let's put on some music.",
        "question": "Давайте включим музыку.",
        "explanation": "[put on] to put a record, tape, or CD into a machine and start playing it",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She put on some music while they ate."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Tomorrow it will be cold.",
        "question": "Завтра будет холодно.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "The kettle is boiling. Please, make tea.",
        "question": "Чайник кипит. Пожалуйста, завари чаю (дословно переводиться как сделать чай).",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "rich- poor",
        "question": "богатый- бедный",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "what a sudden meeting!",
        "question": "какая неожиданная встреча!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "let's go to the concert",
        "question": "пойдёмте на концерт",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "He got in a taxi and left.",
        "question": "Он сел в такси и уехал. (a taxi)",
        "explanation": "If you can walk onto it and stand up inside, you say “get on”. If not, you say “get in”. This rule is especially illustrated by vehicles where we could use either “in” or “on”, depending on the size of the vehicle. We normally say “get on an airplane” but if you have a small, single-engine airplane, you would normally say “get in”. The same goes for boats, where we get on a large ship, but get in a canoe. This is also true for helicopters, submarines and spaceships.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "fashion designer",
        "question": "модельер",
        "explanation": "a person who designs high-fashion clothing",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sample",
        "question": "образец",
        "explanation": "[noun] a small part or amount of something that is examined in order to find out something about the whole",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I’d like to see some samples of your work."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "secondary issue",
        "question": "второстепенный вопрос",
        "explanation": "[secondary] not as important as something else",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the novel’s secondary characters",
            "Price is the most important factor for us- location is a secondary issue."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "spout",
        "question": "носик, горлышко (у сосуда)",
        "explanation": "[noun] a small pipe on the side of a container that you pour liquid out through",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the spout of a teapot"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "see you later",
        "question": "informal saying of goodbye",
        "explanation": "an expression of farewell",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "kettle",
        "question": "чайник (для кипячения воды)",
        "explanation": "[noun] a container with a lid, a handle, and a spout, used for boiling and pouring water",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She filled the kettle and switched it on.",
            "The kettle’s boiling (=the water in it is boiling).",
            "Put the kettle on (=start boiling water in a kettle), will you?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "award",
        "question": "награда",
        "explanation": "[noun] a prize given to someone for something they have achieved",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the award for best actress",
            "to receive/win an award"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "identify",
        "question": "опознавать, устанавливать личность",
        "explanation": "[verb] to recognize someone or something and say or prove who or what they are",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He was too far away to be able to identify faces."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "baby",
        "question": "малыш",
        "explanation": "[noun] a very young child",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "baby clothes",
            "The baby is crying."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i congratulate you on your birthday!",
        "question": "поздравляю вас с днём рождения!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Thursday",
        "question": "четверг",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "extremely important and needing to be done or dealt with immediately",
        "question": "EXPLAIN: imperative CONTEXT: It is imperative that I speak with him at once.",
        "explanation": "[adjective] When something absolutely has to be done and cannot be put off, use the adjective imperative. Imperative is from Latin imperare \"to command,\" and its original use was for a verb form expressing a command: \"Do it!\" is an imperative sentence. It's still used that way, but it's more commonly applied to something so pressing it cannot be put off: \"Hiring new workers has become imperative.\" It has more immediate force than pressing but less than urgent.",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It is imperative that politicians should be good communicators.",
            "It is imperative to meet face to face with the client."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Lucky you!",
        "question": "Повезло тебе!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "fig",
        "question": "инжир",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "routine",
        "question": "заведенный порядок, режим, рутина",
        "explanation": "the usual order in which you do things, or the things you regularly do",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "my daily exercise routine"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "I would like to",
        "question": "You must have dinner with us. Yes, ...",
        "explanation": "We can use \"I would like to (I'd like to)\" as a short answer to an offer or invitation.",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "technical malfunction",
        "question": "Техническая неисправность",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "where do your parents work?",
        "question": "где работают ваши родители?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "yolk",
        "question": "желток",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "rubbish dump",
        "question": "помойка (мусорная свалка)",
        "explanation": "We can also say: a rubbish tip (British English)",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I rescued this table from a rubbish dump."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "ideally",
        "question": "в идеале",
        "explanation": "[adverb] used to describe the way you would like things to be, even though this may not be possible",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Ideally, I'd like to work at home.",
            "Fruit and vegetables should ideally be organically grown."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "implication",
        "question": "последствие",
        "explanation": "[noun] a possible future effect or result of an action, event, decision etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "This scheme has serious implications for the local economy."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "What is water temperature today?",
        "question": "Какая сегодня температура воды?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "state fair",
        "question": "ярмарка штата",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "We are asking about his activity right now.",
        "question": "When we ask, \"What is your father doing?\", what are we asking?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "this week",
        "question": "на этой недели",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "for various reasons",
        "question": "по разным причинам",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He decided to leave school for various reasons."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "what can i do for you?",
        "question": "что я могу для вас сделать?",
        "explanation": "[spoken] used humorously to ask someone how you can help them, especially when you are trying to sell them something",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sheet of paper",
        "question": "лист бумаги",
        "explanation": "[sheet] a thin flat piece of something such as paper, glass, or metal",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a blank sheet of paper"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "uninhabited island",
        "question": "необитаемый остров",
        "explanation": "[uninhabited] one where nobody lives",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "There are over a thousand uninhabited islands in the seas around Greece."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "from half past two up to three o'clock",
        "question": "от половины третьего до трёх",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Which colour shoes should I wear with this dress- blue or black?",
        "question": "Какого цвета обувь я должна носить с этим платьем- синие или черные?",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "well known",
        "question": "широко известный",
        "explanation": "known by a lot of people",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It’s a well-known fact that smoking can cause lung cancer."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "twice",
        "question": "дважды, два раза",
        "explanation": "[adverb] two times",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I have been there twice."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "He carried our luggage to our room.",
        "question": "Он нес наш багаж в нашу комнату.",
        "explanation": "Luggage is an uncountable noun and is not used in the plural.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "punishment",
        "question": "наказание",
        "explanation": "[noun] something that is done to punish someone",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I was sent to bed as a punishment."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "special care",
        "question": "особая забота",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "How much does a ticket cost?",
        "question": "Сколько стоит билет?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "criticize",
        "question": "критиковать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to say that something or someone is bad",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The film was criticized for being too violent."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "cheese",
        "question": "сыр",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sooner or later",
        "question": "рано или поздно",
        "explanation": "used to say that you do not know exactly when something will happen, but you are sure that it will happen",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Sooner or later they'll realize that it's not going to work."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "perish",
        "question": "погибать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to die",
        "source": "Living with the gods: the protectoresses",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Hundreds of people perished in the flood."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "tube",
        "question": "труба, трубка",
        "explanation": "[noun] a round pipe made of metal, glass, rubber etc, especially for liquids or gases to go through",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "on the contrary",
        "question": "наоборот, напротив",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I am pleased.",
        "question": "Я рад",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "second",
        "question": "второй",
        "explanation": "[adjective] the second person, thing, event etc is the one that comes after the first",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a second year student",
            "the second half of the year"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "evidence bears out this idea",
        "question": "данные подтверждают эту идею (without an article)",
        "explanation": "if facts or information bear out a claim, story, opinion etc, they help to prove that it is true",
        "source": "software testing: a craftsman's approach",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Evidence bears out the idea that students learn best in small groups."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "he likes",
        "question": "Restore the invisible part: Garfield likes chocolate-chip cookie dough more than me.",
        "explanation": "than I or than me - could be correct, depending on what you mean. It all becomes clear when you mentally restore the invisible parts.",
        "source": "Woe is I Jr.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "elicit",
        "question": "допытываться, добиваться",
        "explanation": "[verb] to succeed in getting information or a reaction from someone, especially when this is difficult",
        "source": "From Frequency to Meaning: Vector Space Models of Semantics.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "You have to ask the right questions to elicit the information you want.",
            "The test uses pictures to elicit words from the child.",
            "Calls to dozens of independent agents elicited similar responses."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "it is too late, i have to go",
        "question": "уже очень поздно, мне пора идти",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "pineapple",
        "question": "ананас",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "picky",
        "question": "разборчивый",
        "explanation": "[adjective, informal] someone who is picky only likes particular things and not others, and so is not easy to please",
        "source": "software testing: a craftsman's approach",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He’s a very picky eater."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "tea in bags",
        "question": "чай в пакетиках",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "landscape",
        "question": "ландшафт",
        "explanation": "[noun, countable] The landscape is everything you can see when you look across an area of land, including hills, rivers, buildings, trees, and plants.",
        "source": "Hands-on machine learning with Scikit-learn and TensorFlow",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the beauty of the New England landscape",
            "The island's landscape is similar to Hawaii's."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "to refer to someone already mentioned",
        "question": "What is the purpose of the self word, myself, in the following sentence: I looked at myself in the mirror.",
        "explanation": "The self words, myself, yourself, herself, himself, themselves, are used for two purposes: to emphasize something; to refer to someone already mentioned.",
        "source": "Woe is i jr.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "suite",
        "question": "two separate ... within the same apartment",
        "explanation": "a set of rooms designated for one person's or family's use or for a particular purpose",
        "source": "The diary of a young girl by Anne Frank ",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "We got out of the car to see what had happened.",
        "question": "Мы вышли из машины, чтобы посмотреть, что произошло.",
        "explanation": "If you can walk onto it and stand up inside, you say “get on”. If not, you say “get in”. This rule is especially illustrated by vehicles where we could use either “in/out” or “on/off”, depending on the size of the vehicle. We normally say “get on an airplane” but if you have a small, single-engine airplane, you would normally say “get in”. The same goes for boats, where we get on a large ship, but get in a canoe. This is also true for helicopters, submarines and spaceships.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my mother",
        "question": "это моя мама",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "make an attempt",
        "question": "сделать попытку",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "We played",
        "question": "Мы играли. (Past Simple)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "translation",
        "question": "перевод, переведенное произведение",
        "explanation": "[noun] something that has been translated from one language to another, or the process of translating",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I’ve only read ‘Madame Bovary’ in translation (=not in its original language)."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "arrow",
        "question": "стрелка",
        "explanation": "[noun] a symbol used on signs to show a direction",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i wish you success",
        "question": "желаю вам успехов",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "soft- hard",
        "question": "мягкий- жесткий",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "suspense",
        "question": "напряжение, тревога ожидания",
        "explanation": "[noun] the feeling of excitement or anxiety that you have when you are waiting for something to happen",
        "source": "Highlights of Calculus",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "What's your answer then? Don't keep me in suspense.",
            "She couldn’t bear the suspense a moment longer."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "see you soon",
        "question": "used for saying goodbye to someone you are going to meet again soon",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "He asked for help.",
        "question": "Он попросил помощи.",
        "explanation": "If you ask for something, it means that you want someone to give you something.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "what is more",
        "question": "более того",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "jaw",
        "question": "[Скелет человека] челюсть",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "offensive",
        "question": "обидный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] likely to make people angry or upset",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an offensive remark"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "elicit a positive response",
        "question": "получить положительный отклик (ответ)",
        "explanation": "[verb] If you elicit a response or a reaction, you do or say something that makes other people respond or react.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Mr. Norris said he was hopeful that his request would elicit a positive response."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "establish a reputation",
        "question": "создать себе репутацию",
        "explanation": "[verb] make people accept that you are good at doing something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "By then Picasso was already establishing his reputation as an artist."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "may i smoke?",
        "question": "можно закурить?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "authority",
        "question": "власть",
        "explanation": "[noun] the official power to make decisions or to control other people",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We need the support of someone in authority."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sole distributor",
        "question": "эксклюзивный дистрибьютор (единственный дистрибьютор)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "For example, the business may be the sole distributor of certain products within the United Kingdom."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "It is on at the cinema in town this week.",
        "question": "На этой недели он (фильм) идет в кинотеатре в городе.",
        "explanation": "\"In town\" is understood to mean \"in our town\". \"In the town\", on the other hand, requires the mention of a specific town.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "may i look at?",
        "question": "можно посмотреть?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "unabashedly",
        "question": "бессовестно",
        "explanation": "[adverb] without embarrassment or shame",
        "source": "Word smart.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "he was staring unabashedly at her",
            "the film presents an unabashedly biased point of view."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "mostly",
        "question": "главным образом, по большей части (used to talk about most members of a group, most occasions, most parts of something etc)",
        "explanation": "[adverb] mainly or most of the time",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She reads mostly romantic novels.",
            "Green teas are mostly from China or Japan."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "driver",
        "question": "водитель",
        "explanation": "a person who drives a vehicle",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "how are you?",
        "question": "как живёте? (formal)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "a scorching hot week in August",
        "question": "палящая жаркая неделя в Августе (article: a)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "terse",
        "question": "сжатый, краткий (о стиле)",
        "explanation": "[adjective] a terse reply, message etc uses very few words and often shows that you are annoyed",
        "source": "software testing: a craftsman's approach",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Derek’s terse reply ended the conversation."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i want to",
        "question": "мне нужно (надобность)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "month",
        "question": "месяц",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Please, send someone for the things.",
        "question": "Пожалуйста, пришлите кого-нибудь за вещами.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "How to turn an air conditioner on?",
        "question": "Как включить кондиционер?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "illness",
        "question": "болезнь",
        "explanation": "[noun] a disease of the body or mind, or the condition of being ill",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She had all the normal childhood illnesses."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "take pride in",
        "question": "испытывать гордость за",
        "explanation": "[verb] feel proud of something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She takes pride in her beautiful gardens.",
            "He takes great pride in his children’s achievements."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "door handle",
        "question": "дверная ручка",
        "explanation": "We don’t usually use the possessive ’s with things: Not: the door’s handle.",
        "source": "common mistakes at ket",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "mutton",
        "question": "баранина (мясо)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "thick- thin",
        "question": "густой- жидкий",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "greeting",
        "question": "приветствие",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i need an interpreter",
        "question": "мне нужен переводчик",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Sunday",
        "question": "воскресенье",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "bacteria",
        "question": "бактерия",
        "explanation": "[noun] very small living things that sometimes cause disease. the simplest and smallest forms of life. Bacteria exist in large numbers in air, water and soil, and also in living and dead creatures and plants, and are often a cause of disease.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Neither chilling nor freezing kills all bacteria."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "garden",
        "question": "сад",
        "explanation": "[noun] the area of land next to a house, where there are flowers, grass, and other plants, and often a place for people to sit",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He’s outside in the garden."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "good luck",
        "question": "счастливо",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Thank you in advance!",
        "question": "Спасибо заранее!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "weekend",
        "question": "выходные дни",
        "explanation": "[noun] Saturday and Sunday, the two days in the week when many people do not work",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Are you doing anything this weekend?",
            "I'm going home for the weekend."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "psychologist",
        "question": "психолог",
        "explanation": "an expert or specialist in psychology (the scientific study of the human mind and its functions, especially those affecting behaviour in a given context)",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "weather",
        "question": "погода",
        "explanation": "[noun] the temperature or conditions outside, for example if it is hot, cold, sunny, etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The flight was delayed because of bad weather."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "This way, please!",
        "question": "Сюда, пожалуйста!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "help me, please!",
        "question": "помогите мне, пожалуйста!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "stand-in",
        "question": "so a pronoun is a ... for a noun",
        "explanation": "a person who stands in for another, especially in a match or performance; a substitute",
        "source": "Woe is I Jr",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "imagine",
        "question": "представлять себе, воображать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to form a picture or idea in your mind about what something could be like",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Imagine that you have just won a million pounds.",
            "Imagine life without hot water."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "curvature of the spine",
        "question": "искривление позвоночника",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I got on the bus at the station.",
        "question": "Я сел в автобус на станции.",
        "explanation": "If you can walk onto it and stand up inside, you say “get on”. If not, you say “get in”. This rule is especially illustrated by vehicles where we could use either “in/out” or “on/off”, depending on the size of the vehicle. We normally say “get on an airplane” but if you have a small, single-engine airplane, you would normally say “get in”. The same goes for boats, where we get on a large ship, but get in a canoe. This is also true for helicopters, submarines and spaceships.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "soap can irritate skin",
        "question": "мыло может раздражать кожу",
        "explanation": "[irritate] to make a part of your body painful and sore",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "This cream may irritate sensitive skin."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "mouse",
        "question": "мышь",
        "explanation": "[noun] (plural mice /maɪs/) a small furry animal with a pointed nose and a long tail that lives in people’s houses or in fields",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The cat laid a dead mouse at my feet.",
            "a field mouse"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "scissors",
        "question": "ножницы",
        "explanation": "[noun] a tool for cutting paper, hair, cloth, etc that you hold in your hand and that has two blades that move against each other",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a pair of sissors"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "I would like to have come to the party, but I was busy.",
        "question": "Я хотел приехать на вечеринку, но я был занят.",
        "explanation": "We use would like to have + -ed form when talking about things in the past that we have missed. (I wanted to come to the party, but I didn't.)",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "please, open",
        "question": "пожалуйста, откройте",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "temple",
        "question": "висок",
        "explanation": "[noun] one of the two fairly flat areas on each side of your forehead",
        "source": "The documentary podcast: the witch hunts of papua new guinea",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Let's stay in tonight and watch a movie.",
        "question": "Давай сегодня вечером останемся дома и посмотрим кино.",
        "explanation": "to spend the evening at home rather than go out",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I was tired, so I decided to stay in."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "mere",
        "question": "всего лишь",
        "explanation": "[adjective] used to emphasize how small or unimportant something or someone is",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He’s a mere child.",
            "It costs a mere twenty dollars."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "mustard",
        "question": "горчица",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "please, meet my husband",
        "question": "разрешите представить вам моего мужа (неофициальная форма)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "trial",
        "question": "судебный процесс",
        "explanation": "[noun] a legal process in which a judge and often a jury in a court of law examine information to decide whether someone is guilty of a crime",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The two men are now on trial for attempted murder."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "immediate future",
        "question": "ближайшее будущее",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "skin",
        "question": "[наружный покров тела] кожа",
        "explanation": "[noun] the natural outer layer of a person’s or animal’s body",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She had thick black hair and smooth dark skin."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "meeting",
        "question": "встреча",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "angry",
        "question": "сердитый",
        "explanation": "[adjective] feeling strong emotions which make you want to shout at someone or hurt them because they have behaved in an unfair, cruel, offensive etc way, or because you think that a situation is unfair, unacceptable etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I don't understand what he's angry about."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "imminent demise",
        "question": "неминуемая (неизбежная) кончина (смерть)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (Melanie Mitchell)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my father",
        "question": "это мой папа",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i have arrived with my husband and children",
        "question": "я приехала с мужем и детьми",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "irritate",
        "question": "раздражать (продолжительное время или постоянно. Annoy — это «раздражать» в более узком смысле. Обычно это раздражение «здесь и сейчас», не растянутое по времени. Annoy can not be used to refer to a physical sensation.)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to make someone feel annoyed or impatient, especially by doing something many times or for a long period of time",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It really irritates me when he doesn’t help around the house."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "poisonous",
        "question": "ядовитый",
        "explanation": "[adjective] containing poison",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "poisonous gas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "salty- tasteless",
        "question": "соленый- пресный",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "The inception of an institution or activity is the start of it.",
        "question": "inception",
        "explanation": "[noun, formal] начало, возникновение",
        "source": "A field guide to genetic programming.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Since its inception twenty years ago, GP has been used to solve a wide range of practical problems."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "tree",
        "question": "дерево",
        "explanation": "[noun] a very tall plant that has branches and leaves, and lives for many years",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "As a kid, I loved to climb trees.",
            "We planted a peach tree in the backyard."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "a new medical facility",
        "question": "новое медицинское учреждение (a new)",
        "explanation": "[noun] a place where a particular activity happens",
        "source": "The Oxford 3000",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "time",
        "question": "время",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "quarter of an hour",
        "question": "четверть часа",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "spine",
        "question": "[Скелет человека] позвоночник",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ally",
        "question": "союзник",
        "explanation": "[noun] a country that agrees to help or support another country in a war",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "debate continued among NATO allies."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "old- young",
        "question": "старый- молодой",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "affair",
        "question": "дело, ситуация",
        "explanation": "[noun] a situation or set of related events, especially bad ones",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The government's handling of the affair has been widely criticized.",
            "The whole affair was a disaster."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Sorry, I meant well.",
        "question": "Извините, я хотел как лучше.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "turn the water off",
        "question": "закройте (выключите) воду",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Turn the water off while you're brushing your teeth."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "goods",
        "question": "товары",
        "explanation": "items that are made to be sold",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "televisions, washing machines, and other electrical goods"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "to change an event to a later time or date",
        "question": "EXPLAIN: postpone CONTEXT: The meeting was postponed.",
        "explanation": "[verb] to change the date or time of a planned event or action to a later one",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The match had to be postponed until next week."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "rye bread",
        "question": "ржаной хлеб",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "deceive",
        "question": "обма́нывать; вводи́ть в заблужде́ние;",
        "explanation": "[verb] deliberately cause (someone) to believe something that is not true, especially for personal gain",
        "source": "Highlights of calculus.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I didn't intend to deceive people into thinking it was French champagne."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "train",
        "question": "поезд",
        "explanation": "[noun] a set of several carriages that are connected to each other and pulled along a railway line by an engine",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We could go by train.",
            "a train journey"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "clever- silly",
        "question": "умный- глупый",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "a companionable young man.",
        "question": "приветливый молодой человек",
        "explanation": "[adjective] friendly and pleasant to be with",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "traffic accident",
        "question": "дорожно-транспортное происшествие",
        "explanation": "Tom was injured in a traffic accident.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Where is the nearest bus stop?",
        "question": "Где ближайшая остановка автобуса?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Have you drunk the entire bottle?",
        "question": "ты выпил всю бутылку?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "in the evening, tonight",
        "question": "вечером, сегодня вечером",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "police",
        "question": "полиция",
        "explanation": "[noun] the official organization that makes people obey the law and that protects people and places against crime, or the people who work for this organization",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I heard a gun shot and decided to call the police.",
            "A 30-year-old taxi driver is being interviewed by police."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Light bulb is burned out.",
        "question": "Лампочка сгорела (without article)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "on one hand",
        "question": "с одной стороны",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "These shoes pinch my toes.",
        "question": "Эти ботинки жмут мои пальцы",
        "explanation": "[[pinch]] if something you are wearing pinches you, it presses painfully on part of your body, because it is too tight",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sole ownership",
        "question": "единоличное владение",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He now has sole ownership of the company."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "deliver a speech",
        "question": "произнести речь (выступить с речью)",
        "explanation": "[speech] (речь, выступление) a talk, especially a formal one about a particular subject, given to a group of people",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Could we have the bill, please?",
        "question": "Задание: Спросите счет в кафе.",
        "explanation": "Alternative choices: \"May we have the bill/check, please?\", \"Could we get the bill, please?\"",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "That is ok!",
        "question": "Все в порядке!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "please, close",
        "question": "пожалуйста, закройте",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "put on",
        "question": "to put a piece of clothing on your body",
        "explanation": "He took off his uniform and put on a sweater and trousers",
        "source": "Environment around you",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "son",
        "question": "сын",
        "explanation": "[noun] your male child",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "When would you like to meet?",
        "question": "Когда вы бы хотели встретится?",
        "explanation": "We use “would like” or “‘d like to” to say politely what we want, especially when making offers or requests. Verbs that follow would like are in the to-infinitive form.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "at weekends i kept my father company",
        "question": "по выходным я составлял компанию моему отцу",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "skirt",
        "question": "юбка",
        "explanation": "[noun] a piece of outer clothing worn by women and girls, which hangs down from the waist like the bottom part of a dress",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She wore a white blouse and a plain black skirt."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "pancake",
        "question": "блин",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "let me introduce you to my wife",
        "question": "разрешите представить вам мою жену (официальная форма)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ruin",
        "question": "уничтожать( to spoil or destroy something completely)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "This illness has ruined my life.",
            "His career would be ruined.",
            "All this mud’s going to ruin my shoes."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "lukewarm water",
        "question": "чуть теплая вода",
        "explanation": "lukewarm (=only slightly warm)",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The coffee was only lukewarm."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "entitle",
        "question": "давать кому-либо право на что-либо",
        "explanation": "[verb] to give someone the right to do or have something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I'm entitled to apply for citizenship.",
            "Full-time employees are entitled to receive health insurance."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Some people use horrendous to describe something that is so big or great that they find it extremely unpleasant",
        "question": "EXPLAIN: horrendous CONTEXT: The usually horrendous traffic jams.",
        "explanation": "[adjective] (чудовищный) [informal]",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "horrendously expensive"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "seal",
        "question": "пломба, печать",
        "explanation": "Seal is a tricky word since its meanings are so diverse. One type of seal lives in water, coming ashore to breed, give birth, and nurse their young. The largest type of seal — the elephant seal — can weigh 6,000 pounds! On the other hand, seal can also mean a stamp that may be placed on a document to show that the document is official and authentic. And, if you want to make sure that your document is safe in its envelope, you might need to seal (make tight) the envelope with some tape.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "take your time",
        "question": "Не торопитесь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "gamble",
        "question": "играть в азартные игры",
        "explanation": "[verb] to risk money or possessions on the result of something such as a card game or a race, when you do not know for certain what the result will be",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Jack loves gambling on the horses.",
            "Their religion forbids them to drink or gamble."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "We will play.",
        "question": "Мы будем играть. (Future Simple)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "lump of sugar",
        "question": "кусок сахара",
        "explanation": "[lump] a small piece of something solid or firm that does not have a regular shape",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Melt a lump of butter in your frying-pan."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "person",
        "question": "человек, личность",
        "explanation": "[noun] a human being",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "You're the only person I know here.",
            "He is a very dangerous person."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "involvement",
        "question": "причастность, участие",
        "explanation": "[noun] the state of being involved in an activity or event",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He denies any involvement in the attack."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Are you in line?",
        "question": "Вы в очереди?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "information",
        "question": "информация, сведения",
        "explanation": "[noun] facts about a situation, person, event, etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I need more information."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "ultimately",
        "question": "в конечном счёте, в конце концов",
        "explanation": "[adverb] finally, after everything else has been done or considered",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Ultimately, the decision rests with the child’s parents.",
            "a long but ultimately successful campaign"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "put in a request",
        "question": "подать запрос",
        "explanation": "[verb]",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He has put in a request for two weeks' holiday."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "nurse",
        "question": "медсестра",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone whose job is to look after people who are ill or injured, usually in a hospital",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The nurse is coming to give you an injection.",
            "The school nurse sent Sara home."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "persuade",
        "question": "убеждать (в чём-л.) уговорить (на что-л.)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to make someone agree to do something by talking to them a lot about it",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We managed to persuade him to come with us.",
            "I persuaded her that it was the right thing to do."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "surely",
        "question": "обязательно",
        "explanation": "used to show that you think something must be true, especially when people seem to be disagreeing with you",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "You must have heard about the riots, surely?",
            "There must surely be some explanation.",
            "Surely we can’t just stand back and let this happen?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "truth",
        "question": "правда; истина",
        "explanation": "[noun] the state or quality of being true",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Do you think he was telling the truth?",
            "I don't think we'll ever know the truth about what really happened."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "a written or spoken description that says what happens in an event or process",
        "question": "EXPLAIN: account CONTEXT: Chomsky's account of how children learn their first language.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "have you met?",
        "question": "вы знакомы?",
        "explanation": " make the acquaintance of (someone) for the first time",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "where is the nearest toilet here?",
        "question": "где здесь ближайший туалет?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i do not know, what time is it",
        "question": "я не знаю, который час",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "any news?",
        "question": "что нового? (какие новости?)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i was born in seventy-six",
        "question": "я семьдесят шестого года рождения",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "license",
        "question": "давать разрешение, лицензию",
        "explanation": "[verb] to give official permission for someone to do or produce something, or for an activity to take place",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a restaurant which is licensed to sell alcohol"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "immediate response",
        "question": "немедленная реакция, немедленный ответ",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Our immediate response to the attack was sheer horror.",
            "The situation called for an immediate response."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "creature",
        "question": "существо (живой организм)",
        "explanation": "[noun] anything that is living, such as an animal, fish, or insect, but not a plant",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "all the living creatures in the sea"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "associate",
        "question": "ассоциировать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to relate two things, people, etc in your mind",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Most people associate this brand with good quality."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "how are your children?",
        "question": "как дела у ваших детей?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "deserve credit for",
        "question": "заслуживают похвалы за",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i have arrived alone",
        "question": "я приехал один",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "critical",
        "question": "критический",
        "explanation": "[adjective] saying that someone or something is bad or wrong",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He is very critical of the way I work."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "anticipate",
        "question": "предвидеть",
        "explanation": "[verb] to expect something, or to prepare for something before it happens",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "to anticipate a problem"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "peanut",
        "question": "арахис",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "porter",
        "question": "Носильщик",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "rib",
        "question": "[Скелет человека] ребро",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "the quickest way",
        "question": "кратчайший путь",
        "explanation": "Which is the quickest way to the sea from here?",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i sympathize you very much!",
        "question": "очень вам сочувствую!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am seventeen",
        "question": "мне семнадцать лет",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I have forgotten the key in my room.",
        "question": "Я забыл свой ключ в номере.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "melon",
        "question": "дыня",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Please, have a car sent at 5 a.m",
        "question": "Пожалуйста, пришлите машину к 5 часам утра.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Change the towel, please",
        "question": "Смените полотенце, пожалуйста",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "victory",
        "question": "победа",
        "explanation": "[noun] a win in a fight or competition",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Today we have won an important victory."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "head-on crash",
        "question": "лобовое столкновение",
        "explanation": "in which the front of one vehicle directly hits the front of another",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She was involved in a head-on crash with a motorbike."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "vast",
        "question": "обширный; громадный; бескрайний;",
        "explanation": "[adjective] extremely large- used about areas, distances, numbers, or amounts",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The government will have to borrow vast amounts of money.",
            "vast areas of rainforest"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "You would do better to catch a bus.",
        "question": "Лучше поезжай на автобусе.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "They are certainly not mine.",
        "question": "Они, конечно, не мои.",
        "explanation": "without any doubt (syn. definitely)",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Amy’s certainly growing, but she’s not gaining weight.",
            "‘Is this his signature?’ ‘Almost certainly.’",
            "It’s certainly not the cheapest way of getting to New York."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "omnipresent",
        "question": "вездесущий",
        "explanation": "Present everywhere at all times.",
        "source": null,
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the omnipresence of God",
            "the omnipresent threat of natural disasters."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "He brought a friend who waited outside in the car.",
        "question": "Он привел друга, который ждал снаружи в машине. (the car)",
        "explanation": "Relative pronouns refer back to people (who, that, who, or whose), things or concepts (which, that, or whose), place (where), time( when), or explanation (what or why). When used as the subject of a sentence, the subject of a clause, or a subject complement, use \"who\" for people and \"which\" for everything else. That can be used in place of either who or which, but only with restrictive clauses.",
        "source": "Environment around you.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "nation",
        "question": "нация",
        "explanation": "[noun] a country or the people living in a country",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "industrial nations",
            "an independent nation"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sour",
        "question": "кислый, прокисший",
        "explanation": "[adjective] having a sharp, sometimes unpleasant, taste or smell, like a lemon, and not sweet",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "These plums are a bit sour."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i do not understand english",
        "question": "я не понимаю по-английски",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "chief",
        "question": "старший, главный (по званию)",
        "explanation": "[adjective] highest in rank",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He was recently appointed chief economist at the Bank of Scotland.",
            "the government’s chief medical officer"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "rowan berries",
        "question": "ягоды рябины",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Mushroom",
        "question": "Гриб",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "celery",
        "question": "сельдерей",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "initial",
        "question": "первоначальный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] happening at the beginning",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "My initial reaction was one of anger."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "let me introduce you to my friend",
        "question": "разрешите представить вам моего друга (официальная форма)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "high- low",
        "question": "высокий- низкий",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "We have plenty of space at home.",
        "question": "У нас много места в доме.",
        "explanation": "[space] (=empty area) the amount of an area, room, container etc that is empty or available to be used",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He had plenty of space to study."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "tooth",
        "question": "зуб",
        "explanation": "[noun] (plural teeth /tiːθ/) one of the hard, white objects in your mouth that you use for biting and crushing food",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "You should brush your teeth twice a day."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Say it again, please",
        "question": "Повторите еще раз, пожалуйста.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "dawn",
        "question": "рассвет",
        "explanation": "[noun] the first appearance of light in the sky before sunrise",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "he set off at dawn."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Should I run to the store?",
        "question": "Может, мне сходить в магазин?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "civic pride",
        "question": "гражданская гордость",
        "explanation": "[adjective] pride in your town or city",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The museum is a vital source of civic pride."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "lung",
        "question": "(анат.) лёгкое",
        "explanation": "[noun] one of the two organs in your body that you breathe with",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Smoking can cause lung cancer."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i study at a philological faculty",
        "question": "я учусь на филологическом факультете",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "rescue",
        "question": "спасать",
        "explanation": "to save someone from a dangerous or unpleasant situation",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Fifty passengers had to be rescued from a sinking ship."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "currant",
        "question": "смородина",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Good for you!",
        "question": "Тем лучше для вас! (В этой фразе многое зависит от интонации, часто в ней подразумевается сарказм: «Ну-ну, рад за тебя!»)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i agree",
        "question": "я согласен",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "my birthday is very soon",
        "question": "у меня скоро день рождения",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "may i take?",
        "question": "можно взять?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I am sorry, I cannot",
        "question": "Простите, не могу.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "October",
        "question": "октябрь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "inform",
        "question": "сообщать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to tell someone about something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "If he calls me again, I shall inform the police.",
            "He informed us that we would have to leave."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "anger",
        "question": "гнев",
        "explanation": "[noun] a strong feeling against someone who has behaved badly, making you want to shout at them or hurt them",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "public anger at the terrorist killings"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "assume",
        "question": "предполагать (= предусматривать)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to think that something is likely to be true, although you have no proof",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Everything was quiet when I got home so I assumed that you had gone out.",
            "I didn’t see your car, so I assumed you’d gone out."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "how is your family?",
        "question": "как поживает ваша семья?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "let me think",
        "question": "дайте мне подумать",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i understand a little english",
        "question": "я немного понимаю по-английски",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "And so on and so forth",
        "question": "и так далее",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "motion",
        "question": "движение (not standing still)",
        "explanation": "[noun] the process of moving or the way that someone or something moves. Movement: moving from one place to another.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the motion of the planets",
            "The motion of the boat made him feel sick."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "it is all right",
        "question": "не стоит",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "zealot",
        "question": "фанатический приверженец, фанатик",
        "explanation": "[noun] [often disapproving] a person who has very strong feelings about something, such as religion or politics and who wants other people to have those feelings",
        "source": "Word smart.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sauce",
        "question": "соус",
        "explanation": "[noun] a hot or cold liquid that you put on food to add flavour",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "pasta with tomato sauce"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "intelligent beings",
        "question": "разумные существа",
        "explanation": "[intelligent] an intelligent person has a high level of mental ability and is good at understanding ideas and thinking clearly",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a group of highly intelligent (=very intelligent) students"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "trout",
        "question": "форель",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "weakness",
        "question": "слабость",
        "explanation": "[noun] the state of not being strong or powerful",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Asking for help is not a sign of weakness."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "pertain to",
        "question": "[formal] относиться, иметь отношение к чему-либо",
        "explanation": "[phrasal verb] to relate to something",
        "source": "software testing: a craftsman's approach",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Some important evidence pertaining to the case has been overlooked."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "my surname is sadykov",
        "question": "моя фамилия садыков",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "programmer",
        "question": "программист",
        "explanation": "a person who writes computer programs",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Do not mention it!",
        "question": "Не стоит благодарности!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "comfortable- uncomfortable",
        "question": "удобный- неудобный",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "disease",
        "question": "заболевание",
        "explanation": "[noun] an illness caused by an infection or by a failure of health and not by an accident",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "heart disease",
            "an infectious disease"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "I do not know the way.",
        "question": "Я не знаю дорогу.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "recently",
        "question": "недавно",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "commit a crime",
        "question": "совершить преступление",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i wish you a good rest",
        "question": "желаю вам хорошего отдыха",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "apart from",
        "question": "кроме",
        "explanation": "except for",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We didn’t see anyone all day, apart from a couple of kids on the beach.",
            "Apart from the ending, it’s a really good film."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "track",
        "question": "узкая дорога (тропа)",
        "explanation": "[noun] a narrow path or road with a rough uneven surface, especially one made by people or animals frequently moving through the same place",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The road leading to the farm was little more than a dirt track.",
            "We followed a dirt track off the main road."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "susceptibility",
        "question": "восприимчивость, подверженность",
        "explanation": "[noun] how easily someone or something is affected by something. A susceptibility is a type of weakness, but a particular kind. If your knee keeps getting injured, you may have a susceptibility to knee problems. If alcoholism runs in your family, you probably have a susceptibility to being an alcoholic yourself. Some people have a susceptibility to spending a lot of money or eating too much. When you have a susceptibility, there's something you can't resist or can't fight off.",
        "source": "Word smart.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "One of the side effects of the drug is an increased susceptibility to infections.",
            "And people vary, too, in their susceptibility to addiction."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "interpreter",
        "question": "переводчик",
        "explanation": "a person who interprets, especially one who translates speech orally or into sign language",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "decorate",
        "question": "украшать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to make something look more attractive by putting things on it or around it",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "They decorated the room with balloons for her party."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "What is the matter?",
        "question": "В чем дело?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "may i offer you a cigarette?",
        "question": "можно предложить вам сигарету?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "twilight",
        "question": "... is the small amount of light that there is outside just after the sun has gone down (сумерки, полумрак)",
        "explanation": "[noun] You must draw the picture (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dawn)",
        "source": "twilight |ˈtwʌɪlʌɪt|",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "capital punishment",
        "question": "смертная казнь",
        "explanation": "[adjective] =death as a punishment for a crime",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The are trying to abolish capital punishment except in cases of terrorism."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "later",
        "question": "позже (at a time in the future; after the time you are talking about)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She later became a doctor.",
            "We're going to Rome later in the year."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "take off",
        "question": "to remove a piece of clothing",
        "explanation": "He sat on the bed to take his boots off [take something off]",
        "source": "Environment around you",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "criminal",
        "question": "преступный, уголовный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] relating to crime",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Experts cannot agree on the causes of criminal behaviour."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "It is nice today.",
        "question": "[погода] сегодня хороший день.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "this idea sounds crazy.",
        "question": "эта идея кажется сумасшедшей.",
        "explanation": "[crazy]: very strange or not sensible (бредовый, сумасшедший)",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The neighbours must think we’re crazy."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "autumn is drawing on",
        "question": "осень приближается",
        "explanation": "[phrasal verb] As a period of time draws on, it passes and the end of it gets closer",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "artistic",
        "question": "художественный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] showing skill and imagination in creating things, especially in painting, drawing, etc.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "artistic talent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "amiable",
        "question": "дружелюбный, любезный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] friendly and easy to like",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The driver was an amiable young man.",
            "She was in an amiable mood."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "lurk",
        "question": "be or remain hidden so as to wait in ambush for someone or something",
        "explanation": "a ruthless killer still lurked in the darkness.",
        "source": "Woe Is I Jr.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "church",
        "question": "церковь",
        "explanation": "[noun] a building where Christians go to worship God",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We used to go to church every Sunday morning."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "ultimate",
        "question": "предельный, крайний",
        "explanation": "[adjective] better, bigger, worse etc than all other things or people of the same kind",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The Rolling Stones are the ultimate rock and roll band."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "date of purchase",
        "question": "датa приобретения (покупки)",
        "explanation": "When you purchase a pair of shoes, you buy them. If you want to gain purchase, or favor, with new friends, you might tell them about your recent purchase of chocolate, and offer to share. Purchase can refer to the act of buying or the thing you bought. In 1803, the United States paid France approximately $15,000,000 for 800,000 acres of land which was called Louisiana, in a transaction known as the Louisiana Purchase. In this transaction, the purchase nearly doubled the size of the U.S. –– the territory purchased comprises about 23 percent of current US land.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "science",
        "question": "наука",
        "explanation": "[noun] the study and knowledge of the structure and behaviour of natural things in an organized way",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "you could ask this question the other way around.",
        "question": "вы можете задать этот вопрос по-другому (наоборот)",
        "explanation": null,
        "source": "A History of the World in 100 objects: Early Victorian tea set",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "What date is it today?",
        "question": "Какое сегодня число?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "the day after tomorrow",
        "question": "послезавтра",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Which shoes should I wear with this dress- my blue ones or my black ones?",
        "question": "Какую обувь я должна носить с этим платьем- мои синие или мои черные?",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Raspberry",
        "question": "малина",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "craft",
        "question": "ремесло",
        "explanation": "[noun] a job or activity in which you make things with your hands, and that you usually need skill to do",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "traditional rural crafts"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "hurt",
        "question": "причинять боль, наносить повреждение",
        "explanation": "[verb] we use hurt for a whole range of pains. If you stub your toe, it hurts, and if someone is beating you up you might say, \"Stop hurting me!\" Someone injured in battle or in sports is described as hurt. If you say something you shouldn't on live radio, you'll hurt your chances of winning an election.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Simon hurt his knee playing football."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "what time is it?",
        "question": "который час?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Months",
        "question": "Месяцы",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "tomorrow",
        "question": "завтра",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "potato",
        "question": "картофель",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "policy",
        "question": "политика, установка",
        "explanation": "[noun] a set of ideas or a plan of what to do in particular situations that has been agreed by a government, business, etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "foreign policy",
            "It is company policy to help staff progress in their careers."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "gate",
        "question": "ворота, калитка",
        "explanation": "[noun] the part of a fence or outside wall that opens and closes like a door",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Please shut the gate."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Put the kettle on the fire.",
        "question": "Поставь чайник на огонь.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Will you stop interrupting me!",
        "question": "Вы перестанете меня прерывать (перебивать)!",
        "explanation": "[interrupt] to stop someone from continuing what they are saying or doing by suddenly speaking to them, making a noise etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Sorry to interrupt, but I need to ask you to come downstairs."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Can I pay by credit card?",
        "question": "Могу я заплатить кредитной карточкой?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "if someone comes over, they visit you at your house",
        "question": "EXPLAIN: come over CONTEXT: Do you want to come over on Friday evening.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "attraction",
        "question": "привлекательность, достопримечательность",
        "explanation": "[noun] something that makes people come to a place or want to do a particular thing",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a tourist attraction",
            "The opportunity to travel is one of the main attractions of this job."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "doctor",
        "question": "врач",
        "explanation": "a person who is qualified to treat people who are ill",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "how are things?",
        "question": "как дела? (informal)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "cream",
        "question": "сливки",
        "explanation": "[noun] a thick, yellowish-white liquid that is taken from milk",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "strawberries and cream"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "a particular type of welcome, or a particular type of reaction to their ideas, work, etc.",
        "question": "EXPLAIN: reception. CONTEXT: His idea got a cool reception from his colleagues.",
        "explanation": "[noun, uncountable] without an article",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "hazelnut",
        "question": "лесной орех, лещина",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "to wait in line",
        "question": "ждать в очереди",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "She got off the train in Geneva.",
        "question": "Она сошла с поезда в Женеве. (in Geneva)",
        "explanation": "If you can walk onto it and stand up inside, you say “get on”. If not, you say “get in”. This rule is especially illustrated by vehicles where we could use either “in/out” or “on/off”, depending on the size of the vehicle. We normally say “get on an airplane” but if you have a small, single-engine airplane, you would normally say “get in”. The same goes for boats, where we get on a large ship, but get in a canoe. This is also true for helicopters, submarines and spaceships.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Tuesday",
        "question": "вторник",
        "explanation": "[noun] the day between Monday and Wednesday",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He first heard the news on Tuesday evening."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "grapes",
        "question": "виноград",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "average",
        "question": "средний, обычный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] usual and like the most common type",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an average person",
            "an average day"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "I wonder who it was",
        "question": "интере́сно знать, кто э́то мог быть",
        "explanation": "[verb] to think about something and try to decide what is true, what will happen, what you should do, etc.",
        "source": "The Oxford 3000",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I wonder why he left his job.",
            "We were wondering about next April for the wedding."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "The tap water is not safe to drink.",
        "question": "Водопроводная вода не безопасна для питья. (The ...)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Clean the surface thoroughly with a brush.",
        "question": "Тщательно очмстите поверхность щеткой.",
        "explanation": "\"by\" is used to say what means or method someone uses to do something. \"with\" is used to say what tool is used to do something.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "What is the weather forecast for tomorrow?",
        "question": "Какой прогноз погоды на завтра?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "What towns do we go through on the way?",
        "question": "Какие города мы проезжаем в пути? (town)",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from. Certainly use which, not what, when there are only two choices, or if both speaker and listener can visualise all the items under consideration. Generally speaking, you can replace the usage of \"which” with \"what\" and be OK grammatically. It doesn’t always work the other way around, however. There needs to be a context of choice.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "my wife is a housewife",
        "question": "моя жена домохозяйка",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "suffice",
        "question": "[formal] быть достаточным",
        "explanation": "[verb] formal to be enough",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "A light lunch will suffice.",
            "A few brief observations will suffice for present purposes."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "toy",
        "question": "игрушка",
        "explanation": "[noun] an object for children to play with",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He was happily playing with his toys.",
            "a toy car/train"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i do not understand you",
        "question": "я вас не понимаю",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i hope, we shall meet again soon",
        "question": "надеюсь, мы скоро снова встретимся",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "pole",
        "question": "столб, шест, кол",
        "explanation": "[noun] a long, thin stick made of wood or metal, often used to hold something up",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "tent poles"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "in short",
        "question": "вкратце",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "We stood in line for 20 minutes.",
        "question": "Мы стояли в очереди 20 минут.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "tradition",
        "question": "традиция",
        "explanation": "[noun] a custom or way of behaving that has continued for a long time in a group of people or a society",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "There is a strong tradition of dance in St Petersburg.",
            "the traditions of South East Asia"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "annual",
        "question": "ежегодный; годичный, годовой",
        "explanation": "[adjective] happening once a year; based on or calculated over a period of one year",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The school trip has become an annual event.",
            "annual income"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "an hour ago",
        "question": "час тому назад",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "giving only the information that is necessary and important, using few words",
        "question": "concise",
        "explanation": "[adjective] Giving a lot of information clearly and in a few words; brief but comprehensive. So, something concise is not just short in length, but it also \"gives a lot of information.\" Things which are merely \"succinct\" do not have that feature.",
        "source": "Spaced rehearsal program readme.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "clear concise instructions",
            "a concise summary"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Are we still on for tomorrow?",
        "question": "Все остается в силе на завтра? (Договоренность на завтра в силе?)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "escape punishment",
        "question": "избежать наказания",
        "explanation": "[verb]",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The thieves managed to escape punishment."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "It takes about 30 minutes on foot, or 10 minutes by car.",
        "question": "Это занимает около 30 минут пешком или 10 минут на машине.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "producer",
        "question": "продюсер",
        "explanation": "a person responsible for the financial and managerial aspects of the making of a film or broadcast or for staging a play, opera, etc",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "space",
        "question": "место, пространство (an empty area that is available to be used)",
        "explanation": "[noun] the amount of an area, room, container etc that is empty or available to be used",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "There’s space for a table and two chairs.",
            "We need more open spaces for children to play in."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "September",
        "question": "сентябрь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "specialist",
        "question": "специалист",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone who has a lot of experience, knowledge, or skill in a particular subject",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He's a specialist in childhood illnesses."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "next year",
        "question": "в следующем году",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "What do you want for dessert?",
        "question": "Что вы хотите на десерт? (use do)",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from. Certainly use which, not what, when there are only two choices, or if both speaker and listener can visualise all the items under consideration. Generally speaking, you can replace the usage of \"which” with \"what\" and be OK grammatically. It doesn’t always work the other way around, however. There needs to be a context of choice. \"Which\" only works in the context of being presented with choices (e.g. a dessert cart right in front of you)",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "to sing a song",
        "question": "петь песню",
        "explanation": "[song] (песня) words that go with a short piece of music",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "hilarious",
        "question": "уморительный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] extremely funny",
        "source": "Full text search feature test",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "They all thought the film was hilarious."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Can you spare the time?",
        "question": "Ты можешь уделить время?",
        "explanation": "[spare] to make something such as time, money, or workers available for someone, especially when this is difficult for you to do",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Sorry, I can’t spare the time",
            "Can you spare £5?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sometimes",
        "question": "иногда",
        "explanation": "[adverb] on some occasions but not always or often",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He does cook sometimes, but not very often."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "peach",
        "question": "персик",
        "explanation": "[noun] a soft, sweet, round fruit with red and yellow skin",
        "source": "From Frequency to Meaning: Vector Space Models of Semantics.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "awake",
        "question": "бодрствовать, не спать",
        "explanation": "[adjective] to not be sleeping",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Is Tom awake yet?",
            "The noise from the party kept me awake all night."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "everything goes well",
        "question": "все идёт хорошо",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "somewhat",
        "question": "слегка",
        "explanation": "[adverb] slightly",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We were somewhat disappointed with the food."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "nevertheless",
        "question": "тем не менее",
        "explanation": "[adverb] in spite of a fact that you have just mentioned",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "What you said was true. It was, nevertheless, a little unkind.",
            "I knew a lot about the subject already, but her talk was interesting nevertheless."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "That explains it.",
        "question": "Это все объясняет.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "umbrella",
        "question": "зонт",
        "explanation": "[noun] an object that you use to protect yourself against rain or hot sun. It consists of a circular folding frame covered in cloth",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "When it rains, people put up umbrellas."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "black caviar",
        "question": "чёрная икра",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "blackcurrant",
        "question": "черная смородина",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "special treatment",
        "question": "особое обращение",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "infect",
        "question": "заражать (человека, животное)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to give someone a disease",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "People with the virus may feel perfectly well, but they can still infect others.",
            "Thousands of people were infected with the virus."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "expensive- cheap",
        "question": "дорогой- дешевый",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "they are pensioners",
        "question": "они пенсионеры",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "fast- slow",
        "question": "быстрый- медленный",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am in new york, at the conference",
        "question": "я в нью-йорке на конференции",
        "explanation": "People are usually using \"in\" to note a general location and \"at\" for a more specific location. \"In\" is generally used for a larger area where there are numerous specific locations possible: I am in the United States. I am in my backyard. \"At\" is generally used for a specific location or thing: I am at home. I am at the old oak tree in my yard.",
        "source": "English phrase book, afterthought",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "contaminated water",
        "question": "загрязненная вода",
        "explanation": "contaminated (=water that has harmful substances in it)",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "They became ill from drinking contaminated water."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sports ground",
        "question": "спортивная площадка",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "number",
        "question": "число",
        "explanation": "[noun] a word or sign that represents an exact amount or quantity",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "They wrote various numbers on a large sheet of paper.",
            "Add all the numbers together."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "can i borrow your pen? mine's broken",
        "question": "могу я одолжить твою ручку? моя сломалась",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "Really learn 100 phrasal verbs.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "favourite toy",
        "question": "любимая игрушка",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a child’s favourite toy"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "brown bread",
        "question": "черный хлеб",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "The firm originally quoted 6000 for the whole job.",
        "question": "Фирма изначально запросила 6000 фунтов стерлингов за всю работу.",
        "explanation": "quoted- to tell a customer the price you will charge them for a service or product.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "They quoted a price of 15000"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "overcome",
        "question": "преодолевать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to deal with and control a problem or feeling",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He's trying to overcome his drug addiction and find a job.",
            "Let's hope she overcomes her shyness."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "raisin",
        "question": "Изюм",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Which foot did you break?",
        "question": "Какую ступню вы сломали?",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from. Certainly use which, not what, when there are only two choices, or if both speaker and listener can visualise all the items under consideration.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "speech",
        "question": "(устная) речь",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone's ability to talk, or an example of someone talking",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "His speech was very slow and difficult to understand."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "builder",
        "question": "строитель",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I have to run to the store.",
        "question": "Мне нужно сходить в магазин.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "solstice",
        "question": "солнцестояние",
        "explanation": "either of the two times in the year, the summer solstice and the winter solstice, when the sun reaches its highest or lowest point in the sky at noon, marked by the longest and shortest days.",
        "source": "Living with the Gods: Here Comes the Sun.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "family",
        "question": "семья",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "chin",
        "question": "подбородок",
        "explanation": "[noun] the bottom part of your face, below your mouth",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He rubbed his chin thoughtfully."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "touch",
        "question": "трогать, притрагиваться, (при)касаться",
        "explanation": "[verb] to put your hand on something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "You can look at them but please don't touch them."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "may i invite you to a theatre?",
        "question": "разрешите пригласить вас в театр? (a theatre)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "rural craft",
        "question": "сельское ремесло",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The museum contains exhibits of old rural crafts."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "I got back home the day before yesterday.",
        "question": "Я вернулся домой позавчера.",
        "explanation": "two days ago",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "slice of bread",
        "question": "кусок хлеба (тонкий, плоский кусок)",
        "explanation": "[slice] a thin flat piece of bread, cake, meat etc cut from a larger piece",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a slice of pizza",
            "Cut the tomatoes into thin slices."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "twenty-five minutes to nine, eight thirty-five",
        "question": "8.35- без двадцати пяти девять, тридцать пять девятого",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "layer",
        "question": "слой",
        "explanation": "[noun] an amount of a substance covering a surface, or one of several amounts of substance, each on top of the other",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The shelf was covered in a thick layer of dust."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "They are undoubtedly the better team.",
        "question": "Они, несомненно, лучшая команда.",
        "explanation": "\"undoubtedly\" used when saying that you are completely sure about something. \"Undoubtedly\" sounds more certain and a little more formal than \"certainly\"",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The furniture, although undoubtedly fashionable, was a little too plain for my taste."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "special",
        "question": "особенный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] better or more important than usual things",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a special friend",
            "I'm cooking something special for her birthday."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "informal",
        "question": "неофициальный, непринужденный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] relaxed and friendly",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an informal discussion/meeting"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "do not worry",
        "question": "не волнуйтесь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "last week",
        "question": "на прошлой недели",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "adherent",
        "question": "приверженец",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone who supports a particular belief, plan, political party etc",
        "source": "software testing: a craftsman's approach",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "adherents of the Greek Orthodox Church",
            "The anti-globalization movement is attracting new adherents to its principles."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "asleep",
        "question": "спящий",
        "explanation": "[adjective] sleeping",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Quiet! The baby’s asleep."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "It is all the same to me.",
        "question": "мне это безразлично; мне всё равно",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "profusion",
        "question": "изобилие",
        "explanation": "[noun] an abundance or large quantity of something",
        "source": "code complete by steve mcconnell",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a rich profusion of flowers",
            "Snow is falling in profusion."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "What do you mean?",
        "question": "Что вы имеете в виду?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "table",
        "question": "стол",
        "explanation": "a piece of furniture with a flat top supported by legs",
        "source": "Program enhancement",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The food was served on long tables.",
            "Will you clear the breakfast table?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "The booking will be made on receipt of a deposit.",
        "question": "Бронирование производится при получении депозита.",
        "explanation": "[formal, uncountable] when someone receives something",
        "source": "Sentence oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the closing date for receipt of applications",
            "Items must be returned within fourteen days of receipt."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "objective",
        "question": "задача, задание (одна из ближайших целей, обычно имеющая конкретную количественную формулировку, в отличие миссиии или стратегической цели компании; напр., задача корпорации — поддержание рентабельности на определенном уровне)",
        "explanation": "[noun] the specific thing that you are trying to achieve – used especially about things that have been officially discussed and agreed upon in business, politics etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "His main objective was to increase profits.",
            "the best way to accomplish your objectives"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "orange",
        "question": "оранжевый",
        "explanation": "[adjective] reddish yellow",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an orange glow in the sky"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "young",
        "question": "молодой, юный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] having lived or existed for only a short time and not old",
        "source": "The Oxford 3000",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We were very young when we met."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "This way?",
        "question": "В эту сторону?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "attractive",
        "question": "привлекательный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] beautiful or pleasant to look at",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an attractive woman",
            "I find him very attractive."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "the day before yesterday",
        "question": "позавчера",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "now",
        "question": "сейчас",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "afford",
        "question": "быть в состоянии (сделать что-л.); позволить себе (что-л.)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to have enough money to buy something or enough time to do something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I can't afford a new computer.",
            "Can we afford to go away?",
            "I'd love to come out but I can't afford the time."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "chambermaid",
        "question": "горничная",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "criminal offence",
        "question": "уголовное преступление",
        "explanation": "a crime",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He committed several serious offences."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "nothing new",
        "question": "ничего нового",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "DJ",
        "question": "диджей",
        "explanation": "a person who introduces and plays recorded popular music on radio",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "a succinct description of the Egyptian writing system",
        "question": "краткое описание египетской письменной системы",
        "explanation": "said in a clear and short way; expressing what needs to be said without unnecessary words.",
        "source": "Spaced rehearsal program readme.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "machine",
        "question": "механизм, машина",
        "explanation": "[noun] a piece of equipment with moving parts that uses power such as electricity to do a particular job",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Is the washing machine working now?",
            "Could you get me a coffee from the drinks machine?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "angle",
        "question": "(геометрия) угол",
        "explanation": "[noun] a space between two lines or surfaces that meet at one point, which you measure in degrees",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an angle of 90 degrees"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "let me introduce you to my girlfriend",
        "question": "разрешите представить вам мою подругу (официальная форма)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "tunnel",
        "question": "тоннель",
        "explanation": "[noun] a passage that has been dug under the ground for cars, trains etc to go through",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a railway tunnel"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sorrel",
        "question": "щавель",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "expressed clearly and in a few words",
        "question": "succinct",
        "explanation": "[adjective] краткий",
        "source": "Spaced rehearsal program readme.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Keep your letter succinct and to the point.",
            "Use short, succinct sentences."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "time of the day",
        "question": "время суток",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "pride",
        "question": "гордость",
        "explanation": "[noun] The noun pride describes a feeling of happiness that comes from achieving something. When you do a good job or finish a difficult task, you feel pride. Pride can also have a negative meaning and refer to exceedingly high self-regard. If you know someone with the negative kind of pride, you might notice that his pride makes it hard for people to like him. Pride can also refer to the standards you have for yourself — your dignity. For example, you might have too much pride to ask for help when you need it. Pride also acts as a verb meaning \"be proud of.\" You might pride yourself on being punctual, or pride yourself on always having a daring, trendsetting haircut.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He wore his medals with pride."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "do not mention it",
        "question": "не за что (в ответ на благодарность)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I was tired, so I decided to stay in.",
        "question": "Я был уставший и поэтому решил остаться дома.",
        "explanation": "to spend the evening at home rather than go out",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "apricot",
        "question": "абрикос",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "week",
        "question": "неделя",
        "explanation": "[noun] a period of seven days",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I've got three exams this week.",
            "We get paid every week."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Tuesday",
        "question": "вторник",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "eight o'clock",
        "question": "8.00- восемь часов",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sole responsibility",
        "question": "единоличная ответственность (осуществляемый одним лицом)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She has the sole responsibility for a large family."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Something that is horrendous is extremely shocking",
        "question": "EXPLAIN: horrendous CONTEXT: The violence used was horrendous.",
        "explanation": "[adjective] (ужасный) [syn. horrific] frightening and terrible.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The police officer said the attack was the most horrendous he had ever seen."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "windowsill",
        "question": "подоконник",
        "explanation": "[noun] a shelf fixed along the bottom of a window",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Colours",
        "question": "Цвета",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a range of bright colours"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "art",
        "question": "искусство",
        "explanation": "[noun] the making or study of paintings, drawings, etc or the objects created",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "modern art",
            "an art exhibition"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "I did not catch the last word.",
        "question": "Я не понял последнее слово.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "oar",
        "question": "весло",
        "explanation": "a long pole with a wide, flat end that you use to move a boat through water",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "discover a cure",
        "question": "найти лекарство",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "There's always a chance they will discover a cure, isn't there?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "nest",
        "question": "гнездо",
        "explanation": "[noun] a place made or chosen by a bird to lay its eggs in and to live in",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a bird’s nest",
            "In May the females build a nest and lay their eggs."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "clinical trials",
        "question": "клинические испытания",
        "explanation": "trial: a process of testing to find out whether something works effectively and is safe",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The drug is currently undergoing clinical trials."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "diminish",
        "question": "to become or to make sth become smaller, weaker, less etc",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I really should go to the dentist, but I keep putting it off.",
        "question": "Я действительно должен пойти к дантисту, но я продолжаю это откладывать.",
        "explanation": "[phrasal verb] to decide to do something later than you planned to do it or later than you should do it, especially because there is a problem or because you do not want to do it now. Put off is less formal than delay or postpone, and is the usual phrase to use in everyday English",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I used to put off making difficult decisions.",
            "The game has been put off till next week."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "turn the heating off",
        "question": "выключите отопление",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "illegal",
        "question": "незаконный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] not allowed by law",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It is illegal to sell cigarettes to anyone under 16."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "gap",
        "question": "щель, промежуток",
        "explanation": "[noun] an empty space or hole in the middle of something, or between two things",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "There's quite a big gap between the door and the floor.",
            "The sun was shining through a gap in the curtains."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "bandage",
        "question": "бинт",
        "explanation": "[noun] a narrow piece of cloth that you tie around a wound or around a part of the body that has been injured",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "If blood keeps coming through the bandage, do not remove it",
            "simply put another bandage on top."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "cabbage",
        "question": "капуста",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "trade",
        "question": "эк. торговля, коммерческая деятельность",
        "explanation": "[noun] the buying and selling of large numbers of goods or services, especially between countries",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The laws ban the international trade in ivory (слоновая кость)",
            "They rely heavily on trade with Europe."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "requirement",
        "question": "требование, потребность",
        "explanation": "[noun] something that is needed or demanded",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "college entrance requirements",
            "The refugees’ main requirements are food and shelter.",
            "Potatoes can provide one-third of our daily requirement of vitamin C."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "cauliflower",
        "question": "цветная капуста",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "camomile tea",
        "question": "ромашковый чай.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "in the afternoon",
        "question": "днём",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "quarter",
        "question": "квартал",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "actress",
        "question": "актриса",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "pack",
        "question": "упаковывать вещи",
        "explanation": "[verb] to put your things into bags or boxes when you are going on holiday or leaving the place where you live",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I've got to go home and pack.",
            "to pack your bags"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "treat",
        "question": "обращаться, обходиться (с кем-либо)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to behave towards someone or something in a particular way",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She treats me like one of the family.",
            "The prisoners were well treated by their guards."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "in a word",
        "question": "в двух словах",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "All right, where were we?",
        "question": "Так, на чем мы остановились?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "infancy",
        "question": "младенчество",
        "explanation": "[noun] the period during which you are a baby or a very young child",
        "source": "The Oxford 3000",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "In the past, many more babies died in infancy."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "tooth decay",
        "question": "кариес",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Brushing regularly helps prevent tooth decay."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "with a sense of bitter regret",
        "question": "с чувством горького сожаления",
        "explanation": "bitter regret (=when you feel sad and angry)",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "To the bitter regret of his party, he refused to call an election."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "please, wait a bit",
        "question": "пожалуйста, подождите немного",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sensible advice",
        "question": "разумный совет",
        "explanation": "[sensible] (благоразумный) reasonable, practical, and showing good judgment",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She seems very sensible.",
            "It’s sensible to keep a note of your passport number."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "junior employees",
        "question": "младшиe сотрудники (в компании)",
        "explanation": "[junior] having a low rank in an organization or profession",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a junior doctor"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "western",
        "question": "западный; относящийся к западу",
        "explanation": "[adjective] in or from the west of a country or area",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Western Australia"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sad",
        "question": "грустный, печальный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] not happy, especially because something unpleasant has happened",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Dad looked sad and worried as he read the letter."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "parting",
        "question": "прощание",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "whatever",
        "question": "мест: \"всё, что\"",
        "explanation": "[pronoun] anything or everything",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Do whatever you want.",
            "He eats whatever I put in front of him."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am very glad to see you!",
        "question": "как я рад вас видеть!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "skeleton",
        "question": "[Скелет человека] скелет",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Thank you anyway!",
        "question": "В любом случае, спасибо!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "soul",
        "question": "душа",
        "explanation": "[noun] the part of a person that is not their body, which some people believe continues to exist after they die",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "avocado",
        "question": "авокадо",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "speaker",
        "question": "динамик",
        "explanation": "[noun] the part of a radio, CD player, etc which the sound comes out of",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "The breakfast that they served was fabulous.",
        "question": "Завтрак, который они подали, был потрясающим.",
        "explanation": "We use \"a\" when there is an adjective before breakfast, lunch, dinner etc. We use \"the\" when we are talking about a particular meal.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Did you have breakfast this morning?",
            "That was the most delicious dinner I've had in a while."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am on a business trip",
        "question": "я в командировке",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "national security",
        "question": "национальная безопасность",
        "explanation": "[security] (безопасность) things that are done to keep a person, building, or country safe from danger or crime",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We have been asked not to say anything for security reasons."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "plunge",
        "question": "нырять, погружать",
        "explanation": "jump or dive quickly and energetically: our little daughters whooped as they plunged into the sea.",
        "source": "Living with the Gods: Here Comes the Sun.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "scene",
        "question": "сцена, эпизод",
        "explanation": "[noun] a short part of a film, play, or book in which the events happen in one place",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a love scene"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "give my regards to your husband",
        "question": "передайте привет мужу",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "fancy meeting you here!",
        "question": "не ожидал вас здесь встретить!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Children have a strong sense of justice.",
        "question": "Дети обладают сильным чувством справедливости.",
        "explanation": "[justice] (справедливость) fairness in the way people are treated",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "tube of toothpaste",
        "question": "тюбик зубной пасты (without an article)",
        "explanation": "[tube] a narrow container made of plastic or soft metal and closed at one end, that you press between your fingers in order to push out the soft substance that is inside",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Tom studied medicine for 3 years.",
        "question": "Том изучал медицину в течение 3 лет. (Здесь подразумевается, что Том изучал когда-то медицину, но в данный момент этим не занимается, Past Simple)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "She hopes that Tom will have repaired his car by Monday evening.",
        "question": "Она надеется, что Том отремонтирует свою машину к вечеру понедельника. (Future Perfect)",
        "explanation": "Будущее совершенное (завершенное) время служит в английском языке для описания действий, которые завершатся в определенное время в будущем.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I can catch a bus from there.",
        "question": "Я там смогу сесть на автобус.",
        "explanation": "Catching a bus describes the process of getting to a stop/station, waiting and boarding. Taking a bus describes the entire process, including the journey itself. One other thing, you catch a bus at a specific place. But you take the bus from a place.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "You can catch the bus to Coventry on Smith Street.",
            "You can take the bus to Coventry from Smith Street."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "yawn",
        "question": "зевать",
        "explanation": "to take a deep breath with your mouth wide open, because you are tired or bored",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She yawned and looked at her watch."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "something",
        "question": "что-то, что-нибудь, кое-что",
        "explanation": "[pronoun] used to refer to a thing when you do not know what it is or when it is not important what it is",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "As soon as I walked in, I noticed that something was missing."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i study at a faculty of economics",
        "question": "я учусь на экономическом факультете",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "at midnight",
        "question": "в полночь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "We are seeing a musical at the theatre next week.",
        "question": "На следующей недели мы идем в театр на мюзикл. (the theatre)",
        "explanation": "We use the present continuous to describe an event in the future which has already been arranged by the time of speaking. (=We have got the tickets). Compare this with the use of be going to: We are going to see a musical at the theatre sometime next week. (not arranged yet; the focus is on our intention).",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "It was very pleasant here.",
        "question": "Здесь было очень приятно.",
        "explanation": "\"pleasant\"- enjoyable or attractive and making you feel happy (syn. nice). In everyday English, people usually say something or someone is nice rather than pleasant.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It was a really nice day."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "in two days",
        "question": "через два дня",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ahead",
        "question": "впереди",
        "explanation": "in front",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The road ahead is very busy."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "long ago",
        "question": "давно",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am not yet married",
        "question": "я еще не замужем",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "gain",
        "question": "получать, приобретать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to get something useful or positive",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "After gaining independence in 1957, it was renamed ‘Ghana’.",
            "You will gain a lot of experience working there."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "among",
        "question": "в, среди",
        "explanation": "[preposition] in the middle of something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He disappeared among the crowd.",
            "I could hear voices coming from somewhere among the bushes."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "vinegar",
        "question": "уксус",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "June",
        "question": "июнь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "almost",
        "question": "почти",
        "explanation": "[adverb] If something almost happens, it does not happen but it is very close to happening.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I almost missed the bus."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "awful",
        "question": "ужасный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] very bad, of low quality, or unpleasant",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an awful place",
            "The film was absolutely awful."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "a perfectly valid reason",
        "question": "абсолютно обоснованная причина (with an article)",
        "explanation": "[valid reason/argument/criticism etc] a reason, argument etc that is based on what is reasonable or sensible",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Police officers must have a valid reason for stopping motorists."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "legal implications",
        "question": "юридические последствия",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "live up to its reputation",
        "question": "оправдывать (соответствовать) своей репутации",
        "explanation": "[verb] be as good as people say it is",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "New York certainly lived up to its reputation as an exciting city."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "cranberry",
        "question": "клюква",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "may i invite you to a restaurant?",
        "question": "разрешите пригласить вас в ресторан?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "information office",
        "question": "справочное бюро",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ceiling",
        "question": "потолок",
        "explanation": "[noun] the inner surface of the top part of a room",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "rooms with high ceilings"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "nerve",
        "question": "нерв",
        "explanation": "[noun] one of the threads in your body that carry messages between your brain and other parts of the body",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "nerve cells"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "attend",
        "question": "присутствовать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to go to an event",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "to attend a concert/meeting"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Do you mind if I open the window",
        "question": "Вы возражаете если я открою окно.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "What is your phone number?",
        "question": "Какой у тебя номер телефона?",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from. Certainly use which, not what, when there are only two choices, or if both speaker and listener can visualise all the items under consideration. Generally speaking, you can replace the usage of \"which” with \"what\" and be OK grammatically. It doesn’t always work the other way around, however. There needs to be a context of choice.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "connivance",
        "question": "попустительство, молчаливое согласие",
        "explanation": "willingness to allow or be secretly involved in an immoral or illegal act",
        "source": "Germany: Memories of a Nation - The view from the gate.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "internal",
        "question": "внутренний (касательно страны, организации или группы)",
        "explanation": "[adjective] happening or coming from inside a particular country, group, or organization",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an internal report",
            "internal injuries"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "iron",
        "question": "железо",
        "explanation": "[noun] a dark grey metal used to make steel (= very strong metal) and found in small amounts in blood and food (formula Fe)",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an iron bar/gate"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i strongly object",
        "question": "я категорически возражаю",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "tune",
        "question": "мелодия",
        "explanation": "[noun] a series of musical notes that are played or sung and are nice to listen to",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She sang some old classics and a few new tunes."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "in recent years",
        "question": "в последние годы",
        "explanation": "In everyday English, people usually say in the last/past few weeks/months/years etc rather than in recent weeks/months etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The situation has improved in recent years.",
            "Things have been pretty busy in the last few weeks."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "repeat, please",
        "question": "повторите, пожалуйста",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ability",
        "question": "способность, умение (что-л. делать)",
        "explanation": "[noun] the physical or mental skill or qualities that you need to do something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He had the ability to explain things clearly.",
            "athletic/academic ability"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i apologize",
        "question": "я извиняюсь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "walnut",
        "question": "грецкий орех",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "hunt",
        "question": "охотиться",
        "explanation": "[verb] to chase animals and birds in order to kill or catch them",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "to hunt rabbits"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "screw",
        "question": "винт, шуруп",
        "explanation": "a small, pointed piece of metal that you turn round and round to fix things together, especially pieces of wood",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Fix the frame in position and tighten the screws."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Weather",
        "question": "Погода",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my husband",
        "question": "это мой муж",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Which of the restaurants is open on Sunday?",
        "question": "Какой из ресторанов открыт в воскресенье?",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from. Certainly use which, not what, when there are only two choices, or if both speaker and listener can visualise all the items under consideration.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "serviceable- broken",
        "question": "исправный- сломанный",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "herbal tea",
        "question": "травяной чай",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "fall short",
        "question": "to fail to reach an amount or standard that was expected or hoped for, causing disappointment",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "Operating Systems: Three Easy Pieces",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ask",
        "question": "спрашивать, задавать вопрос",
        "explanation": "[verb] to say something to someone as a question that you want them to answer",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Can I ask you a few questions?",
            "I asked him about his hobbies.",
            "I asked why the plane was so late."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "after two o'clock",
        "question": "после двух часов",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i wish you a happy journey",
        "question": "желаю вам счастливого пути",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "request",
        "question": "просьба, запрос",
        "explanation": "[noun] a question which politely or officially asks for something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "An application form is available on request (= if you ask for it).",
            "Anderson repeated his request that we postpone the meeting."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "You can either walk, drive or take the bus.",
        "question": "How can I get to the concert hall? Вы можете либо пешком, либо на машине, либо сесть на автобус. (the bus)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "declare",
        "question": "объявлять, заявлять",
        "explanation": "[verb] to announce something publicly or officially",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "to declare war",
            "Scientists have declared that this meat is safe to eat."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Today is the twelfth of August",
        "question": "Сегодня двенадцатое августа",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "rush",
        "question": "мчаться, нестись",
        "explanation": "to move very quickly, especially because you need to be somewhere very soon",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "A small girl rushed past her.",
            "Mo rushed off down the corridor."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my cousin",
        "question": "это мой двоюродный брат",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "seat",
        "question": "сиденье, место",
        "explanation": "[noun] a place where you can sit, especially one in a vehicle or one from which you watch a performance, sports event etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Never leave bags on the back seat of a car."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "blanket",
        "question": "одеяло",
        "explanation": "[noun] a cover for a bed, usually made of wool",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "actor",
        "question": "актёр",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "another",
        "question": "ещё один, другой",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Would you like another piece of cake?",
            "I'm going to look for another job."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "space",
        "question": "космос",
        "explanation": "[noun] the area outside the Earth",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the history of space travel",
            "Who was the first American in space?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "We do not use articles before the names of meals.",
        "question": "Мы не используем артикли перед названиями блюд.",
        "explanation": "We use \"a\" when there is an adjective before breakfast, lunch, dinner etc. We use \"the\" when we are talking about a particular meal.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Mother is cooking lunch.",
            "Dinner is ready.",
            "I had a late dinner yesterday.",
            "The lunch we had at the restaurant was very good."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "cod",
        "question": "треска",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "by all means",
        "question": "непременно",
        "explanation": "of course; certainly (granting a permission)",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "itself",
        "question": "себя, себе, сам, сама",
        "explanation": "[pronoun]",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The cat lay on the sofa, washing itself.",
            "The garden is enormous but the house itself is very small."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am tired",
        "question": "я устал",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "fervent",
        "question": "пылкий",
        "explanation": "[adjective] believing or feeling something very strongly or sincerely",
        "source": "Word smart.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a fervent supporter of the revolution."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "ultimate goal",
        "question": "Конечная цель",
        "explanation": "[ultimate] someone’s ultimate goal is their main and most important goal, that they hope to achieve in the future",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The ultimate goal is to achieve gender equality."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "I can lend you a spare key to the store until you get one cut.",
        "question": "Я могу одолжить вам запасной ключ от магазина, пока вы не сделайте дупликат.",
        "explanation": "Say \"the key to\" something. Don't say \"the key of\" something",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "keys to the house"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Digital technology resulted in a myriad of new TV channels.",
        "question": "Цифровая технология привела к множеству новых телевизионных каналов.",
        "explanation": "[adjective] a myriad of (= many) несметное количество",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (Melanie Mitchell)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "balance",
        "question": "равновесие",
        "explanation": "[noun] the state of having your weight spread in such a way that you do not fall over",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I lost my balance and fell off the bike."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "muddle",
        "question": "путаница, неразбериха",
        "explanation": "an untidy and disorganized state or collection",
        "source": "Fundamental Concepts in Programming Languages - paper",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "wedding anniversary",
        "question": "годовщина свадьбы",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ultimate decision",
        "question": "Окончательное решение",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The ultimate decision rests with the Public Health Service."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "bring me, please",
        "question": "принесите мне, пожалуйста",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "do",
        "question": "Restore the invisible part: Garfield likes chocolate-chip cookie dough more than I.",
        "explanation": "than I or than me - could be correct, depending on what you mean. It all becomes clear when you mentally restore the invisible parts.",
        "source": "Woe is I Jr.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I would like to order.",
        "question": "Я хотел бы сделать заказ.",
        "explanation": "We use “would like” or “‘d like to” to say politely what we want, especially when making offers or requests. Verbs that follow would like are in the to-infinitive form.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "clergyman",
        "question": "священник (a male member of the clergy)",
        "explanation": "a male priest, minister, or religious leader, especially a Christian one",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "imagine",
        "question": "полагать (= считать)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to believe that something is probably true",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I imagine he must be under a lot of pressure at the moment."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "memory",
        "question": "память",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone’s ability to remember things, places, experiences etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She has a terrible memory for names.",
            "The pianist played the whole piece from memory.",
            "The image has remained in my memory ever since."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "In the latter case, buyers pay a 15% commission.",
        "question": "В последнем случае, покупатели платят 15% комиссии.",
        "explanation": "being the second of two people or things, or the last in a list just mentioned (opp. former)",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "wave",
        "question": "махать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to raise your hand and move it from side to side in order to attract someone's attention or to say goodbye",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Wave goodbye to Grandma."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "legal secretary",
        "question": "юридический секретарь",
        "explanation": "[secretary] (секретарь) someone who works in an office typing letters, keeping records, answering telephone calls, arranging meetings etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "My secretary will fax you all the details.",
            "I am a single 33-year-old woman employed as a legal secretary."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "drainer",
        "question": "сушилка для посуды",
        "explanation": "draining board |ˈdreɪnɪŋ bɔːd| ",
        "source": "Environment around you",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "the year before last",
        "question": "в позапрошлом году",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "lie down",
        "question": "ложись",
        "explanation": "to put yourself in a position in which your body is flat on the floor or on a bed",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Just lie down on the bed."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "leaf",
        "question": "лист (растения)",
        "explanation": "[noun] a flat, green part of a plant that grows from a stem or branch",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the falling leaves"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "learn",
        "question": "учить(ся)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to get knowledge or skill in a new subject or activity",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I learned Russian at school."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am divorced",
        "question": "я в разводе",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "the best way",
        "question": "лучший способ",
        "explanation": "way- how you do something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Doing the job is often regarded as the best way of learning the job."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "The original study, which took place many years later, challenged his conclusions.",
        "question": "Первоначальное исследование, которое прошло много лет спустя, оспаривало его выводы.",
        "explanation": "Relative pronouns refer back to people (who, that, who, or whose), things or concepts (which, that, or whose), place (where), time( when), or explanation (what or why). When used as the subject of a sentence, the subject of a clause, or a subject complement, use \"who\" for people and \"which\" for everything else. That can be used in place of either who or which, but only with restrictive clauses.",
        "source": "Environment around you.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "where do you study?",
        "question": "где вы учитесь?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "stale bread",
        "question": "черствый хлеб",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "per capita",
        "question": "на душу населения",
        "explanation": "[adjective] for each person",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "This county has the lowest per capita income in the country.",
            "Belgians eat more chocolate per capita than any other nation in Europe."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "wealth",
        "question": "богатство",
        "explanation": "[noun] a large amount of money or valuable possessions that someone has'",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He enjoyed his new wealth and status."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "fine",
        "question": "штраф, пеня",
        "explanation": "[verb] to make someone pay money as a punishment",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She was fined for speeding.",
            "I got an £80 fine for speeding."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "trial period",
        "question": "испытательный срок",
        "explanation": "trial: a short period during which you use or do something or employ someone to find out whether they are satisfactory for a particular purpose or job",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The security system will be reviewed after a three-month trial period."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "salad",
        "question": "салат",
        "explanation": "[noun] a mixture of raw vegetables, especially lettuce, cucumber, and tomato",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Would you like some salad with your pasta?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "We arrived at the art gallery just as it was closing.",
        "question": "Мы приехали в художественную галерею перед ее закрытием. (the gallery)",
        "explanation": "The preposition \"to\" can never follow the verb \"arrive\", because it is a preposition of movement and the verb is not. Instead of \"to\", we can use \"at\" or \"in\". We use \"at\" when we get to a small place such an airport, station or village. We use \"in\" when we get to a large place such as a country or a city.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We arrived at the art gallery just as it was closing. (The gallery is seen as a point)",
            "Immigrants who arrived in the country after 2005 have to take a special language test. (The country is seen as a larger area)."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "After you!",
        "question": "После вас!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "bake",
        "question": "печь (например хлеб)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to cook something using dry heat, in an oven",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I’m baking some bread.",
            "baked potatoes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "arrival",
        "question": "прибытие",
        "explanation": "[noun] an occasion when someone or something arrives somewhere",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He first met Panos soon after his arrival in Greece.",
            "There was a car waiting for him on arrival."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "scrap of paper",
        "question": "клочок бумаги",
        "explanation": "[scrap] a small piece of paper, cloth etc that is no longer needed",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I wrote the phone number on a scrap of paper."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "She got off the bus at her usual stop.",
        "question": "Она вышла из автобуса на своей обычной остановке.",
        "explanation": "If you can walk onto it and stand up inside, you say “get on”. If not, you say “get in”. This rule is especially illustrated by vehicles where we could use either “in/out” or “on/off”, depending on the size of the vehicle. We normally say “get on an airplane” but if you have a small, single-engine airplane, you would normally say “get in”. The same goes for boats, where we get on a large ship, but get in a canoe. This is also true for helicopters, submarines and spaceships.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sweet- bitter",
        "question": "сладкий- горький",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sky",
        "question": "небо",
        "explanation": "[noun] the space above the Earth where clouds and the Sun and stars appear",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The sky grew dark, and a cold rain began to fall."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "age",
        "question": "возраст",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "minute",
        "question": "минута",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "perpetuate",
        "question": "увекове́чивать",
        "explanation": "If someone or something perpetuates a situation, system, or belief, especially a bad one, they cause it to continue. make (something) continue indefinitely. [a monument to perpetuate the memory of those killed in the war.]",
        "source": "Living With The Gods (bbc radio 4)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am on a leave",
        "question": "у меня отпуск",
        "explanation": " time when one has permission to be absent from work or from duty in the armed forces: Joe was home on leave",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "abash",
        "question": "конфузить (смущать)",
        "explanation": "[verb] a verb that means you have caused another person to feel awkward, bashful, embarrassed, or ashamed. Typically abash is used when something has a shaming effect.",
        "source": "Word Smart",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Harriet looked slightly abashed.",
            "I was abashed by the magnitude of the others’ generosity so I donated twenty thousand more."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "accept my condolences",
        "question": "примите мои соболезнования",
        "explanation": "accept /əkˈsept/, except  /ɪkˈsept/",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "safety",
        "question": "безопасность",
        "explanation": "[noun] when someone or something is safe from danger or harm",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "measures to improve the health and safety of employees"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Monday",
        "question": "понедельник",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "book-keeper",
        "question": "бухгалтер",
        "explanation": "a person whose job is to keep records of the financial affairs of a business",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "nervous",
        "question": "нервный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] worried or frightened about something, and unable to relax",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She was so nervous about her exams that she couldn’t sleep.",
            "a nervous cough"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "abroad",
        "question": "за границей, за границу",
        "explanation": "[adverb] in or to a foreign country",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He goes abroad a lot with his job."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "towel",
        "question": "полотенце",
        "explanation": "[noun] a soft piece of cloth or paper that you use for drying yourself or for drying something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a bath/beach towel",
            "a paper towel"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "distributor",
        "question": "дистрибьютер",
        "explanation": "an agent who supplies goods to retailers",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "adolescent",
        "question": "подростковый, юношеский",
        "explanation": "[adjective] especially written at the age when you change from being a child into an adult – used especially when talking about the problems that young people have at this age",
        "source": "The Oxford 3000",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Sudden mood changes are common in adolescent girls.",
            "adolescent behaviour"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "emergent",
        "question": "in the early stages of existence or development",
        "explanation": "[adjective]",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the emergent nations of the world"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "can you speak spanish?",
        "question": "вы говорите по-испански?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "a park bench",
        "question": "скамейка в парке (with an article)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "What colour are your shoes?",
        "question": "Какой цвет вашей обуви?",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from. In answer to your question about shoes, you would most likely ask what colour, not which colour, if you haven’t seen the shoes yet and you want the owner of the shoes to tell you the colour. This is because there are so many possibilities that the colour of the shoes could be.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "for life",
        "question": "на всю жизнь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The accident scarred him for life."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "November",
        "question": "ноябрь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "excerpt",
        "question": "отрывок, выдержка",
        "explanation": "[noun, countable] a short piece taken from a book, poem, piece of music etc",
        "source": "Complexity: A guided tour (Melanie Mitchell)",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Here is a short excerpt from the poem."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "as soon as",
        "question": "как только",
        "explanation": "at the same time or a very short time after",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "As soon as I saw her, I knew there was something wrong.",
            "They want it as soon as possible."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "create",
        "question": "создавать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to make something happen or exist",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The project will create more than 500 jobs."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "advise",
        "question": "советовать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to make a suggestion about what you think someone should do or how they should do something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "His doctor advised him to take time off work.",
            "They advise the government on environmental matters.",
            "The government is advising against travelling in the area.",
            "They're advising that children be kept out of the sun altogether."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "traveller",
        "question": "путешественник",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone who is on a journey or someone who travels often",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "frequent travellers to France",
            "We're doing a survey of business travellers."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "develop a cure",
        "question": "создать лекарство.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It will be at least ten years before a cure is developed."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "international cuisine",
        "question": "международная кухня (еда)",
        "explanation": "[international] relating to or involving more than one nation",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the response of the international community",
            "the UN and other international organizations"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Today it is hot outdoors.",
        "question": "Сегодня на улице жарко",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ignore",
        "question": "игнорировать, не замечать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to pay no attention to something or someone",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "You can’t ignore the fact that many criminals never go to prison."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "trap",
        "question": "ловушка, капкан",
        "explanation": "[noun] a piece of equipment for catching animals; a clever trick that is used to catch someone or to make them do or say something that they did not intend to",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The only way to catch mice is to set a trap.",
            "Police had set a trap for hooligans at the match."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am not against it",
        "question": "я не против этого",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "decision",
        "question": "решение",
        "explanation": "[noun] a choice that you make about something after thinking about several possibilities",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She has had to make some very difficult decisions.",
            "The committee should come to/reach a final decision by next week."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "pedestrian precinct",
        "question": "пещеходная зона",
        "explanation": "a shopping area in the centre of a town where cars, trucks etc. cannot go",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "wheel",
        "question": "колесо",
        "explanation": "[noun] a circular object fixed under a vehicle so that it moves smoothly over the ground",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "My bike needs a new front wheel."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "immoral",
        "question": "безнравственный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] morally wrong",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "immoral behaviour"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "pinch",
        "question": "ущипнуть, щипать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to press a part of someone’s skin very tightly between your finger and thumb, especially so that it hurts",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He pinched her cheek.",
            "Stop pinching me!"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "away",
        "question": "от, прочь",
        "explanation": "[adverb] to or in a different place or situation",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Go away and leave me alone.",
            "We would like to move away from the town centre."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my wife",
        "question": "это моя жена",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "offence",
        "question": "обида",
        "explanation": "[noun] the feeling of being upset or angry by something rude someone says",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Many people take offence at swearing."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "How is life?",
        "question": "Как жизнь?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "league",
        "question": "лига",
        "explanation": "[noun] a group of teams that compete against each other in a sport",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Who won the league championship this year?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "beget",
        "question": "порождать (быть источником, служить причиной чего-либо)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to cause something or make it happen",
        "source": "word smart",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Hunger begets crime.",
            "In the long term, violence begets violence."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Let's take a walk",
        "question": "Давайте прогуляемся",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am glad to meet you",
        "question": "рад с вами познакомиться",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "scientific",
        "question": "научный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] relating to science, or using the organized methods of science",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "scientific experiments/research"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "I jumped over the log.",
        "question": "Я перепрыгнул через бревно.",
        "explanation": "[jump] to push yourself up into the air, or over or away from something etc, using your legs",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "choose",
        "question": "выбирать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to decide which thing you want",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I helped my sister choose a name for her baby.",
            "There were lots of books to choose from."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "an eminently readable textbook",
        "question": "чрезвычайно читабельный учебник (an)",
        "explanation": "[adverb] You use eminently in front of an adjective describing a positive quality in order to emphasize the quality expressed by that adjective. (Extremely, very)",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "mountain",
        "question": "гора",
        "explanation": "[noun] a very high hill",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the highest mountain in Austria",
            "to climb a mountain"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Saturday",
        "question": "суббота",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ill",
        "question": "больной",
        "explanation": "[adjective] not feeling well, or suffering from a disease",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Mark had been feeling ill for a couple of days."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "crazy idea",
        "question": "безумная идея",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "nail",
        "question": "гвоздь",
        "explanation": "[noun] a thin piece of metal with a sharp end, used to join pieces of wood together",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a hammer and nails"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "nothing interesting",
        "question": "ничего интересного",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Do you have any special requests?",
        "question": "У вас есть особые пожелания?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "pollute the environment",
        "question": "загрязнять окружающую среду",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "seed",
        "question": "семечко",
        "explanation": "[noun] a small hard object produced by plants, from which a new plant of the same kind grows",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a packet of sunflower seeds"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Which of the grocery stores is open now?",
        "question": "Какой из продуктовых магазинов открыт сейчас?",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from. Certainly use which, not what, when there are only two choices, or if both speaker and listener can visualise all the items under consideration.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "primary",
        "question": "что-л, имеющее первостепенное значение",
        "explanation": "[adjective] most important",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Personal safety is of primary importance",
            "Our primary concern is to provide the refugees with food and health care."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "lie",
        "question": "лежать (to be in a position in which your body is flat on the floor, on a bed etc)",
        "explanation": "[verb]",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "to lie in bed"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sack",
        "question": "мешок",
        "explanation": "[noun] a large bag made of strong rough cloth or strong paper, used for storing or carrying flour, coal, vegetables etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a sack of potatoes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "tell me, please",
        "question": "подскажите мне, пожалуйста",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "inevitable",
        "question": "неизбежный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] certain to happen and impossible to avoid",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It was inevitable that his crime would be discovered."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Can you remind me what that job entails?",
        "question": "Не мог бы напомнить, что в себя включает эта работа? (can)",
        "explanation": "[verb] To entail is to involve. A job at a movie theater might entail sweeping popcorn off the floor, probably because watching a movie entails eating popcorn in the dark. It’s a small price to pay! The word entail, which comes from Latin, is connected to the idea of preconditions. If you want something, you better figure out what it entails. If it’s only 8 o’clock and you want to see a movie at 9, that will entail waiting for an hour. If you want to stay out of trouble, that will entail calling your parents and letting them know you're going to be late. That’s what being responsible entails! (have as a logical consequence)",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "punish",
        "question": "наказывать",
        "explanation": "[verb] To punish is to discipline or penalize someone because they've done something wrong. If you stole the cookie from the cookie jar, someone may have to punish you. Not you? Then who? A judge will often punish a guilty defendant with community service or parole — or sometimes even with time spent in prison, if the crime is serious enough. You probably punish your puppy for chewing your shoes simply with a firm \"No!\" Sometimes people are punished unfairly, like how higher gas prices punish the people who can already barely afford to drive to their jobs.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It’s unfair to punish a whole class for the actions of one or two students.",
            "I felt I was being punished for what my mother had done."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "aberration",
        "question": "отклонение от нормы",
        "explanation": "[noun] a departure from what is normal, usual, or expected, typically an unwelcome one",
        "source": "Word smart.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I see these activities as some kind of mental aberration."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "arrangement",
        "question": "приготовление",
        "explanation": "[noun] plans for how something will happen",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We're meeting tomorrow to discuss arrangements for the competition.",
            "I've made arrangements to go home this weekend."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "What month is the warmest in your city?",
        "question": "какой месяц самый теплый в вашем городе? (city)",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from. Certainly use which, not what, when there are only two choices, or if both speaker and listener can visualise all the items under consideration. Generally speaking, you can replace the usage of \"which” with \"what\" and be OK grammatically. It doesn’t always work the other way around, however. There needs to be a context of choice.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "scratch",
        "question": "царапать, оцарапать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to make a slight cut or long, thin mark with a sharp object",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I scratched myself on the roses.",
            "I’m afraid I’ve scratched your car."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "wet",
        "question": "мокрый",
        "explanation": "[adjective] covered in water or another liquid",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a wet towel"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i work at a bank",
        "question": "я работаю в банке",
        "explanation": " It means,  I work for a bank.",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "enthusiasm",
        "question": "энтузиазм",
        "explanation": "[noun] the feeling of being very interested in something and wanting very much to be involved in it",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She has always had a lot of enthusiasm for her work."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "image",
        "question": "изображение",
        "explanation": "[noun] a picture, especially on film or television or in a mirror",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The images on a computer screen are made up of thousands of tiny dots."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "may i invite you to the cinema?",
        "question": "разрешите пригласить вас в кино? (the cinema)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "awkward",
        "question": "неудобный, затруднительный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] rather difficult to deal with – used especially when something could be embarrassing",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an awkward customer",
            "an awkward question"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "May I help you?",
        "question": "Могу ли я вам помочь?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "season",
        "question": "время года",
        "explanation": "[noun] one of the four periods of the year; winter, spring, summer, or autumn",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "the effect on plants as the seasons start to change"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "You can reserve the tickets by phone.",
        "question": "Вы можете забронировать билеты по телефону. (can)",
        "explanation": "\"by\" is used to say what means or method someone uses to do something. \"with\" is used to say what tool is used to do something.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i study at a faculty of law",
        "question": "я учусь на юридическом факультете",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "How can I help you?",
        "question": "Чем я могу вам помочь?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "arrive",
        "question": "прибывать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to get to a place",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "When he first arrived in New York, he didn't speak a word of English.",
            "We were the last to arrive at the station.",
            "A letter arrived for you this morning."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "We have played.",
        "question": "Мы сыграли. (Present Perfect)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "April",
        "question": "апрель",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "spoon",
        "question": "лошка",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "brain",
        "question": "[Органы человека] мозг",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "accept our condolences",
        "question": "примите наши соболезнования",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "no change may be made without the consent of all the partners",
        "question": "никакое изменение не может быть сделано без согласия всех партнеров",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": false,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "how are your parents?",
        "question": "как родители?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "done in careless and lazy way",
        "question": "EXPLAIN: sloppy CONTEXT: It was a sloppy piece of work.",
        "explanation": "небрежный",
        "source": "code complete by steve mcconnell",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "we gave away a goal through sloppy defending."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "gather",
        "question": "собирать(ся) (группой)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to come together and form a group, or to make people do this",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Crowds of fans gathered at the stadium for the big match.",
            "Thousands of people gathered outside the embassy."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "ugly",
        "question": "уродливый",
        "explanation": "[adjective] extremely unattractive and unpleasant to look at",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a very ugly man",
            "the ugliest building in town"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "What country is he from?",
        "question": "Из какой он страны?",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from. Certainly use which, not what, when there are only two choices, or if both speaker and listener can visualise all the items under consideration.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my aunt",
        "question": "это моя тётя",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i study at a university",
        "question": "я учусь в университете",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "He got in the car and drove away.",
        "question": "Он сел в машину и уехал. (сам за рулем) (the car)",
        "explanation": "If you can walk onto it and stand up inside, you say “get on”. If not, you say “get in”. This rule is especially illustrated by vehicles where we could use either “in/out” or “on/off”, depending on the size of the vehicle. We normally say “get on an airplane” but if you have a small, single-engine airplane, you would normally say “get in”. The same goes for boats, where we get on a large ship, but get in a canoe. This is also true for helicopters, submarines and spaceships.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "in an hour",
        "question": "через час",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "August",
        "question": "август",
        "explanation": "the eighth month of the year",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "swimming pool",
        "question": "бассеин",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "may i make a suggestion? by all means",
        "question": "могу ли я сделать предложение? конечно (непременно)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Do not hurry.",
        "question": "Не спешите.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "decide",
        "question": "решать, принимать решение",
        "explanation": "[verb] to choose something after thinking about several possibilities",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I haven't decided whether or not to tell him.",
            "She's decided to take the job."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "a smaller enclosed space inside something larger",
        "question": "EXPLAIN: compartment CONTEXT: engine compartment",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "skull",
        "question": "[Скелет человека] череп",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "five minutes to nine",
        "question": "8.55- без пяти девять",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Can I pay in cash?",
        "question": "Могу я заплатить наличными?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "try",
        "question": "пытаться, делать попытку; стараться",
        "explanation": "[verb] to take action in order to do something that you may not be able to do",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Let’s have a rest and then we’ll try again."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "chicken",
        "question": "курица",
        "explanation": "[noun] a bird kept on a farm for its meat and eggs",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We never buy cheap frozen chicken."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Today it is cold outdoors.",
        "question": "Сегодня на улице холодно.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "traffic jam",
        "question": "пробка (в уличном движении)",
        "explanation": "a line of cars that have stopped, or are moving very slowly",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She spent two hours sitting in a traffic jam."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "tangerine",
        "question": "мандарин",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "proponent",
        "question": "(сторонник) (formal) a person who supports an idea or course of action",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone who supports something or persuades people to do something",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Steinem has always been a strong proponent of women’s rights.",
            "Dr George is one of the leading proponents of this view."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "radish",
        "question": "редиска",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Tomorrow it will be warm.",
        "question": "Завтра будет тепло.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "to get in line",
        "question": "встать в очередь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "She has an irritating habit of interrupting.",
        "question": "У нее есть раздражающая привычка перебивать.",
        "explanation": "[irritating] an irritating habit, situation etc keeps annoying you",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "diplomat",
        "question": "дипломат",
        "explanation": "an official representing a country abroad",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "What happened?",
        "question": "Что случилось?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Try to get into a routine",
        "question": "Попытайтесь придерживаться режима",
        "explanation": "[routine] the usual order in which you do things, or the things you regularly do",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Dressing is a task which we do every day as a matter of routine (=done regularly and not unusual)."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "the thing is",
        "question": "дело в том, что",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "membership",
        "question": "членство",
        "explanation": "[noun] the state of belonging to a group or an organization",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I've applied for membership of the union.",
            "a membership card"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "We will have played.",
        "question": "Мы сыграем (до определенного события в будущем, Future Perfect)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "at one o'clock",
        "question": "в час",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "enormous amount",
        "question": "огромное количество",
        "explanation": "[enormous] very big in size or in amount. Прилагательное enormous- \"огромный\" означает гораздо больший, чем обычно и употребляется с существительными, обозначающими размер, цену, количество.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an enormous amount of money",
            "An enormous building",
            "An enormous sum of money",
            "Enormous difference",
            "Enormous loss"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "she took off her jacket and hung it on a hanger",
        "question": "она сняла свой жакет и повесила его на вешалку",
        "explanation": " a shaped piece of wood, plastic, or metal with a hook at the top, from which clothes may be hung in order to keep them in shape.",
        "source": "Environment around you",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "then",
        "question": "тогда",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "game",
        "question": "игра",
        "explanation": "[noun] an entertaining activity or sport that people play, usually needing some skill and played according to rules",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a computer game",
            "Do you want to play a different game?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sustain",
        "question": "обеспечивать, содержать (для жизни или существования)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to support someone or something so that they can live or exist",
        "source": "Living with the gods: the protectoresses",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The money he received was hardly enough to sustain a wife and five children."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "way of life",
        "question": "образ жизни",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Shopping is an important part of the American way of life."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "severely punish",
        "question": "сурово наказывать",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Drug dealers are severely punished."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "to become less strong",
        "question": "EXPLAIN: abate CONTEXT: By the weekend, the storms had abated.",
        "explanation": "[verb, formal] (уменьшаться, ослабевать, утихать)",
        "source": "Word smart.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "date",
        "question": "финик",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "weekly",
        "question": "еженедельный, еженедельно",
        "explanation": "[adjective] happening once a week or every week",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a weekly newspaper",
            "We're paid weekly."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "to emphasize something",
        "question": "What is the purpose of the self word, myself, in the following sentence: I made the burrito all by myself.",
        "explanation": "The self words, myself, yourself, herself, himself, themselves, are used for two purposes: to emphasize something; to refer to someone already mentioned.",
        "source": "Woe is I Jr",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "health insurance",
        "question": "медицинское страхование",
        "explanation": "[insurance] an arrangement with a company in which you pay them money, especially regularly, and they pay the costs if something bad happens, for example if you become ill or your car is damaged",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Do you have insurance on your house and its contents?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "elusive",
        "question": "неуловимый, ускользающий",
        "explanation": "[adjective] difficult to describe, find, achieve, or remember",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The answers to these questions remain as elusive as ever.",
            "Success, however, remained elusive for her."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "a piece of writing or speech that gives details about what someone or something is like.",
        "question": "description (smn, smth)",
        "explanation": "[noun] A description puts something in words, like a portrait puts a person in paint.",
        "source": "Spaced rehearsal program readme.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The diary provides a clear description of farming life in the 1850s.",
            "Police have issued a description of the two men they are looking for. [issue a description (=formally give a description of someone to the public)]",
            "The book contains some vivid descriptions of his childhood. [vivid (=very clear and interesting)]"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "left-luggage office",
        "question": "камера хранения",
        "explanation": "(U.S: checkroom)",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I will pay for the tickets.",
        "question": "Я заплачу за билеты.",
        "explanation": "Do not use pay followed directly by a noun referring to the thing you are buying. Use pay (an amount of money) for something.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "aspect",
        "question": "аспект",
        "explanation": "[noun] one part of a situation, problem, subject, etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "His illness affects almost every aspect of his life."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "ruler",
        "question": "правитель",
        "explanation": "[someone such as a king or queen who has official power over a country or area]",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "runner",
        "question": "бегун",
        "explanation": "someone who runs for sport or pleasure",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a long-distance runner"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "head of a firm",
        "question": "глава фирмы",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sand",
        "question": "песок (мелкие частички камней и минералов)",
        "explanation": "[noun] a substance consisting of very small pieces of rocks and minerals, that forms beaches and deserts",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I have sand in my shoe."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Let's discuss this over dinner.",
        "question": "Давай обсудим это за обедом.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "assistant",
        "question": "помощник",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone whose job is to help a person who has a more important job",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "an administrative assistant",
            "assistant manager"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "millennium",
        "question": "тысячелетие",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "rude remark",
        "question": "грубое замечание",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "to think about something and try to decide what is true, what will happen, what you should do, etc.",
        "question": "EXPLAIN: wonder CONTEXT: ‘What should I do now?’ she wondered.",
        "explanation": "[verb]",
        "source": "The Oxford 3000",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We were wondering about next April for the wedding.",
            "I wonder who she is."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "addressing",
        "question": "обращение",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "How should I ask for a bill in a restaurant politely?",
        "question": "Как вежливо попросить счет в ресторане?",
        "explanation": "If you ask for something, it means that you want someone to give you something.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "bagel",
        "question": "бублик",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Weather forecast",
        "question": "Прогноз погоды",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "as I said before",
        "question": "как я уже говорил",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "overload",
        "question": "перегружать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to put too many things or people on or into something",
        "source": "software testing: a craftsman's approach",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Be careful not to overload the washing machine."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "beautiful bunch of flowers",
        "question": "красивый букет цветов",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Which bus goes downtown?",
        "question": "Какой автобус отправляется в центр города?",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from. Certainly use which, not what, when there are only two choices, or if both speaker and listener can visualise all the items under consideration.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "He gave up a permanent job in order to freelance.",
        "question": "Он отказался от постоянной работы, чтобы заниматься фрилансом.",
        "explanation": "[adjective] Something that’s permanent is constant and lasting, as opposed to temporary. Think twice about writing in permanent marker or getting a tattoo — both are just about impossible to erase. If you wait around for something permanent to change, you'll be there for a long time — maybe forever. That's because the adjective permanent is used to describe something that continues on into the foreseeable future without shifting, moving, or changing at all.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "permanent address",
            "Miller soon became a permanent fixture (=someone or something that is always there) on the team."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "by Wednesday",
        "question": "к среде",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "enclosed space",
        "question": "закрытое (замкнутое) пространство",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "no",
        "question": "нет",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ashamed",
        "question": "стыдиться",
        "explanation": "[adjective] feeling guilty or embarrassed about something you have done",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "You have got nothing to be ashamed of."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Acts of terrorism must not escape justice.",
        "question": "Акты терроризма не должны избежать правосудия.",
        "explanation": "[justice] (правосудие) the system by which people are judged in courts of law and criminals are punished",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "special occasion",
        "question": "особое событие (особый случай)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "entire",
        "question": "весь",
        "explanation": "[adjective] used when you want to emphasize that you mean all of a group, period of time, amount etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It was the worst day in my entire life.",
            "Have you drunk the entire bottle?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "wedding",
        "question": "свадьба",
        "explanation": "[noun] an official ceremony at which a man and woman get married",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a wedding dress"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am for it",
        "question": "я за",
        "explanation": "I am in favour of it [in support]",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Friday",
        "question": "пятница",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "mad",
        "question": "сумасшедший",
        "explanation": "[adjective] stupid or crazy",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "You're mad to walk home alone at night."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "obliterate",
        "question": "уничтожать [to destroy something completely so that nothing remains]",
        "explanation": "[verb, formal] It means to erase or destroy completely so that there is nothing left. Whatever you obliterate is completely gone.",
        "source": "A history of the world in 100 objects.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Hiroshima was nearly obliterated by the atomic bomb."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "decline",
        "question": "понижение, падение",
        "explanation": "[noun] a situation in which something becomes less in amount, importance, quality, or strength",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a steady decline in sales",
            "a rapid decline in unemployment"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i congratulate you on the holiday!",
        "question": "поздравляю вас с праздником!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my sister",
        "question": "это моя сестра",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "scientist",
        "question": "ученый",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone who studies science or works in science",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "gas",
        "question": "газ",
        "explanation": "[noun] a substance in a form like air and not solid or liquid",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "poisonous gases"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "abhor",
        "question": "питать отвращение, ненавидеть",
        "explanation": "[verb]",
        "source": "Word smart.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "he abhorred sexism in every form."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "notorious",
        "question": "пользующийся дурной славой",
        "explanation": "[adjective] famous for something bad",
        "source": "software testing: a craftsman's approach",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She was notorious for her bad temper.",
            "a notorious computer hacker"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my niece",
        "question": "это моя племянница",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "please, meet my wife",
        "question": "разрешите представить вам мою жену (неофициальная форма)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "tough",
        "question": "трудный, жесткий",
        "explanation": "[adjective] difficult; not easily damaged, cut, etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He's had a tough time at work recently.",
            "Children's shoes have to be tough.",
            "This meat's very tough."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my bridegroom",
        "question": "это мой жених",
        "explanation": "a man on his wedding day or just before and after the event",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "environment",
        "question": "окружающая среда",
        "explanation": "[noun] the air, land, and water where people, animals, and plants live",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The new road may cause damage to the environment."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "using very few words or including few details",
        "question": "brief (a brief description)",
        "explanation": "[adjective] \"in brief\" basically means in short or in summary. \"succinct\" is a bit different. It also implies clarity in the summary. Not just a summary but clear, understandable and to the point.",
        "source": "Spaced rehearsal program readme.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The president read a brief statement to reporters before boarding his plane.",
            "a brief description of the film"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "nut",
        "question": "орех",
        "explanation": "[noun] the dry fruit of some trees that grows in a hard shell, and can often be eaten",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "We were sitting round the fire cracking nuts (=opening them).",
            "roasted nuts"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "own",
        "question": "свой собственный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] belonging to or done by a particular person or thing",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Each student has their own dictionary.",
            "\"Is that your mum's car?\" \"No, it's my own (= it belongs to me).\""
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "mental",
        "question": "умственный",
        "explanation": "relating to the health or state of someone’s mind",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Stress has an effect on both your physical and mental health.",
            "The centre provides help for people suffering from mental illness."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "run",
        "question": "бежать",
        "explanation": "to move very quickly, by moving your legs more quickly than when you walk",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I ran down the stairs as fast as I could."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "ice cream",
        "question": "мороженое",
        "explanation": "[noun] a sweet food made from frozen milk or cream and sugar",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "chocolate/vanilla ice cream"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "vague idea",
        "question": "смутное представление",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Which one of your sisters is the singer?",
        "question": "Какая из ваших сестер певица?",
        "explanation": "“What” is used to ask a question when there are an unknown number or infinite possibilities for an answer. You can use “which” when you have a very small or limited field to choose from. Certainly use which, not what, when there are only two choices, or if both speaker and listener can visualise all the items under consideration.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "lawyer",
        "question": "юрист",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "this year",
        "question": "в этом году",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "What is the weather like today?",
        "question": "Какая сегодня погода?",
        "explanation": null,
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "We had played.",
        "question": "Мы сыграли (до определенного события в прошлом, Past Perfect)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "are you married?",
        "question": "вы женаты (замужем)?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "When I got married, I had been studying art for 8 years.",
        "question": "Когда я поженился, я изучал искусство в течение 8 лет.",
        "explanation": "\"Had been\" is the past perfect tense and is used in all cases, singular and plural. The past perfect tense refers to something that began in the past and was still true at another time that also was in the past. So, if I began studying art when I was 13, and I got married when I was 21, and now I am 55, I could say \"When I got married, I had been studying art for 8 years.\" The \"when I got married\" part identifies a specific time in the past, and the \"had been studying for 8 years\" says that the studying was still going on at another time that is alos in the past. Note that it does not matter, in this case, whether I am still studying art in the present- the sentence is correct either way.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i disagree",
        "question": "я не согласен",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "pedestrian crossing",
        "question": "пешеходный переход",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I parked in the car park next to the hospital.",
        "question": "Я припарковался на автостоянке рядом с больницей.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "attempt",
        "question": "попытка",
        "explanation": "[noun] If you make an attempt to do something, you try to do it.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "This is his second attempt at the exam.",
            "They closed the road in an attempt to reduce traffic in the city.",
            "She made no attempt (= did not try) to be sociable."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "jar of strawberry jam",
        "question": "банка с клубничным вареньем",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "her name is",
        "question": "ёе зовут",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "specific way",
        "question": "конкретный способ",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "advice",
        "question": "совет",
        "explanation": "[noun] suggestions about what you think someone should do or how they should do something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She asked me for advice about writing a book.",
            "I took your advice (= did what you suggested) and went home early.",
            "Can I give you a piece of advice?",
            "There's a booklet giving advice on how to set up your own club."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "reconcile",
        "question": "restore friendly relations between (примирять)",
        "explanation": "she wanted to be reconciled with her father",
        "source": "Living With The Gods (bbc radio 4)",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "how old are you?",
        "question": "сколька вам лет?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my brother",
        "question": "это мой брат",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "may i ask you?",
        "question": "можно вас попросить?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "rubber",
        "question": "резина",
        "explanation": "a strong material that bends easily, originally produced from the juice of a tropical tree, and used to make tyres, boots, etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a rubber ball"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "reduce speed",
        "question": "снизить скорость",
        "explanation": "[speed] the rate at which something moves or travels",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The truck was travelling at a speed of 50 mph.",
            "She reduced speed as she approached the village."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am a student",
        "question": "я студент",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i congratulate you on birth of the son!",
        "question": "поздравляю вас с рождением сына!",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "mango",
        "question": "манго",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my nephew",
        "question": "это мой племянник",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "in a hurry",
        "question": "в спешке",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am staying at my friends",
        "question": "я остановился у друзей",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "impatient",
        "question": "нетерпеливый",
        "explanation": "[adjective] wanting something to happen as soon as possible",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "People are increasingly impatient for change in this country."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "on the other hand",
        "question": "с другой стороны",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "musician",
        "question": "музыкант",
        "explanation": "a person who plays a musical instrument, especially as a profession, or is musically talented.",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "this is my daughter-in-law",
        "question": "это моя невестка",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "by the way",
        "question": "кстати",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "something or someone that is elusive is difficult to find, describe, remember or achieve",
        "question": "EXPLAIN: elusive CONTEXT: success will become ever more elusive. (smth, smn)",
        "explanation": "[adjective] неуловимый, уклончивый",
        "source": "Complexity: a guided tour (melanie mitchell).",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "sense of pride",
        "question": "чувства гордости",
        "explanation": "[phrase] The people have a sense of pride in their community.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Today is Wednesday",
        "question": "Сегодня среда",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "compartment",
        "question": "отсек, отделение, купе",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "permanent employment",
        "question": "постоянное трудоустройство (постоянная работа)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "cure",
        "question": "лекарство, лечение",
        "explanation": "something that makes someone with an illness healthy again",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "They are trying to find a cure for cancer."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "tasty",
        "question": "вкусный",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "to leave a hotel after paying and returning your room key.",
        "question": "EXPLAIN: check out CONTEXT: hotel",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "any extra charges will be settled with guests on check-out."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "i study at the Royal Academy.",
        "question": "я учусь в Королевской академии.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ankle",
        "question": "щиколотка",
        "explanation": "[noun] the part of your leg that is just above your foot",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Two women got out of the taxi.",
        "question": "Две женщины вышли из такси.",
        "explanation": "If you can walk onto it and stand up inside, you say “get on”. If not, you say “get in”. This rule is especially illustrated by vehicles where we could use either “in/out” or “on/off”, depending on the size of the vehicle. We normally say “get on an airplane” but if you have a small, single-engine airplane, you would normally say “get in”. The same goes for boats, where we get on a large ship, but get in a canoe. This is also true for helicopters, submarines and spaceships.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "adventure",
        "question": "приключение",
        "explanation": "[noun] an exciting and sometimes dangerous experience",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "It's a film about the adventures of two friends travelling across Africa."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "you are three years older than me",
        "question": "вы старше меня на три года",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "whipped cream",
        "question": "взбитые сливки",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "village",
        "question": "деревня",
        "explanation": "[noun] a very small town in the countryside",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a little fishing village"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "congratulation",
        "question": "поздравление",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "diminish",
        "question": "to deliberately make someone or something appear less important or valuable than they really are",
        "explanation": "Don't let him diminish your achievements. I don't wish to diminish the importance of their contribution",
        "source": "",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "letter",
        "question": "письмо (a written message that you send to someone, usually by post)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I got a letter from Paul this morning."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "whimsical",
        "question": "причудливый (unusual and strange in a way that might be funny or annoying)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "Living With The Gods (bbc radio 4)",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I would like to get a return ticket for tomorrow.",
        "question": "Я хотел бы получить обратный билет на завтра.",
        "explanation": "We use “would like” or “‘d like to” to say politely what we want, especially when making offers or requests. Verbs that follow would like are in the to-infinitive form.",
        "source": "English phrase book (postscript).",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "polish",
        "question": "полировать",
        "explanation": "[verb] the act of rubbing something in order to make it clean and shiny",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I spent all afternoon polishing the silver."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "December",
        "question": "декабрь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "receive",
        "question": "получать (It is a rather formal word, which is used especially in written English. In everyday English, people usually use \"get\".)",
        "explanation": "[verb] Receive means to get or accept. On your birthday you might receive many presents. If you have a huge formal party that night, you'll stand in a \"receiving line,\" where you'll greet or receive your guests.Unless you're receiving good news or a stiff reprimand, receive can be pretty great. If one of your gifts is a trip to a spa, you might receive the news with pleasure, and then, when you go to the spa, receive several treatments. And remember, receive is one of those words that you have to say \"I before E, except after C, or when sounding like \"A\" as in neighbor or weigh\" before knowing how to spell it.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "All the children will receive a small gift.",
            "She received an honorary degree from Harvard."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "radiator",
        "question": "радиатор (отопления зданий)",
        "explanation": "[noun] a thin metal container that is fastened to a wall and through which hot water passes to provide heat for a room",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Turn off the central heating so that radiators cool."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "precarious",
        "question": "зависящий от непредвиденных обстоятельств",
        "explanation": " dependent on chance; uncertain",
        "source": "Living With The Gods (bbc radio 4)",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "ocean waves",
        "question": "океанские волны",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "why are you late? did the bus break down?",
        "question": "почему ты опоздал? сломался автобус?",
        "explanation": "break down means 'to stop working because of a fault'. Machines and vehicles can break down.",
        "source": "Really learn 100 phrasal verbs",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "vehicle",
        "question": "транспортное средство",
        "explanation": "[noun] formal a machine with an engine that is used to take people or things from one place to another, such as a car, bus, or truck",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a description of the stolen vehicle",
            "Have you locked your vehicle?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "pea",
        "question": "горох",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "avoid",
        "question": "избегать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to stay away from a person, place, situation, etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Try to avoid the city centre."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "exhaust",
        "question": "изнурять",
        "explanation": "[verb] [tired] to make someone very tired",
        "source": "From Frequency to Meaning: Vector Space Models of Semantics.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "in my spare time",
        "question": "в мое свободное время",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "parsley",
        "question": "петрушка",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "onion",
        "question": "лук",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "immediate family",
        "question": "ближайшие родственники",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "venture",
        "question": "рискованное предприятие, рискованное начинание",
        "explanation": "[noun] a new business activity that involves taking risks",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a business venture"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Does that sound all right to you?",
        "question": "Фраза \"Would that be okay with you?\" спрашивает разрешения на согласие и используется в формальной обстановке. Необходимо написать фразу, которая пременима в неформальном общении, например с близким человеком или другом.",
        "explanation": "We can also use other phrases such as: Does that sound acceptable? Does that work for you?",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "as a rule",
        "question": "обычно, как правило",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "having lived or existed for only a short time and not old",
        "question": "EXPLAIN: young CONTEXT: young children",
        "explanation": "[adjective]",
        "source": "The Oxford 3000",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He’s younger than me.",
            "When I was young, I wanted to be a model.",
            "John was a great footballer in his younger days (=when he was younger)."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "response",
        "question": "отклик (ответ), реакция",
        "explanation": "[noun] A response is a reaction to a question, experience, or some other type of stimulus. If you cry at sad movies, you're having an emotional response to the drama that's taking place on the screen. A response can come in many forms, including an answer to a question, an emotional reaction, or a reply. If a teacher asks, \"Who invented the phonograph?\" She hopes her students will give her the response, \"Why, Thomas Edison, of course!\" When a parent tells a child not to cross the street when the light is red, he hopes the response will be compliance.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The exhibition has received a positive response from visitors."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "I decided to delay my departure by a few days.",
        "question": "Я решил отложить отъезд на несколько дней.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "soon",
        "question": "скоро",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "owner",
        "question": "владелец",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone who legally owns something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a property owner"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "with regard to",
        "question": "что касается",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "baggage",
        "question": "багаж (has a greater scope of meaning)",
        "explanation": "[noun] the cases, bags, boxes etc carried by someone who is travelling",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "What happens if my baggage gets lost?"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "What is your mother like?",
        "question": "Как выглядит твоя мама?",
        "explanation": null,
        "source": "",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Please show me on the map.",
        "question": "Пожалуйста покажите мне на карте.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "jam",
        "question": "варенье",
        "explanation": "[noun] a sweet food made from fruit that you spread on bread",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "strawberry jam"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "what is your name?",
        "question": "как вас зовут?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "i am single",
        "question": "я холост",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "cup",
        "question": "чашка",
        "explanation": "[noun] a small, round container with a handle on the side, used to drink from",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a cup of tea/coffee"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "travel",
        "question": "путешествие",
        "explanation": "[noun] to go from one place to another, or to several places, especially ones that are far away",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Someday I’d like to travel abroad.",
            "We’re planning to travel across America this summer."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "roll up the sleeves",
        "question": "закатать рукава (засучить рукава)",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "mutual trust",
        "question": "взаимное доверие",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "pour juice into a cup",
        "question": "Налейте сок в чашку",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "identity",
        "question": "личность (человек как юридическое лицо)",
        "explanation": "[noun] someone’s identity is their name or who they are",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The true identity of the author was not revealed until 100 years later."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "as well as",
        "question": "так же, как и",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "How is your mother?",
        "question": "Как твоя мама? (вопрос о ее здоровье)",
        "explanation": null,
        "source": "",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "maintain",
        "question": "поддерживать, сохранять (ситуацию или активность)",
        "explanation": "[verb] to make a situation or activity continue in the same way",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The army has been brought in to maintain order in the region.",
            "A lot depends on building and maintaining a good relationship with your customers."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "abuse",
        "question": "злоупотребление",
        "explanation": "[noun] the use of something for the wrong purpose in a way that is harmful or morally wrong",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "drug/alcohol abuse",
            "abuse of public money"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "overlook",
        "question": "in amsterdam's old buildings the apartments ... a garden or court may be divided from those ... the street",
        "explanation": "have a view of from above",
        "source": "The diary of a young girl by Anne Frank ",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "I got on the train at Bristol.",
        "question": "Я сел в поезд в Бристоле. (use at, Bristol)",
        "explanation": "If you can walk onto it and stand up inside, you say “get on”. If not, you say “get in”. This rule is especially illustrated by vehicles where we could use either “in/out” or “on/off”, depending on the size of the vehicle. We normally say “get on an airplane” but if you have a small, single-engine airplane, you would normally say “get in”. The same goes for boats, where we get on a large ship, but get in a canoe. This is also true for helicopters, submarines and spaceships.",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "annoy",
        "question": "раздражать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to make someone slightly angry",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "He's always late and it's starting to annoy me."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "turnip",
        "question": "[vegetable] репа",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Get well soon.",
        "question": "Поправляйся скорее",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "refusal",
        "question": "отказ",
        "explanation": "when you say firmly that you will not do, give, or accept something",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "His refusal to pay the fine got him into even more trouble.",
            "They couldn’t understand her refusal of a scholarship to Yale."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "We want a secure future for our children.",
        "question": "Мы хотим безопасного будущего для наших детей.",
        "explanation": "[secure] (безопасный, защищенный) safe from danger",
        "source": "The oxford 3000 words.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "I don't feel that the house is secure."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "announce",
        "question": "анонсировать",
        "explanation": "[verb] to officially tell people about something, especially about a plan or a decision",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The government has announced plans to create 10,000 new jobs."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "sore",
        "question": "болезненный, воспаленный",
        "explanation": "[adjective] painful, especially when touched",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Her eyes were red and sore."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "midnight",
        "question": "полночь",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Today it is cool outdoors.",
        "question": "Сегодня на улице прохладно.",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "may i offer you a cup of coffee?",
        "question": "можно предложить вам чашечку кофе?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "That is an interesting question.",
        "question": "Это интересный вопрос.",
        "explanation": "[interesting] if something is interesting, you give it your attention because it seems unusual or exciting or provides information that you did not know about",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a really interesting TV programme"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "pumpkin",
        "question": "тыква",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "downturn",
        "question": "спад (экономический, бизнесовый, итд)",
        "explanation": "[noun] a decline in economic, business, or other activity",
        "source": "Highlights of calculus.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a downturn in the housing market."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "ban",
        "question": "запрещать (to say officially that people must not do or have something)",
        "explanation": "[verb] an official order that prevents something from being used or done",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "A lot of people think boxing should be banned.",
            "Ian has been banned from driving for 2 years."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "slab",
        "question": "плита (бетонная плита)",
        "explanation": "a large, thick, flat piece of stone or concrete, typically square or rectangular in shape: paving slabs",
        "source": "Living with the Gods: Here Comes the Sun.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "when?",
        "question": "когда?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "what time?",
        "question": "в котором часу?",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "kitchen appliances",
        "question": "кухонные приборы",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "Please close the curtains.",
        "question": "пожалуйста задерни шторы",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "barman",
        "question": "бармен",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "title",
        "question": "заглавие, название (book, film, etc.)",
        "explanation": "[noun] the name of a book, film, etc",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "The title of this play (пьесы) is ‘Othello’."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "Change bed linen, please",
        "question": "Смените пожалуйста, постельное бельё.",
        "explanation": "[uncountable]",
        "source": "English phrase book.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "such as",
        "question": "как например",
        "explanation": "",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "to pass information, knowledge to other people",
        "question": "impart sth to sb",
        "explanation": "[verb] (formal) сообща́ть, передава́ть (знания, новости)",
        "source": "Genetic algorithms with python (Clinton Sheppard)",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "She had information that she couldn’t wait to impart.",
            "These people are unable to impart positive life values to their children because they have none to impart."
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "My offer of help still stands.",
        "question": "Мое предложение о помощи все еще в силе.",
        "explanation": "[still stand] if a decision, offer etc stands, it continues to exist, be correct, or be valid",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "Does your invitation still stand? (Твое приглашение еще в силе?)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "tool",
        "question": "инструмент (ручной)",
        "explanation": "[noun] a piece of equipment that you use with your hands in order to help you do something",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "a shop selling garden tools"
        ]
    },
    {
        "answer": "announcer",
        "question": "диктор",
        "explanation": "a person who announces something, in particular someone who introduces or gives information about programmes on radio or television",
        "source": "English phrase book",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": []
    },
    {
        "answer": "available",
        "question": "доступный, имеющийся в продаже",
        "explanation": "[adjective] If something is available, you can use it or get it.",
        "source": "The oxford 3000.",
        "is_ready_to_add": true,
        "created": false,
        "examples": [
            "This information is available free on the Internet.",
            "The new drug is not yet available to the public."
        ]
    }
]